<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The additional articles in Pope Pius's creed, no articles of the Christian faith being an answer to a late pamphlet intituled, Pope Pius his profession of faith vindicated from novelty in additional articles, and the prospect of popery, taken from that authentick record, with short notes thereupon, defended.</title>
            <author>Altham, Michael, 1633-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 265 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18073</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12039456</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12039456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52954</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25225)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52954)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 47:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The additional articles in Pope Pius's creed, no articles of the Christian faith being an answer to a late pamphlet intituled, Pope Pius his profession of faith vindicated from novelty in additional articles, and the prospect of popery, taken from that authentick record, with short notes thereupon, defended.</title>
                  <author>Altham, Michael, 1633-1705.</author>
                  <author>Altham, Michael, 1633-1705. Creed of Pope Pius IV, or, A prospect of popery taken from that authentick record.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.L. for Luke Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pius --  IV, --  Pope, 1499-1565.</term>
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Pope Pius his profession of faith vindicated from novelty in additional articles.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Creeds.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Council of Trent (1545-1563). --  Canones et decreta.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52954:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52954:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Additional Articles</hi> IN Pope Pius'<hi rend="sup">s</hi> Creed, NO ARTICLES OF THE CHRISTIAN FAITH. BEING AN ANSWER To a Late PAMPHLET, Intituled, <hi>Pope</hi> PIUS <hi>his profeſſion of Faith Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from Novelty in Additional Articles.</hi> AND The PROSPECT of <hi>POPERY,</hi> taken from that Authentick Record, with ſhort <hi>NOTES</hi> thereupon, DEFENDED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. L.</hi> for <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:52954:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Needham,</hi> R. R. in Chriſto P. ac D. D. <hi>Whilhelmo</hi> Archiep. <hi>Cantuar.</hi> à Sacr. Domeſt.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Mart.</hi> 22. 1677/8.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52954:2"/>
            <head>THE ADDITIONAL ARTICLES IN Pope Pius'<hi rend="sup">s</hi> Creed, NO ARTICLES OF THE CHRISTIAN FAITH.</head>
            <p>AMONG thoſe many and great grievances which we complain of in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Additional Articles of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. are none of the leaſt. We look upon them as Additions to the ancient Faith, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed with great ſeverity, and as Novelties introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into the Church, without any Authority. But the Vindicator tells us, That though we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> be the moſt forward; yet we, of all ſorts of Chriſtians, have the leaſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to condemn this Prelate for this Addition; who, for XXIV. Articles in his Profeſſion, have XXXIX. in our own. If this were true, or the Additions were of the ſame kind, this Remarque of his might paſs among thinking Men, as very conſiderable. But had this Gentleman been ſo Thinking a perſon as he would make the World believe he is, he would not have been guilty of ſo great a Blunder; he would have ſeen a vaſt difference between Articles of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52954:3"/> 
               <hi>Faith,</hi> and Articles of <hi>Communion.</hi> We do not find fault with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any particular Church, or any Society of Men, whether Sacred or Civil, for making Laws and Rules to govern themſelves by, or framing Articles, upon compliance wherewith they will admit into, or acknowledge any one to be a Member of their Society; provided they be ſuch as may be complied with, without Sin and Danger. But we deny, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, or the Catholick Church it ſelf hath any Authority to make new Articles of Faith, or declare any thing as neceſſary to be Believed in order to Man's Salvation, which was not ſo antecedent to ſuch Declaration. And this I take to be the true ſtate of the Queſtion between us and the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and not as the Vindicator ſtates it, <hi>Whether there be Authority in the Catholick Church of Chriſt, which<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it be, to make any Addition of Articles to the Apoſtles Creed, and require other terms of Communion, beſides the aſſenting to what is expreſſed in that Symbol?</hi> Upon this miſtaken Queſtion the Vindicator proceeds, and all along fights with his own ſhadow, nor with us; for all that we ſay is only this, <hi>That no new Articles of Faith ought to be added to the Apoſtles Creed;</hi> but we never denied, That other terms of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, beſides the aſſenting to what is expreſſed in that Symbol, may, by any Church, be required of Her Members. Unleſs therefore the Vindicator do make it appear, That new Articles of Faith, <hi>de jure,</hi> may be, or, <hi>de facto,</hi> have been, by conſent of the Catholick Church, added to the Apoſtles Creed; he will not at all impugn the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor will the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be much indebted to him for his Vindication. Now, whether he doth, or hath made this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, will beſt be ſeen, by taking his Inſtances into Conſideration, by which he pretends and endeavours to do it. But before I do that, it may be convenient to acquaint you what is the juſt and true diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between Articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> and Articles of <hi>Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> I take to be certain Propoſitions, containing ſuch divine Verities as are neceſſary to be believed and aſſented to by all Chriſtians, in order to their Salvation.</p>
            <p>Articles of <hi>Communion,</hi> I take to be ſome certain Laws or Rules agreed upon and eſtabliſhed by ſome particular Society of Chriſtians; a compliance wherewith is neceſſary to the admittance of any one as a Member of that Society, and an Obſervance whereof is neceſſary to the Peace, Order, and good Government of that Society.</p>
            <p>The former of theſe are certain Fundamental Verities, taught us by God, revealed in the holy Scriptures, and ſummarily comprized in the Apoſtles Creed. For this we have the Authority of the <hi>Trent</hi> Catechiſm,<note n="*" place="margin">Catech. ad Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chos par. 1. Tit. de 12. Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis, n. 1.</note> and therefore may reaſonably ſuppoſe that it will not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52954:3"/> be diſowned by thoſe of the Roman <hi>Communion.</hi> And if this be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then methinks the Conſequence is plain, That whatſoever is not contained in the Apoſtles Creed, is not to be admitted as an Article of Faith. For there are many Truths revealed by God in holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, all which, when known to be ſo revealed, are neceſſary to be believed; yet are they not all of equal neceſſity to Salvation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently not to be admitted as Articles of Faith in the ſtrict and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per acceptation of the Word.</p>
            <p>The latter are things of a quite different nature, reſpecting prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the Peace, Order, and good Government of ſome particular Society, neceſſary to be aſſented to and obſerved by all the Members thereof, but not by all Chriſtians. For there are great Numbers of Eccleſiaſtical Societies in the World, all or moſt of which have diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent terms of Communion, which the Members of every particular Society are obliged to comply with; but the Members of one Society are not under the ſame Obligation to obſerve the Conſtitutions of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they are to do thoſe of their own.</p>
            <p>The Catholick Church, we know, is divided into ſeveral particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches, differing in the terms of their Communion; and yet none will deny, but that the terms of Communion in each particular Church are to be obſerved, in order to thoſe ends before mentioned, by the reſpective Members of thoſe ſeveral Churches. 'Tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that all thoſe particular Churches are Members of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and do, or ought to hold Communion with her in Faith and Worſhip, and upon the ſame terms with one another: But as to what relates to the admitting of Members into, or caſting them out of their Society, they have different terms, and always have had without blame, and without any the leaſt breach of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Communion.</p>
            <p>But to bring the Inſtance a little nearer, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which calls her ſelf Catholick, hath many particular Societies within her ſelf, as the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits, &amp;c.</hi> all which have particular Laws and Rules, and thoſe different from one another, which are the Bands and Ligaments of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Societies. And yet the Vindicator will not deny, but that they are all true Members of the Church, and do hold Communion with her, and with one another, notwithſtanding thoſe different terms of Communion among themſelves.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, you may eaſily obſerve a vaſt difference between theſe two ſorts of Articles, which difference I ſhall briefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulate to you in theſe Four particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Church Communion,</hi> it is plain, is of two ſorts, either with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52954:4"/> the Catholick, or with a particular Church. Now it muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, That Articles of Faith properly ſo called, are really terms of Communion with the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> for by our Profeſſion of them it is, that we are look'd upon as Chriſtians, and own'd as members of the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> But they are not, nor cannot be the only terms of Communion with any particular Church; for it is not by owning and aſſenting to the terms of Communion with any particular Church, that we are called Chriſtians, but only Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of ſuch or ſuch a Denomination, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> We are upon our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with ſuch terms, look'd upon as Members of ſuch a particular Society of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Articles of Faith</hi> properly ſo called, are certain Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Verities, revealed by God in holy Scripture, and ſummarily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed:</hi> But meer Articles of Communion with any particular Church, are no fundamental Verities of Religion, though they may be fundamental Conſtitutions of a Society; nor is it neceſſary that they ſhould all be revealed by God, but may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by Men; and certain it is, that all of them never were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized either in the Apoſtles, or any other ancient <hi>Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Articles of Faith</hi> are the ſame to all Chriſtians, being ſuch fundamental Verities as all ought to believe and aſſent thereunto. But <hi>Articles of Communion</hi> are various, each Community having different terms of Communion from another; ſo that the Members of one Society, though they ſtand obliged to comply with, obſerve, and aſſent unto the terms of Communion eſtabliſhed and required of them by their own Body, yet are they not any way obliged to comply with, obſerve, or aſſent unto the terms of Communion required in another.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Articles of Faith</hi> are certain fundamental Verities, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be believed and aſſented to by all Chriſtians, in order to their Salvation. but <hi>Articles of Communion,</hi> as ſuch, are not neceſſary to the Salvation of Men, but only to the Peace, Order, and good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a Society. For a Member of one Society may be ſafe and ſaved at laſt, without complying with the terms of Communion eſtabliſhed by another.</p>
            <p>Having thus repreſented to you the difference between theſe two ſorts of Articles, I ſhall now proceed to conſider the Vindicator's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, by which he endeavours to prove, That it is in the power of the Church to add unto the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> not only other <hi>Articles of Communion,</hi> beſides the aſſenting to what is expreſſed in that Symbol, but alſo other <hi>Articles of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His firſt Inſtance is, The acknowledged practice of the Primitive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52954:4"/> Church, in the time of her confeſſed Purity. This is a mighty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and if he can make any thing of it to evince the Addition of any new Article of Faith to the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> in that time, he will do a great Work; for we own there is a great deal of difference due to the practice of the Primitive Church in that time. But inſtead of ſo doing, he acknowledgeth that the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> was the only ſummary of the Chriſtian Faith known in the firſt Three hundred Years. And if ſo, then the Church, in all that time, never thought it neceſſary to add any new Article thereunto. But after this time, ſaith he, upon occaſion of the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie, another <hi>Creed</hi> was compoſed by the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> with an expreſs condemnation and deteſtation of that new broach'd Error, in the Addition of theſe Words, in relation to the Divinity of the Son; <hi>I believe in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">For <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>born of his Father before all Worlds, God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God, begotten not made, conſubſtantial to the Father.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the expreſs aſſenting to this Addition, none could be admitted to Ordination, or be acknowledged as Members of the Church. Which <hi>Creed,</hi> with this Addition, was received by the whole Church, and Subſcription to it is required by the Church of <hi>England, Art.</hi> VIII.</p>
            <p>Here this Gentleman, as he thinks, hath found a conſiderable Addition to the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and that made by no leſs Authority than that of the Famous Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> But certainly never any Thinking Man beſides himſelf ever thought this to be an Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to, but only an Explication of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> or a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what was the Sence of the Church in thoſe Three hundred Years preceding, touching that Article of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed.</hi> And whereas he ſaith, <hi>That without the expreſs Aſſenting to this Addition,</hi> (as he calls it) <hi>none could be admitted to Ordination, or be acknowledg'd as Members of the Church:</hi> It is very true, but little to his purpoſe; for what doth this import? but only that an Aſſent to this Explication was required as a term of Communion, but not that it ſhould be owned as a new Article of Faith. And whereas he further ſaith, <hi>That this Creed, with this Addition, was received by the whole Church, and a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to it is now required by the Church of England,</hi> Art. VIII. It is very true, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the ſame Article will tell him upon what Grounds ſhe now doth, and the Church then did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this <hi>Creed.</hi> The Three <hi>Creeds, Nice Creed, Athanaſius</hi>'s <hi>Creed,</hi> and that which is commonly called the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> ought through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be received and believed; for they may be proved by moſt certain Warrants of holy Scripture. So that upon the whole matter, it is very evident, That the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> makes no new Article, but only explains an old one.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52954:5"/>
            <p>The ſame Anſwer may ſerve to his two next Inſtances out of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinopolitan Creeds,</hi> in which, upon like Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, we meet with Explications of ſome other Articles of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed;</hi> but no Addition of any new Article thereunto.</p>
            <p>But our Vindicator, being a mighty Thinking Man, hath found out a way not only of confounding Articles of Faith with Articles of Communion, but alſo of jumbling Additions and Explications toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as if they were one and the ſame thing. And if you will allow this Iſſue of his ſo pregnant Thoughts, you ſhall not want a Vindication of the moſt abſurd Doctrines, and irregular Practices in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but if you deny him this, you take away the Foundation he is to build upon, and then it would be unreaſonable for you to expect any good and durable Superſtructure from him.</p>
            <p>This is plain from his next Inſtance, which is taken from the XXXIX. Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in which (he ſaith) are many particular Points not found in the Symbol of the Apoſtles, nor yet in any of the forementioned <hi>Creeds</hi> of the Primitive Church. Whence he concludes, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath greater variety, and a greater number of Additional Atticles than the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> To make good which concluſion, he muſt, according to his new way of Thinking, take all the Articles of our Church to be Articles of Faith ſtrictly and properly ſo called, as neceſſary to be received and believed by all Men, in order to their Salvation, (as the Articles of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV.<note place="margin">Bulla Pii 4ti. apud Concil. Trid.</note> are declared to be) or elſe the force of his Argument is quite loſt. For if they be only Articles of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſuch as are neceſſary only for our admittance into, and our peaceable and orderly living in that Society, of which we are Members; then are they no Additions to the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> which only contains Articles of Faith. And that they are ſo, will evidently appear, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be but allowed to ſpeak for her ſelf.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> VI.</note> She will tell us, That the Holy Scripture contains all things neceſſary to Salvation; ſo that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any Man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Salvation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> VIII.</note> And ſhe will further tells us, That the Three <hi>Creeds,</hi> the <hi>Nicene,</hi> the <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> and that commonly called the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> ought throughly to be received and believed; for they may be proved by moſt certain Warrants of holy Scripture. But when ſhe ſpeaks of her own Articles, ſhe tells us, they were agreed upon, and deſigned for this end and purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> For the avoiding of diverſities of Opinions, and for the eſtabliſhing of Conſent touching true Religion. It is a ſcandal therefore upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52954:5"/> to ſay, that ſhe ever thought it lawful to add to the Apoſtles Creed; or that it was in hers, or in the power of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of all the Churches in the World to make or coin any one new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith. Which if it be true, then will it be a very hard task indeed to juſtifie Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. who hath added XII. new Articles, as neceſſary to be received and believed by all Men in order to their Salvation. To bring off this Prelate as well as he can, our Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator tells us, That theſe Articles were collected by him at that time in oppoſition to the then broach'd Errors of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin;</hi> that in ſo doing he is warranted by Primitive practices; and that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles do not contain any new Doctrine, but only a Declaration of that, to be the true and Orthodox Doctrine of the Church, which was really ſo antecedent to that Declaration. And therefore (ſaith he) We have now only to enquire, <hi>Whether the Doctrine propos'd in the profeſſion of</hi> Pius IV. <hi>be according to Scripture, and the ſence of the Primitive Fathers?</hi> if it be not, they do well that reject it; but if it be, the noiſe of Additional Articles will be but a weak juſtification of thoſe, that have made a breach in the Church on this ſcore.</p>
            <p>That theſe Articles were collected in oppoſition to ſome pretended Errors of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> and that it was the practice of the Primitive Church, when any Error or Hereſie was raiſed againſt any point of received Doctrine, to condemn the Error or Hereſie and the Abettors of them, and to declare the oppoſed Doctrine to be Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, is readily granted: But <hi>Whether the Doctrine delivered in theſe Articles be new or old,</hi> is the thing now in queſtion. The Vindicator undertakes to prove that it is according to Scripture, and the Sence of the Primitive Fathers; which, if he do, then we muſt own our ſelves to blame; but if he fail in it, then, notwithſtanding this his Vindication, he muſt, if he be ingenuous, acknowledge that we have juſt cauſe to withdraw from their Communion upon that ſcore.</p>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <head>The Profeſſion of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV.</head>
               <q>I ſteadfaſtly admit and embrace Apoſtolical and Eccleſiaſtical Traditions, and other Obſervances and Conſtitutions of the Church.</q>
               <p>IN this Article there are III. things which we are required to admit and embrace: I. Apoſtolical Traditions. II. Eccleſiaſtical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. III. Other Obſervances and Conſtitutions of the Church.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52954:6"/>
               <p>As for the firſt of theſe, <hi>viz. Traditions</hi> truly <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally own'd for obligatory through all ages, we are ready with all due Veneration and profound Reverence to admit and embrace them. We are well aſſured that the Apoſtles were Men divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, and whatſoever Doctrine was delivered by them, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Rules of practice they, did preſcribe to be perpetually obſerved in the Church, were no leſs than the Dictates of unerring Wiſdom; and therefore to contravene or not comply with them, if they be ſufficiently propounded to us, would be great impiety. But if we do not receive every thing as a Tradition truly Apoſtolical, which is pretended to be ſo, we ought to be excuſed by the Impoſers. If we are told, as we have been by ſome of the Romiſh Writers, That the whole Canon, word by word, as it is now uſed in the Maſs, came directly from the Apoſtles: Or, That the Apoſtles appointed their Orders of Monks: Or, That Chriſt was the Captain and Standard-bearer of Monaſtick life: Or, That private Maſs, Half-Communion, Purgatory, Pardons, Indulgences, and I know not what elſe, are all from the Apoſtles: This will want a confirmation, and till we have it, we muſt beg leave to ſuſpend our belief; and crave their pardon if we do not admit or embrace it as a Tradition truly Apoſtolical.</p>
               <p>The next thing we are required to admit and embrace, are, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Traditions.</hi> Now thoſe are either ſuch as have been uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received by the Church in all Ages; or are recommended to us by the preſent Church only. The former of theſe we have a very great regard and reverence for, are willing to admit and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them,<note place="margin">Seſſ. 4. de Canon. Script. Contra Creſcon. Gram. l. 2. c. 31. Aug. ad Hieron. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 19.</note> and to give them the next place in our eſteem to Scripture Tradition. But we cannot be ſo complaiſant, nor ſo far comply with the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> to receive them with equal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and reverence. We think with St. <hi>Aug. That it is no injury to St.</hi> Cyprian <hi>to diſtinguiſh his Writings from the Canonical Authority of the holy Scriptures.</hi> And with the ſame holy Father, We think, <hi>That the Jugdment of St.</hi> Paul <hi>alone, is to be preferred before that of all the Fathers taken together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The latter of theſe, <hi>viz. The Traditions of the preſent Church,</hi> though we have a very great eſteem and value for them, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſtrict examination how far they agree with Scripture and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Tradition, we cannot ſo readily admit and embrace them. For as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his time ſaid, ſo we ſay now, <hi>Thoſe things which Men invent of themſelves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. in 1. c. Agg. Proph.</note> 
                  <hi>as it were by Apoſtolical Tradition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Authority and witneſs of the holy Scriptures, are confounded by God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52954:6"/>
               <p>The third thing we are here required to admit and embrace, are, <hi>All other Obſervances and Conſtitutions of the ſame Church.</hi> If by Church here, be mean the Catholique Church of all Ages, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is made appear to have been an Obſervance or Conſtitution thereof, we ſhall have a mighty regard for it; but how ſhall we know what the Obſervances and Conſtitutions of the Church have been, if they be not conveyed unto us by an uninterrupted and unqueſtionable Tradition? and if we do not know them, how can we admit or embrace them? But it is remarkable, That the Obſervances and Conſtitutions mentioned in this Article, are things different from what hath been delivered to us, either by Apoſtolical or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Tradition; elſe, why are they called <hi>other?</hi> And it is as obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, That by Church here, he doth not mean the Church of all Ages, but the preſent Church only; not the Catholick, but the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Church, whoſe Obſervances and Conſtitutions we are required to admit and embrace; Otherwiſe, why doth he reſtrain it to the ſame Church? which word, <hi>ſame,</hi> the Vindicator hath thought fit to leave out.</p>
               <p>Now there are many Obſervances and Conſtitutions in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which we think ſhe hath no authority to impoſe upon other Churches, nor have they any reaſon to admit and embrace.</p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding all this our Vindicator hath undertaken to prove, <hi>That, not only this, but all the Articles in the Profeſſion of Pope</hi> Pius IV. <hi>are according to Scripture, and the ſence of the Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> How well he hath acquitted himſelf in this undertaking, I ſhall now examine; and obſerving his own method, ſhall conſider his proofs of every Article ſeverally.</p>
               <p>He begins his proof of this Article by Scripture, and then fortifies it by the Teſtimony of the Fathers. His firſt Scripture proof is taken out of 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. Where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Brethren, ſtand faſt, and hold the traditions, which ye have been taught, whether by word, or our epiſtle.</hi> Here he obſerves, That there are two ways of deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſacred Truth, one by writing, the other by Word of Mouth; and that the Doctrine is to be held faſt, whether it be delivered the one way, or the other. All which we readily grant him, provided, it be made appear, That the Tradition as it ſtands diſtinguiſhed from the written Word, be Apoſtolical; or that what is ſo delivered be Truth; or a Doctrine agreeable to the written Word. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not preach one thing and write another; and if he did not, then all that can be made of this Text, will amount only to this, Hold faſt the ſelf ſame ſubſtance of Religion and Doctrine, that I have taught you either by Word or Writing, <hi>i. e.</hi> either by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52954:7"/> preaching unto you in perſon, when preſent; or inſtructing you by my Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Niceph. l. 2. c. 45.</note> when at a diſtance. Thus <hi>Nicephorus</hi> underſtands it, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, That thoſe things which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had plainly taught by preaching, when preſent; the ſame things, being abſent, he was deſirous to recal to their memories, by a compendious recapitulation of them in Writing.<note place="margin">Hieron. in 2 Th. 2.</note> And the Annotator under St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s name, ſaith, <hi>Quando ſua vult teneri, non vult extranea ſuperaddi.</hi> And if thus we are to underſtand this place, it will do but little ſervice for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Romiſh Traditions: Many, I wiſh I might not ſay, moſt of which are beſides, if not againſt, the written word. But doth not St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> underſtand this place of Scripture otherwiſe?<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 2 Th. 2.15. Hom. 4</note> the Vindicator thinks he doth, and therefore hath produced him as an evidence againſt us; Well, let us hear what he ſaith, <hi>They</hi> (the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) <hi>have not delivered all in their Epiſtles.</hi> (who denies it?) <hi>but many things alſo without writing.</hi> (who doubts of it?) <hi>which are likewiſe to be believed,</hi> (yes, if we knew what they were;) But all things worthy of belief, and which ought to be believed when known, are not neceſſary, nor indeed poſſible to be believed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are known.<note place="margin">John 21.25.</note> Thoſe many other things which Jeſus did and <hi>were never written,</hi> of which St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, would all be worthy of belief, and ought to be believed, if they were known; but not being known, they are not neceſſary to be believed; nor are we obliged to believe any one, who tells us This or That was one of them, the Scripture being ſilent therein.</p>
               <p>But St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> adds, <hi>Let us therefore eſteem the Tradition of the Church worthy of Credit.</hi> 'Tis a Tradition, enquire no farther. We grant the Tradition of the Church is worthy of Belief, and when any is made appear to be ſo, we will ſeek no farther. But then it muſt be the Tradition not of the preſent Church only, but of the Church in all Ages, and ſuch a Tradition as from hand to hand, and Age to Age, brings us up to the times and perſons of the Apoſtles, and our Saviour himſelf, and ſo is confirmed by all thoſe Miracles and other arguments, whereby they convinced their Doctrine to be true.</p>
               <p>But I know none can better acquaint us with the mind and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> than St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> himſelf, who, in the ſame Homily out of which theſe words are taken,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. ibid.</note> hath theſe other, <hi>All thoſe things that are in the holy Scriptures are right and clear,</hi> all <hi>that which is neceſſary, is therein clear and manifeſt.</hi> And if ſo then thoſe Traditions that are not in the Scripture, are unneceſſary things.<note place="margin">In Pſ. 95.</note> And the ſame Father, in another place tells us, <hi>When we ſay any thing without the Scripture, the thoughts of the Hearers are uncertain.</hi> The Traditions therefore which St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> here
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52954:7"/> ſpeaks of, are ſuch as are either contained in, or may be warranted by the written word, and if ſo, then he will ſtand the Vindicator in little ſtead.</p>
               <p>His next Scripture Proof is taken out of 2 <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> thus directeth <hi>Timothy, The things that thou haſt heard of me among many Witneſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithful men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi> Whence he obſerves, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> takes care, that what he had taught the faithful, though only heard from him, might be obſerved, and conveyed down to Poſterity, by their teaching of others. How well this Gloſs doth agree with the Text, needs no other evidence, than comparing the one with the other. But if we would know St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s deſign in theſe words, let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for what end he beſought <hi>Timothy</hi> to abide ſtill at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> when he himſelf went into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> which he tells us was, That he might charge ſome to teach no other Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3. <hi>i. e.</hi> None other but what he himſelf had delivered to the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> for there were certain falſe Apoſtles which did endeavour to draw the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to the obſervation of Legal Rites, and Jewiſh Traditions, as neceſſary to ſalvation, ſaith their own <hi>Lyra</hi> upon the place. The buſineſs therefore which <hi>Timothy</hi> had to do, as Governour of that Church, was, That none but only faithful and able men ſhould be admitted by him to preach unto them. And this is that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> again charges him to do in this place; ſo their own <hi>Lyra</hi> upon the place informs us; for, ſaith he, St. <hi>Paul</hi> here ſtirs up <hi>Timothy</hi> to be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous in preaching himſelf, and to make choice of others who were fit for that work: and therefore he ſaith, <hi>The things that thou haſt heard of me among many Witneſſes (i. e.</hi> confirmed by the Law and the Prophets, and the <hi>Hagiographa,</hi> or other ſacred Writings) <hi>the ſame commit thou to faithful Men, who ſhall be able to teach others alſo. (i. e.</hi> to Men of a ſound Faith, who ſhall be fit by the example of holy life, by their Knowledge and by their Eloquence to teach others alſo.) Now what relation this hath to Traditions, or why this Gentleman brought it in as a proof of them, I cannot deviſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all the Scripture proofs which he offers for Traditions, but he hath a Reſerve of two paſſages out of two of the Fathers to make good the Reer.</p>
               <p>The firſt of which, he tells us, is to be found in <hi>Epiphanius, Haer.</hi> 61. in theſe words, <hi>'Tis neceſſary to admit of Traditions, for all things cannot be found in Scripture; and therefore the holy Apoſtles delivered ſome things in writing, and ſome by Tradition.</hi> How far this will ſerve the end he aims at, is now to be conſidered. That in ſome caſes it is neceſſary to admit of Traditions, was never denied
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52954:8"/> by us; nor did we ever affirm, That all things are to be found in Scripture, nor do we deny, but that the Holy Apoſtles did deliver ſome things in Writing, and ſome by Tradition, <hi>i. e.</hi> by word of Mouth. But we deny that it is neceſſary to admit of Traditions, <hi>i. e.</hi> unwritten Traditions, in all caſes; or indeed in any, unleſs it can be made appear that they have been univerſally received by the whole Church in all Ages. And we do affirm, that though the Scriptures do not contain all things, yet they do contain all things neceſſary to be believed by us in order to our Salvation. And though we do not deny, but that ſome things were delivered by the Apoſtles in Writing, and ſome by word of mouth; yet we do deny, that what was delivered by word of mouth was either beſides or againſt what was written by them. What was delivered in writing hath been carefully preſerved, we have it before our eyes, and are ſure of it; but of thoſe things which were delivered by word of mouth, ſome we are ſure have been loſt; as for inſtance, Thoſe many other things which Jeſus did, mentioned by St. <hi>John c.</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 25. and the cauſe of the hinderance of the coming of Anti-Chriſt, mentioned by St. <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Th.</hi> 2. That Records are a much more faithful keeper than Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, appears by theſe inſtances; thoſe few that were written being ſtill preſerved and believed, and thoſe infinity that were not written being all loſt and vaniſhed out of the memory of Men. And ſeeing God in his providence hath not thought fit to preſerve the memory of them, he hath freed us from the obligation of believing them: for every obligation ceaſeth, when it becomes impoſſible. You will not, you dare not ſay, that God would ſuffer any thing to be loſt that was neceſſary to Salvation, nor can you deny but that he hath ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Traditions to be loſt; and therefore the Knowledge or Belief of them, though it were a profitable thing, yet is it not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. And if ſo, then with what face can you require us to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto this Article upon pain of damnation; when we have no footſteps or print remaining, which with divine Faith we may rely upon? All which conſidered, may we not truly ſay, That <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> here, if rightly underſtood, is neither for them, nor againſt us? For we ſay with him, that it is neceſſary to admit of Tradition in ſome, but not in all caſes; We acknowledge alſo, that the Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles delivered ſome things in Writing, and ſome by Tradition; and when any thing is made appear to us to be of Apoſtolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and delivered by them as neceſſary to Salvation, we will enquire no farther, but will readily admit and embrace it.</p>
               <p>His next Authority is taken out of St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen. l.</hi> 3. <hi>contra Eunom. p.</hi> 126. where he tells us theſe words are to be found, <hi>'Tis a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52954:8"/> ſufficient proof of our Doctrine, that we have received it by Tradition from our Anceſtors; it having been left us, as an Inheritance, by the Apoſtles; and convey'd down to us, by a continued Succeſſion of the Faithful in all Ages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee nothing to all this, but what without any ſcruple we may readily aſſent to. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> ſays, <hi>It is a ſufficient proof of our Doctrine, that we have received it by Tradition from our Anceſtors.</hi> And who theſe Anceſtors were, he tells us in the next words; <hi>It having been left us, as an Inheritance, by the Apoſtles:</hi> So then the Anceſtors here ſpoken of were the Apoſtles, and the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here mentioned, was, what was left us, as an Inheritance, by them. Now what was it that was left us, as an Inheritance, by the Apoſtles, but only the Doctrine of Chriſtianity contained in their Writings? which Doctrine hath been convey'd down to us by a ſucceſſion of the Faithful in all Ages <hi>i. e,</hi> by Univerſal Tradition.</p>
               <p>That this is the ſence of this Father in this place, is plain from his own words, and is agreeable to the way and manner of ſpeaking among the Fathers; by whom the Goſpel it ſelf, and the whole Religion of Chriſt is frequently called <hi>A Tradition.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription. adverſ. Haereticos. Concil. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinop. 6. Act. 4. Eadem Actione. Baſil. de Spiritu Sancto. 2 Th. 2.15.</note> So the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Faith are by <hi>Tertullian</hi> called <hi>An old Tradition.</hi> So the Faith of the Holy Trinity in the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> is called <hi>A Tradition.</hi> And the Faith of two ſundry Natures in Chriſt, in the ſame Council is called <hi>The lively Tradition of the Apoſtles.</hi> So St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> calls it <hi>A Tradition,</hi> To believe in the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt. And in this ſence St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Apoſtolical Doctrine, <hi>A Tradition.</hi> This is all that he produceth in the behalf of Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Now whether he hath hereby proved that the Romiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Traditions is according to Scripture, and the Sence of the Primitive Fathers, I leave the Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>His next Effort is to make good the latter part of this Article touching all the other Obſervances and Conſtitutions of the Church. And here we might reaſonably have expected, that he ſhould have told us, what thoſe Obſervances and Conſtitutions are, which we are required to admit and embrace. But that is not the way of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe expects that her votaries ſhould rely upon her guidance and conduct with an implicit Faith, and obſerve her Dictates with a blind Obedience. And therefore the Vindicator here like a dutiful Son of ſuch a Mother, never ſtops to us what is required of us; but, without more ado, goes about to prove, That, whatſoever thoſe Obſervances and Conſtitutions are, it is our duty to admit of them, and embrace them. And this he pretends to do both by an Apoſtolical Precept, and Apoſtolical Practice; Two
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52954:9"/> mighty arguments, if they be appoſite to the thing in hand, and well managed; which whether they be or no, I ſhall now examine.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtolical Precept which he produceth, is in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews, c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 7, 17. in theſe words, <hi>Remember them, which have the rule over you, &amp;c. Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves; for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give an account, &amp;c.</hi> In the former of theſe Verſes (as their own <hi>Lyra</hi> upon the place tells us) we are taught how to behave our ſelves towards our Spiritual Rulers that are dead:<note place="margin">Lyra in Hebr. c. 13. v. 7.</note> We ought to remember them, by following their Faith, and imitating their good Examples. And leſt we ſhould be at a loſs to know who they are whom we are to remember, and whoſe Faith and Vertue we are to follow, the ſame <hi>Lyra</hi> tells us, They were the Apoſtles and other Diſciples of Chriſt. In the latter place, the ſame <hi>Lyra</hi> tells us, we are taught how to behave our ſelves towards our Spiritual Rulers who are alive, <hi>viz.</hi> by obeying their Commands, and giving due Reverence to their Perſons. That obedience is due from Inferiors to their Superiors, we readily grant. But then, I. They muſt be ſuch Superiors as not only pretend to have, but really have a right to rule over them. Now we do not think, that any particular Church, no not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, hath any authority to give Laws to another Church; for it is a certain Rule, <hi>Par in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem non habet imperium,</hi> Equals have no power over one another. And if ſo, then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no reaſon to expect our compliance with every thing, which ſhe thinks fit to require of us. II. As they ought to have a right to rule over us, ſo their commands ought to be ſuch as we may without ſin obey them; otherwiſe the rule of the Apoſtles will diſpenſe with us,<note place="margin">Act. 4.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether it be better to obey God or Man, judge ye.</hi> Now whether they be ſo or no, how can we tell, if we are not allowed before-hand to know what they are? Theſe things being thus premiſed, I dare now venture any unbyaſſed Reader to be the Judge, whether by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this Precept the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may juſtly challenge a power to impoſe what Obſervances and Conſtitutions ſhe pleaſeth upon the whole Chriſtian World? For that is truly the queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us.</p>
               <p>Having conſidered the Precept by him procured, and found him miſtaken in it; Let us now conſider his argument from Primitive Practice, and ſee whether that will ſtand him in any more ſtead. This he tells us, was the practice of the Apoſtles, even of St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf and <hi>Silas,</hi> who, as they went through the Cities, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them the Decrees for to keep, that were ordained of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52954:9"/> Apoſtles and Elders, which were at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And ſo were the Churches eſtabliſhed in the Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> xvi. 4, 5. The Apoſtolical Council held at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> having finiſhed their Decrees, commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> with <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> to publiſh the ſame among the Brethren that were of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> Acts c. xv. v. 22, 23. Theſe Men faithfully diſcharged their duty, in performing their Commiſſion, and their ſo doing had a good effect; for thereby the Churches were eſtabliſhed in the Faith, and increaſed in number daily. Now what is all this to the Vindicator's purpoſe? Will it neceſſarily follow, That becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> publiſhed the Apoſtles Decrees in theſe places, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may impoſe what Ordinances and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions ſhe will upon all Chriſtians? If not, I do not ſee what good this inſtance of Apoſtolical Practice will do the Vindicator.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I alſo admit the Holy Scripture according to that Sence, which our Holy Mother, the Church, has held, and does hold; to whom it belongs to judge of the true Sence and Interpretation thereof. Nor will I ever admit or interpret it otherwiſe, than according to the unanimous conſent of the Holy Fathers.</q>
               <p>WHAT <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid merrily of the Heathens in his time;<note place="margin">Tertul. in Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs God pleaſe Man well, He ſhall be no God,</hi> (and ſo now Man muſt be friendly and favourable unto God) may with a little variation be here applied to the Church of <hi>Rome, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the Holy Scriptures pleaſe Her well, they ſhall be no Scriptures.</hi> For unleſs they ſpeak according to Her Sence, they are not to be admitted, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Her to judge of the true Sence and Interpretation of them. For I do not at all doubt but it is of that Church that this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle ſpeaks, and which it ſtiles <hi>Our Holy Mother, the Church.</hi> And for this, I have the warrant of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> himſelf, who in his XXIII. Article ſtiles it, <hi>The Holy, Catholick and Apoſtolick</hi> Roman <hi>Church, the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches.</hi> Nor indeed can it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe underſtood, for if the true Sence of Scripture muſt depend upon the Judgment of the Univerſal Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> of all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or at leaſt of all the Biſhops and Paſtors in the World; how is it poſſible to get them together to declare the Sence thereof? or muſt we reject all Scripture, till we have ſuch a Declaration? If you tell me, that we muſt look for it in the unanimous conſent of the Holy Fathers. I anſwer, I. That this is an impoſſible task for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52954:10"/> all ſorts of Chriſtians; for Women and unlearned Men can never perform it: if therefore their Salvation depend thereupon, they muſt inevitably be damned. II. Thoſe that are learned and able to read and underſtand the Fathers, do not find any ſuch unanimous conſent among them; ſo that if according to this Article we muſt not admit the Scripture, till they are all agreed about the Sence of it; both learned and unlearned will for ever want a Rule to govern themſelves by, in the eternal concerns of their immortal Souls.</p>
               <p>To avoid theſe difficulties, The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>Catholick,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church; and by <hi>Our Holy Mother the Church,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which they call, <hi>the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches.</hi> But will this make the buſineſs ever a jot the more eaſie? Muſt all the Chriſtians in the World, out of <hi>Greece, Egypt,</hi> and many other more remote parts, repair to <hi>Rome,</hi> to receive the true Sence and Interpretation of the Scriptures? Or if they do, are they ſure to meet with it, when they come there? Will they not find as much difference in opinions between the Doctors of that Church, as of any other? Will they not find, that Councils have contradicted Councils, and Popes condemned Popes? And if ſo, where then can they hope to meet with an infallible Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Holy Scriptures? To this may be added, That if it belong to the Church to judge of the true Sence and Interpretation of Scripture, and we are not to admit of it but according to Her Sence; then it will be neceſſary to know which is the Church, and whether that which pretends to be ſo, be indeed the true Church; for without that we cannot with any certainty depend upon Her Judgment. But how ſhall we know that but by the Scriptures?<note place="margin">
                     <p>Nullo modo cognoſcitur quae ſit vera Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Chriſti, niſi tantummodo per Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras. <hi>Chryſoſtom. in opere imperfect. Hom.</hi> 49.</p>
                     <p>Eccleſiam Chriſti ſicut ipſum Caput Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, in Scripturis Sanctis Canonicis debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus agnoſcere. <hi>Aug. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitat. Eccl. c.</hi> 66.</p>
                  </note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is impoſſible to know it otherwiſe.</hi> And St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> for the diſcovery of the true Church, directs us to the ſacred Scriptures. And indeed, how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to know this or that to be a <hi>True</hi> Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> of a ſound Judgment, and pure in the Faith; unleſs we firſt know the Rule of Faith, which is the Word of God? But how ſhall we know either the one or the other, but by making uſe of our own Reaſon, and judging for our ſelves of thoſe Evidences which are produced? So that in fine, If we ſhould grant all that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> requires of us, yet muſt we make uſe of our own Reaſon to underſtand that Sence and Interpretation which ſhe gives us of the Holy Scriptures. Which is no more, nor leſs, than reſolving all at laſt into a private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52954:10"/> And that all Chriſtians not only may, but ought, in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and in theſe caſes, thus to judge for themſelves, we have good warrant and Authority from the Word of God; in which we are adviſed, <hi>Not to believe every Spirit, but to try the Spirits whether they be of God; becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World,</hi> 1 John iv. 1. <hi>And to prove all things, but to hold faſt that which is good,</hi> 1 Th. v. 21. <hi>And to be ready always to give an anſwer to every man that asketh us a reaſon of the hope that is in us,</hi> 1. Pet. iij. 15. And our Saviour tells us, <hi>If the blind lead the blind, both ſhall fall into the ditch,</hi> Matth. xv. 14. And he ſeverely reproves thoſe who did not receive his Doctrine, ſaying, <hi>And why even of your ſelves judge ye not what is right?</hi> Luke xij. 57. But notwithſtanding all this, and much more, which hath been told them oftentimes oyer and over; yet the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator like a ſtout Champion of his Church, undertakes to prove, <hi>That this Article and every Branch of it, is according to Scripture, and the Sence of the Primitive Fathers.</hi> Let us ſee now, how he acquits himſelf in this undertaking. This, he tells us, is founded upon the Doctrine delivered by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Ep. i. 20. <hi>No Prophecy of the Scripture is of any private Interpretation.</hi> From whence he thus argues, And if it be not of private Interpretation, private perſons muſt apply themſelves for the true Sence of it to ſome others; and to whom, but unto thoſe whom God hath put over them; whom he hath commanded them to hear, to ſubmit to and obey? &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When Men, by their own diligence and induſtry, cannot attain to the true ſence and meaning of Holy Scripture, or after all their care and pains in the uſe of all proper means, are not ſatisfied there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; that in ſuch a caſe they ſhould apply themſelves to thoſe whom God hath ſet over them, as their Spiritual Guides, we think to be a method, not only ſafe and reaſonable, but very neceſſary. But whether this be deducible from, or can be built upon this Text of Scripture, I take to be very queſtionable; or rather that it is out of queſtion, that it cannot. And therefore before we proceed any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let us make a ſtand a while, and take a view of the Apoſtle's deſign in this place, and of the full and genuine importance of theſe words. St. <hi>Peter</hi> having faithfully diſcharged his duty in preaching the Goſpel, and now finding the time of his departure hence near at hand, he commits to writing the ſubſtance of what he had preached, that ſo thoſe to whom he had preached might always have it in remembrance; ſo little did he rely upon Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That this was his deſign appears plainly from the 12, 13, 14, and 15 Verſes of this Chapter. And that he might not burthen their memories too much, he gives them a ſhort Summary of what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52954:11"/> he had preached unto them, <hi>viz. The power and coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> v. 16. And to aſſure them of the truth and certainty thereof, he lays before them two undeniable Arguments; I. A voice from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> This was at his Transfiguration in the Mount, at which time <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were with him, and were Eye-Witneſſes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and Ear-Witneſſes of that Heavenly Voice, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17, 18. II. But leſt they ſhould diſtruſt them, or look upon this as an illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or a dream and fancy of their own; he furniſheth them with another Argument, which he was well aſſured would not be rejected by them; and that is taken from the Prophetical Writings, for which thoſe of the Diſperſion, <hi>viz.</hi> the coverted Jews had a mighty regard; ſaying, <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of Prophecy, whereunto ye do well that ye take heed,</hi> &amp;c. v. 19. meaning that Prophecy of holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. ij. 7. <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee.</hi> And then he adds, <hi>Knowing this firſt, that no Prophecy of the Scriptures (i. e.</hi> no Prophecy contained in the Scriptures of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to diſtinguiſh it from the dreams of thoſe Men, who pretended to propheſie, but had neither Miſſion nor Commiſſion from God ſo to do) <hi>is of any private Interpretation, (i. e.</hi> proceeds from any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or uninſpired perſon, or is an invention of Man.) And that this is the full importance of this Expreſſion, the Apoſtle himſelf ſeems plainly to intimate in the very next words, where he ſaith, <hi>For the Prophecy came not in old time by the Will of Man; (i. e.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of old did not propheſie either what they pleaſed, or when they pleaſed) <hi>but holy Men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt. (i. e.</hi> they publiſhed nothing but what was dictated to them by the Holy Ghoſt, nor at any time but when they were moved by him) v. 21. And if we conſult the Original words, they cannot well be conſtrued otherwiſe; for what in the 20 verſe is rendred, <hi>Of any private Interpretation,</hi> in the Greek is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and may be rendred thus, <hi>All Prophecy of the Scripture is not made of their own Explication;</hi> which is the ſame which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle afterwards ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Prophecy came not in old time by the Will of Man.</hi> And for this ſence of the Words, if that will weigh any thing with them, we have the Authority of their own <hi>Lyra</hi> upon the place. Now, if this be, as undoubtedly it is, the ſence of the Apoſtle here; let us ſee what conſequence the Vindicator can draw from hence to favour his undertaking. The Apoſtle here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thoſe to whom he wrote, <hi>That all Prophecy of Scripture is not made of their own Explication, i. e.</hi> (as he explains himſelf) <hi>Prophecy of old came not by the Will of Man. Therefore</hi> (ſaith the Vindicator)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52954:11"/> 
                  <hi>it belongs to the Church (i. e.</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome) and her only, to judge of the true ſence and interpretation of Scripture for all Chriſtians.</hi> If you can ſwallow this conſequence, I do not ſee what you need to ſtick at. One would have thought, the more natural conſequence had been this, <hi>Therefore truſt not every thing that pretends to come from a Prophetical and infallible Spirit, but try whether it do ſo, or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee what a firm foundation this Gentleman hath laid, which thus failing him, his Superſtructure thereupon, muſt needs be in a very tottering condition.</p>
               <p>His next Scripture is <hi>Acts</hi> xx. 28. Where St. <hi>Paul</hi> charges the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Epheſus, To take heed to themſelves, and to all the flock, over which the Holy Ghoſt had made them Overſeers, to feed the Church of God, which he had purchaſed with his own blood.</hi> To theſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he had <hi>declared all the Counſel of God,</hi> v. 27. and then bids them <hi>to take heed to the flock,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> to inſtruct thoſe committed to their charge in that Doctrine which they had learned of him. That by a parity of reaſon, all Paſtors and Teachers are to feed the flock committed to their care, we willingly grant; but how he will hence infer, That all Chriſtian People are to receive the true ſence and Interpretation of Scripture from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine.</p>
               <p>His next is, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> III. 15. Where St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs <hi>Timothy,</hi> how to <hi>behave</hi> himſelf <hi>in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God, the pillar and ground of the Truth.</hi> There is an excellent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe lately printed at <hi>London,</hi> intituled, <hi>The Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> to which (if this Gentleman be permitted to read it) I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr him, for his better underſtanding of this Text.</p>
               <p>His next is, <hi>Matth.</hi> xxviij. 20. Where our Saviour having given his Apoſtles his laſt and largeſt Commiſſion, promiſeth, <hi>to be with them alway even unto the end of the World.</hi> This promiſe was made to the Apoſtles, and not only to them, but to the whole Church of God in all Ages; but how the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> comes to claim a Title to this promiſe, more than any other, I know not; or if ſhe had it, I do not ſee what ſervice it would do her in this caſe; For, that Chriſt will be alway with his Church, ſo to preſerve it as it ſhall never ceaſe to be a Church, we do not doubt; but to preſerve it from all error, as he never promiſed it, ſo we have no reaſon to expect it.</p>
               <p>His next is, <hi>John</hi> xvi. 13. Where our Saviour tells his Diſciples, <hi>When he, the Spirit of truth, is come, he will guide you into all truth.</hi> This promiſe was not made to the whole Church, but to the Apoſtles; whoſe caſe was ſo peculiar and extraordinary, that the Church now hath no ground upon which to hope for the ſame Aſſiſtance which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52954:12"/> they then had, and which indeed was then neceſſary for them to have. That Chriſt will aſſiſt his Church in all Ages by his Grace, we do not deny; but that that Aſſiſtance implies Infallibility, we cannot grant; for then every private Chriſtian, who is aſſiſted by Divine Grace, would be infallible: But if it did, why the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould put in a peculiar claim to this privilege, more than the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or any other particular Church, I ſee no reaſon. But it ſeems the Vindicator found great reaſon for it; for thus he argues, <hi>Chriſt promiſed his Apoſtles, when he, the Spirit of truth, came, he ſhould guide them into all truth. Therefore it belongs to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>to judge of the true ſence and interpretation of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> Juſt as if one ſhould argue, <hi>Chriſt promiſed that theſe ſigns ſhould follow them that believe,</hi> In his name they ſhould caſt out Devils, They ſhould ſpeak with new Tongues, They ſhould take up Serpents, and if they drank any deadly thing it ſhould not hurt them; They ſhould lay hands on the ſick, and they ſhould recover, <hi>Mark</hi> c. xvi. v. 17, 18. <hi>Therefore all that believe in Chriſt at this day ſhall do the ſame things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His laſt Scripture proof is, <hi>Matth.</hi> xviij. 17. Where our Saviour ſaith, <hi>If he neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen man, and a Publican.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, I. That our Saviour in this place doth not ſpeak of Controverſies in Religion, or points of Faith; but of quarrels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween neighbours; as is plain from <hi>v.</hi> 15. where our Saviour ſaith, <hi>If thy Brother ſhall treſpaſs againſt thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him alone,</hi> &amp;c. II. By <hi>Church</hi> here, we cannot underſtand either the <hi>Catholick,</hi> or that which they call the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Church. Not the former, for that would make the thing not only impracticable, but altogether impoſſible; for when a quarrel happens to ariſe between two Neighbours, if they muſt ſtay for the Deciſion of it, till the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal</hi> Church is aſſembled for that purpoſe, their quarrel may laſt long enough. Nor the latter; for that would be as impracticable as the former; for if two Chriſtians have a quarrel in <hi>Syria,</hi> or in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> muſt they go to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to end their difference? III. By the word, <hi>Church,</hi> therefore in this place, we muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any particular Church, or Society of Chriſtians, of which the the two quarrelling Neighbours are Members. Now it is confeſſed on all hands, that any ſuch Society, in giving Admonitions, and uſing of Cenſures, may err; being ſubject to be miſlead either by paſſion, or prejudice, or ignorance. 'Tis plain therefore that this Scripture is not at all to his purpoſe, or if it were, it would do him no ſervice.</p>
               <p>Thus have I conſidered his Scripture proofs, and now let us ſee what the Fathers will ſay for him. He produceth two paſſages, both
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52954:12"/> out of one and the ſame Father, <hi>viz.</hi> St. <hi>Aug.</hi> His firſt Authority is taken out of his firſt Book, <hi>contra Creſcon.</hi> Gram. c. 33. <hi>Then,</hi> ſays he, <hi>we follow the truth of the Scriptures, when we do that, which hath ſeemed good to the whole Church, which Church is commended to us by the Authority of the Scripture; To the end that becauſe Holy Writ cannot deceive, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is afraid of being deceived by the difficulty of this queſtion, may conſult the Church concerning it; which without leaving room to doubt, the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture demonſtrates.</hi> I cannot imagine what was in this Gentlemans mind, when he pickt up this paſſage of St. <hi>Aug.</hi> for a proof of this Article. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> indeed ſays, <hi>Then we follow the truth of the Scriptures, when we do that, which has ſeem'd good to the whole Church.</hi> And who denies it? We have too great a Veneration for the Doctrine and Practice of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Church, to ſuſpect that there can be any ill in them; let but any thing be made appear to have been univerſally received, or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally practiſed by the Church in all Ages, and we will readily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and embrace it, we will acquieſce in it, and ſeek no farther. Thus far do we perfectly agree with this holy Father, nor do we diſſent from him in the reſt. <hi>Which Church,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is commended to us by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Scriptures.</hi> Well then, by his Rule we muſt underſtand the Scriptures before we can know the Church. Now the Scriptures, they themſelves confeſs, do not conſiſt in the Letters and Words, but in the Sence and meaning: And if ſo, then we muſt underſtand the ſence and meaning of Scriptures antecedent to the Churches Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them. But he goes on, <hi>To the end,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that becauſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ cannot deceive, whoſoever is afraid of being deceived by the difficulty of this queſtion, may conſult the Church concerning it; which, without leaving room to doubt, the holy Scripture demonſtrates.</hi> And here I cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marque, I. That, according to St. <hi>Auſtin, Holy Writ</hi> is the only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule to judge by, for it cannot deceive. II. That by <hi>this</hi> rule we are to find out <hi>the true Church,</hi> for, <hi>without any ambiguity, or leaving room to doubt, it plainly demonſtrates it to us.</hi> III. That having by this means found out the true Church, we ought, in all queſtions which are too hard and difficult for us, to conſult her about them. All which we readily agree to. Now let the Vindicator once more put on his ſpectacles, and ſeriouſly review this place of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and I dare appeal to himſelf, or any man of ſence, whether it do not directly conclude againſt this Article, which he undertakes to prove by it.</p>
               <p>But perhaps he may have better luck with his next Authority, let us therefore conſider that too; which he cites out of the ſame Father, <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitat. Eccleſ.</hi> c. 19. whence he quotes theſe words; <hi>If we had any wiſe man, whoſe Authority was recommended to us by Chriſt himſelf; we could no ways doubt of following his judgment, having conſulted him upon this point;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52954:13"/> leſt in refuſing, we ſhould not ſo much ſeem obſtinately to withſtand him, as Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, by whoſe teſtimony he was recommended to us.</hi> Who doubts of all this? If it had pleaſed our Bleſſed Saviour to have given ſuch teſtimony to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other Church, we ſhould never have doubted to follow the judgment of that Church; and when they can make it appear that he hath done ſo, we ſhall, without any the leaſt ſcruple, ſubmit to it. But St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> goes on, <hi>Chriſt hath given teſtimony of his Church,</hi> (True, but where? is it not in the holy Scriptures? and if ſo, then we muſt underſtand them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can be ſatisfied concerning this Teſtimony) <hi>and as this Church directs, you ought with all readineſs obey.</hi> (Right, but firſt we muſt know which is this Church, and that according to St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do, but by the Scriptures.) <hi>And if you will not, 'tis not to me you are diſobedient, or any man; but moſt perverſly to the prejudice of your own Soul, you withſtand Chriſt himſelf, becauſe you refuſe to follow the Church, which is recommended by his Authority, whom you judge it a wickedneſs to reſiſt.</hi> All this we can readily ſubſcribe to, for when by the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, we have once found out which is the true Church, we ought with all readineſs to yield obedience thereunto; becauſe it is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us by the Authority of Jeſus Chriſt, whom to reſiſt in any thing, we account a great wickedneſs. But where ſhall we meet with this Authoritative Recommendation, except in the holy Scriptures? So that ſtill we muſt underſtand the Scriptures, before we can know which is that Church, that is recommended to us by Chriſt. And now, pray'e, what is all this to the proof of this Article; <hi>That it belongs to the Church to judge of the true ſence and interpretation of Scripture, and that we are not to admit Scripture to be Scripture, but according to that ſence, which ſhe gives of it.</hi> And yet, all this while, <hi>we cannot,</hi> according to St. <hi>Auſtin, know the Church, but by the Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I do alſo profeſs that there are truly and properly ſeven Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the new Law, inſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and neceſſary for the ſalvation of Mankind; though all be not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for every one; to wit, Baptiſm, Confirmation, Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, Penance, Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, Order, and Matrimony; that they conferr Grace, and that three of them, Baptiſm, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and Order, cannot be reiterated without Sacrilege.</q>
               <p>HERE the Vindicator tells us, That the holy Scripture no where aſſigns the number of the Sacraments, either of their being two
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52954:13"/> or ſeven. Neither doth it give us the definition of a Sacrament, and the word is not ſo much as named in the Engliſh Tranſlation, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly once in the Vulgar, <hi>viz. Epheſ.</hi> v. 32. ſpeaking of Matrimony. All that we believe therefore in this point, we receive from the Church, as it hath been delivered, founded upon the Doctrine of the Fathers, and the Sence of the Scripture. To this I anſwer, That it is not more plain that in Scripture there is no mention of Sacraments, than that in the Fathers there is no mention of ſeven. The determination of the number is of ſo late a date,<note place="margin">Caſſand. Conſult. Art. 13. de numero Sacram. An. 1439.</note> that their ingenuous <hi>Caſſander</hi> freely confeſſes, <hi>That it is not eaſie to find any man before</hi> Peter Lombard (who lived in the twelfth Century) <hi>which hath ſet down any certain and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of Sacraments.</hi> The Council of <hi>Florence</hi> indeed inſinuates this number of ſeven Sacraments, as <hi>Suarez</hi> contends. But it was never determined till the late Council of <hi>Trent</hi> in the laſt Age; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt needs be a great Novelty.<note place="margin">An. 1546.</note> But to vindicate the Doctrine of ſeven Sacraments, as it is now taught in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſumm'd up in this Article, from the imputation of Novelty; This Gentleman undertakes to prove, that it is founded upon the Doctrine of the Fathers, and the ſence of the Scripture; wherein, how well he acquits himſelf, we ſhall now conſider. But becauſe he tells us, that the Holy Scripture gives us no definition of a Sacrament, It will be neceſſary to ſtate the notion of the thing, and to agree what it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we diſpute how many of them there be. To the conſtitution of a Sacrament properly ſo called, we ſay that theſe three things muſt of neceſſity concurr, <hi>viz.</hi> the word of Inſtitution, a viſible Sign, or outward Element;<note place="margin">Aug. in Joan. Tract. 80.</note> and a promiſe of inviſible Grace annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Which is the ſame that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Accedat verbum ad Elementum, &amp; fit Sacramentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now let us ſee,<note place="margin">Catech. ad Parochos pars 2. Tit. de Sacram. n. 5. p. 113. Aug. l. 10. de civ. Dei. c. 5. And Epiſt. 2.</note> how far they agree with us in this notion of a Sacrament. The <hi>Trent Catechiſm,</hi> which always ſpeaks the ſence of that Council, gives us this definition of a Sacrament, <hi>It is a viſible Sign of inviſible Grace, inſtituted for our Juſtification,</hi> which it grounds upon the Authority of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the compliance of all the School Doctors with him therein.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Doway Catechiſm</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">P. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>A Sacrament is a viſible ſign of inviſible Grace, inſtituted by Chriſt our Lord, for our Sanctification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And their<note n="†" place="margin">P. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Summ of Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1686. ſaith, <hi>A Sacrament is a viſible Sign inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt, to convey his Grace into our Souls, and to apply unto us the merits of his death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then it is agreed between us, that theſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi> The word of Inſtitution, a viſible Sign, and a promiſe of inviſible Grace, are abſolutely neceſſary to make and conſtitute a Sacrament. And it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52954:14"/> is acknowledged on all hands, that theſe three are to be found in the Sacrament of Baptiſm and the Lords Supper. The diſpute therefore between us is, concerning the Five additional Sacraments of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Of which we ſay, That they want either the Word, or the Element, or both. <hi>Matrimony, Order,</hi> and <hi>Penance,</hi> have the word of God, but they have no outward Element; <hi>Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> and <hi>Confirmation</hi> have neither Word nor Element. But this Gentleman contends, That theſe Five, as well as the other Two, are founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Doctrine of the Fathers, and the Sence of the Scripture. And here, I confeſs, the Vindicator hath taken a great deal of pains, but to little purpoſe; he hath ſweat and toil'd, and at laſt found out a great many Fathers, who have called them Sacraments; which is a thing that no body would have deny'd him upon his own bare word. For, That many things, which indeed, and by ſpecial property, are no Sacraments, may nevertheleſs paſs under the general name of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he muſt be a very great ſtranger to the Writings of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who will not acknowledge it. We very well know that it was uſual with the Fathers, to call any ſacred Sign, or Myſtery in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or any holy ſignificant Rite, by the name of a Sacrament. And in this Sence he might reckon not only ſeven, but ſeventy, or more if he pleaſed, for he may furniſh himſelf with great variety. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> calls the Stick which <hi>Eliſha</hi> cut down, caſt into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Tertul. adverſ. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos.</note> and made the Iron ſwim, <hi>Sacramentum Ligni,</hi> the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Wood. And the ſame Father calls the whole State of the Chriſtian Faith,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Contr. Marcion, l. 4.</p>
                     <p>Aug. in Sermone de Sanctis 19.</p>
                     <p>Leo de Reſurrect. Domini, Serm. 2.</p>
                     <p>Hieron. ad Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</p>
                     <p>Inter Decreta Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, c. 14.</p>
                     <p>Aug. de peccat. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. &amp; remiſſ. l. 2.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Religionis Chriſtianae Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> The Sacrament of the Chriſtian Religion. And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Sacrament of the Croſs.</hi> And <hi>Leo</hi> calls the <hi>Croſs of Chriſt</hi> both <hi>a Sacrament</hi> and <hi>an Example.</hi> And St. <hi>Jerome</hi> calls the Water and Blood which iſſued out of the ſide of the bleſſed Jeſus, <hi>the Sacraments of Baptiſm and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom.</hi> And <hi>Leo</hi> calls the vow of Virginity, <hi>a Sacrament.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> calls the Bread that was given unto the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices or Beginners in the Faith called <hi>Catechumens,</hi> before they were baptized; <hi>a Sacrament.</hi> And if he will but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult St. <hi>Hilary</hi> he may find in him theſe expreſſions,<note place="margin">Hilar. in Matth. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. 11, 12, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Prayer, the Sacrament of Hunger, the Sacrament of the Scriptures, The Sacrament of Weeping,</hi> and <hi>the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Thirſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. in Sermone de Coena Domini.</note> And St. <hi>Bernard</hi> calls our Saviour's waſhing of the Diſciples Feet, <hi>the Sacrament of daily ſins.</hi> I ſuppoſe he will not call all theſe Sacraments of the new Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and if not, then muſt he aknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that there are Sacraments to be found in the Fathers, beſides
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52954:14"/> thoſe that are properly ſo called. The truth is, the Fathers ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpake Metaphorically, and ſometimes properly; ſometimes they ſpake more looſely, and ſometimes more cloſely; ſometimes they ſpake of things as they were in themſelves, and by ſpecially property ſuch, and ſometime by way of alluſion, and as in a general ſence they might be called ſuch. And if we be not careful to difference theſe ſeveral ways and manners of ſpeech in the reading of them, we may unawares fall into great errors and miſtakes. This is plain in the matter now before us. All are not Sacraments properly ſo called, which they call ſo; we are therefore to diſtinguiſh between their expreſſions when they ſpeak of a thing <hi>obitèr,</hi> and by the bye, and when they treat of it deſignedly and on ſet purpoſe. And if we conſider their Writings, when in the latter way they treat of this ſubject, we ſhall find that they men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no more Sacraments but only two. St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Then may they be throughly ſanctified,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Cypr. l. 2. Ep. 1. ad Steph.</p>
                     <p>Aug. de Doctrina Chriſtiana l. 3. c. 9.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and become the Children of God, if they be new-born by</hi> both <hi>the Sacraments.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Our Lord and his Apoſtles have delivered unto us</hi> a few <hi>Sacraments inſtead of many, and the ſame in doing moſt eaſie, in ſignification moſt excellent, in obſervation moſt reverend, as is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſm, and the Celebration of the Body and Blood of our Lord.</hi> And again the ſame holy Father ſpeaking of Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord, ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Aug. de Symbolo ad Catechumenos.</p>
                     <p>Paſchaſius de Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Domini.</p>
                     <p>Beſſarion de Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Euchariſtiae.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Theſe be the</hi> two <hi>Sacraments of the Church.</hi> And <hi>Paſchaſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Theſe be the Sacraments of Chriſt in the Catholick Church, Baptiſm and the Body and Blood of our Lord.</hi> And Cardinal <hi>Beſſarion</hi> ſaith, <hi>We read, that theſe</hi> only two <hi>Sacraments were delivered us plainly in the Goſpel.</hi> Here you have <hi>Both</hi> the Sacraments, and the <hi>Two</hi> Sacraments, and the <hi>Only Two</hi> Sacraments of the Church. Whence it is plain, that though the Fathers ſometimes, either in heat of this diſcourſe, or for a Rhetorical flouriſh, might call thoſe Sacraments, which properly ſpeaking, were not ſo; yet when they did deſignedly and on ſet purpoſe ſpeak of them, they mentioned only <hi>Two,</hi> which, I think, may be a ſufficient anſwer to his Authorities. But he has yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reſerve to bring up, and that is, That all theſe are founded upon the ſence of the Scripture. Let us ſee how, whether this will any more avail him, than the Authority of the Fathers hath done.</p>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Of the pretended Sacrament of <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO eſtabliſh this, he produceth <hi>Acts</hi> viij. 17, 18. where it is ſaid, <hi>Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt. And when Simon ſaw that through laying on of the Apoſtles hands, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52954:15"/> Holy Ghoſt was given, he offered them money.</hi> Here we have a narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of matter of Fact, but nothing that looks like a Sacrament in it; for, here is neither any word of Inſtitution, nor any outward Element; which are things agreed to be abſolutely neceſſary to the making or conſtituting of a Sacrament. Here is no mention of Chriſm, or Unction, or of the blow on the Ear, or of the Head-band, which are look'd upon as things neceſſary, and of the Eſſence of the pretended Popiſh Sacrament of Confirmation. Beſides, the Impoſition of hands by the Apoſtles in this place, was not to celebrate a Sacrament to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or ſtrengthen Baptiſm, but to conferr miraculous and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gifts, <hi>i. e.</hi> to give the Holy Ghoſt. This <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſaw, and therefore offered money for that gift, which he would never have done for Popiſh Confirmation. To this I may add the teſtimony of their own <hi>Alexander de Hales,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Alex. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. part 4. qu. 24. memb. 1.</note> who ſaith, <hi>The Sacrament of Confirmation, as it is a Sacrament, was neither inſtituted by our Lord himſelf, nor by his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but was afterwards instituted in the Council of</hi> Melda. So that though this may be an ancient Rite, it can be but a new Sacrament, <hi>i. e.</hi> no Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Of the pretended Sacrament of <hi>Penance.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO prove this, he produceth, <hi>John</hi> xx. 22. Where it is ſaid, <hi>He breathed on them, and ſaith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and v. 23. <hi>Whoſeſoever ſins ye remit, they are remitted unto them; and whoſeſoever ſins ye retain, they are retained.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before I give a direct anſwer hereunto, let me premiſe; That the difference between <hi>us</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this point is not, Whether Penance be neceſſary to Salvation, or whether men ought to confeſs their ſins, amend their lives, and turn unto God by true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; but whether this Penance be a Sacrament, wherein a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſinner ought punctually to confeſs his ſins to a Prieſt, and from him to receive judicial Abſolution, upon condition to make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto God by Corporal or Pecuniary Penance, which whoſoever doth not accompliſh in this life, ſhall ſuffer for it in Purgatory?</p>
                  <p>The former of theſe we willingly aſſent to, as being founded on the Word of God; but the latter we reject, as having no foundation either in this, or any other Text of Scripture.</p>
                  <p>That our Saviour here doth commit to his Church the power of the Keyes <hi>i. e.</hi> of publick Diſcipline, by virtue whereof ſhe hath Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to admit into, or caſt out of the Church, ſuch as ſhe ſhall judge worthy of it; we readily grant, and do heartily bewail the want of it. But that it is of ſuch abſolute neceſſity, that the truly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52954:15"/> penitent ſinner cannot receive Pardon of ſins without it, we cannot ſubſcribe to.<note place="margin">Lyra in loc.</note> And this is all that their own <hi>Lyra</hi> can find in theſe words.</p>
                  <p>But the Vindicator, in compliance with the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſſ. 14. cap. 1. &amp; Can. 1.</note> (which teacheth, <hi>That thoſe who fall from Grace after Baptiſm, have need of another Sacrament to reſtore them, and therefore our Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted this of Penance, and Anathematizeth all thoſe who deny this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi>) hath found out a Sacrament in theſe words. But if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did by theſe words Inſtitute a Sacrament, I would fain know, which is the Element or Viſible Sign Inſtituted by Chriſt; for this, on both ſides, is acknowledged to be a neceſſary part of a Sacrament. According to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> this Sacrament conſiſts of Four Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Contrition, Confeſſion, Abſolution, and Satisfaction. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of the Heart can be no ſenſible nor viſible Sign. Nor can Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion pretend to it; for, 1. Confeſſion is ſo far from being a Sign of the Grace of God, that it is a declaration that we are unworthy of his Grace. 2. It is deſigned not to ſignify the Grace of God, but to ask it. 3. The ſacred Signs ought to be adminiſtred by the Prieſt, but Confeſſion is made by the Penitent. Nor can Abſolution lay any claim to it; for, 1. Abſolution, if it be good and available, is the Grace of God; and therefore cannot be a Sign of it. 2. If it could be a Sign, yet can it not be a Viſible Sign, for the words are not Viſible. Nor can Satisfaction pretend to it, for that is accompliſhed by the Sinner, and not adminiſtred by the Prieſt. So that in all theſe we can find no outward Element, or Viſible Sign of Inviſible Grace, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt; and without that it cannot be a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>There is one thing yet which may make ſome colourable pretence to it, and that is, The Impoſition of the Prieſt's Hands. This we confeſs is a Viſible Sign: But, 1. It is no Element, but an Action; as the diſtribution of the Bread in the Lord's Supper is not the Element, but the Bread ſanctified. 2. This Impoſition of Hands is not of Chriſt's Ordination or Inſtitution, and therefore cannot be a Sacramental Sign: He did never command, That the Prieſt ſhould lay his Hands on any one to conferr Sacramental Abſolution. If he did, let them produce the command.</p>
                  <p>But if we review theſe words, we ſhall find, that they were ſpoken to the Apoſtles after that Chriſt was riſen again from the Dead. And if ſo, then Repentance preached before, whether by the Prophets,<note place="margin">Matth. iij. Mark i. 15. Acts ij. 38. Concil. Trid. Seſſ. 14. c. 1.</note> or by St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, or by Chriſt himſelf, was no Sacrament; nor that preached by St. <hi>Peter</hi> after the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe the perſons to whom he preached were not then Baptized. For thus the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath determined the point; <hi>Repentance was not a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52954:16"/> Sacrament before the coming of Chriſt, nor after his coming, is ſo to any one before Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And yet all good Chriſtians in the Primitive and pureſt Times of the Church, for many hundred Years after Chriſt, never knew, nor dream'd of any other Penance, than what had been preached either by the Prophets, or by St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, or by Chriſt himſelf, or by his Apoſtles; nor ever doubted of obtaining Pardon thereby. The truth is,<note place="margin">Anno. 1215.</note> till the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> we do not find, that ever Penance, as it is now uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was determin'd to be of neceſſary Obſervance.<note place="margin">Anno. 1546.</note> Nor till the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> that it was required to be received as a Sacrament of divine Inſtitution, and abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
                  <p>All which conſidered, notwithſtanding this Gentleman's Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I think we may ſafely conclude, That though Repentance be an old Duty, yet it is but a new Sacrament; and that Penance, as it is now uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is neither a Duty nor a Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Of the pretended Sacrament of <hi>Extream Unction.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO prove this, he produceth <hi>James</hi> v. 14, 15. where it is ſaid, <hi>Is any ſick among you? let him call for the Elders of the Church; and let them pray over him, anointing him with Oil, in the Name of the Lord: And the prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſick, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him up; and if he have committed ſins, they ſhall be forgiven him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This place of Scripture hath been often enough brought upon the ſtage by one or other of the <hi>Roman</hi> party; and as often conſidered, and the Arguments drawn from it baffled by ſome of our Men. And therefore when I met with it here, I did expect that this Gentleman, who is ſo brisk at a Vindication, had found ſome new Matter in it, and thereby cut us out ſome new Work; but inſtead of that, he only quotes the place, tranſcribes the words, and leaves them to ſhift for themſelves.</p>
                  <p>What therefore is here to be done by us, ſave only to conſider the deſign of the Apoſtle in theſe Words? Which is plainly this; St. <hi>James</hi> directs the ſick perſon, <hi>to call for the Elders of the Church,</hi> to aſſiſt him in that condition. The means by which they were to aſſiſt him are Two, 1. They were to <hi>pray over him.</hi> And, 2. To <hi>anoint him with Oil, in the Name of the Lord.</hi> And that in order to Two ends, 1. The Recovery of the Sick. 2. The Remiſſion of Sins. Of theſe Means and Ends, the one is Perpetual, <hi>viz.</hi> Prayer and Remiſſion of Sins; the other Temporary, <hi>viz.</hi> The Anointing with Oil, and the Recovery of bodily Health. That the Apoſtles had the Gift of Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52954:16"/> we grant; and that in order to the working of their miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Cures, they did uſe the Ceremony of Anointing with Oil, we deny not; but the Gift of Healing being now ceaſed in the Church, that Ceremony is become uſeleſs and unprofitable, and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon laid aſide; for God loves no unprofitable Signs. Whilſt it was in uſe, it was uſed only in Order to bodily health, but now, in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is not to be uſed whilſt there are any hopes of Recovery, but only in <hi>Articulo mortis,</hi> when Men are at the point of Death, as a <hi>viaticum</hi> into the other World.</p>
                  <p>That this was deſign'd and uſed only in order to bodily health, is plain from the Ancient Rituals of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, for above Eight hundred Years after Chriſt. And Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> freely confeſſeth,<note place="margin">Annot. in loc.</note> that this was the only uſe of it, for ſaith he, <hi>Theſe words of St.</hi> James <hi>ſpeak not of the Sacramental <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, whether we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the words or the Effects of them; but rather of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, which the Lord Jeſus ordained in the Goſpel, to be uſed by his Diſciples to the Sick. For the Text ſaith not,</hi> Is any ſick to Death? <hi>but abſolutely,</hi> Is any ſick? <hi>Nor doth it aſſign any other uſe of anointing of the ſick perſon, but only the recovery of bodily health.</hi> And the Ingenuous <hi>Caſſander,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caſſand. in Conſult. Art. 22.</note> without any heſitation, freely delivers his Opinion, ſaying, <hi>It is no Sacrament pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, becauſe it hath neither Word of Inſtitution, nor outward Element.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The eldeſt Evidence that we meet with for this pretended Popiſh Sacrament of <hi>Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> is, the Council of <hi>Chalons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anno. 813.</note> which was held above Eight hundred Years after Chriſt; and was but at beſt a National Synod neither. So that though we do not deny, but that Anointing the Sick with Oil, was a very Ancient Rite; yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but look upon it as a very New Sacrament, and one that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver advanc'd to that honour by any Appointmant of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Of the pretended Sacrament of <hi>Orders.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TO evince this, he produceth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> i. 6. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtir up the Gift of God, which is in thee, by the putting on of my Hands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> here admoniſheth his Son <hi>Timothy</hi> to a vigorous exerciſe of that Power and Authority, which, by the Impoſition of his Hands, he had received, to Preach the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Lyra in loc.</note> And this is all that their own <hi>Lyra</hi> can find in this place.</p>
                  <p>But the Queſtion between us is not, Whether the Office of a Prieſt ought to be conferred upon him by the Impoſition of Hands; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52954:17"/> ſuch Ordination be a Sacrament of the new Law, inſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer, That if by the word, <hi>Sacrament,</hi> they only mean any ſacred Sign, or Myſtery in Religion, (in which ſence it is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed, eſpecially by the Latine Fathers) we can very willingly and readily admit this Impoſition of hands to be called a Sacrament. But if they would advance it higher, and have it called a Sacrament in the ſame ſence, as Baptiſm and the Supper of the Lord are; or as this Article requires, That we ſhould receive it as a Sacrament of the New Law, inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt, and neceſſary for the Salvation of Mankind; we cannot in this conſent with them, and that for theſe Reaſons: I. Becauſe Impoſition of hands, though it be a Sign, yet is it not a ſacred Sign of the Covenant of God in Jeſus Chriſt. II. Becauſe it is not common to all the Faithful, but confin'd to a certain order of Men only. III. Becauſe there is no expreſs Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it to be found in the Holy Scriptures of the New Teſtament, and conſequently no promiſe of Grace annexed to it. IV. Becauſe it is well known, that many of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, do not think Impoſition of hands to be Eſſential to Holy Orders, and if not, then can it be no outward Sign of a Sacrament in them: Nor can Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation it ſelf be a Sacrament, ſeeing there is no outward viſible Sign of it ordained by God. For theſe Reaſons, Though we acknowledge the Conferring of Orders by Impoſition of hands, to have been a very ancient uſage in the Church, and of Apoſtolical practice; yet we think it to be a very new, <hi>i. e.</hi> no Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sacrament">
                  <head>Of the pretended Sacrament of <hi>Matrimony.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AS an evidence of this, he produceth <hi>Eph.</hi> v. 31, 32. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>For this cauſe ſhall a man leave his Father and Mother, and ſhall be joined to his Wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh. This is a great myſtery, but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and his Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> calls the marriage of Prieſts, Sacrilege; and yet will have the Marriage of Lay-men to be a Sacrament, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs juſtifying Grace. And to prove this the Vindicator alledgeth this Text of Scripture, as many others before him have done, and have received their anſwer; but as if there had been no ſuch thing, this Gentleman with ſufficient confidence, barely cites it, and ſo leaves it.</p>
                  <p>To which however I ſhall return this anſwer, The Apoſtle in this place (as is plain to every conſiderate Reader) ſpeaketh of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Union between Jeſus Chriſt and his Church; which Union he illuſtrates by that of Marriage between the Husband and the Wife. His
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52954:17"/> intent was not to exalt the Myſtery of Marriage, but the Union of the Church with Jeſus Chriſt. This Myſtery then whereof he ſpeaketh, is the Myſtical Union between Jeſus Chriſt and his Church, and not the Union between the Husband and the Wife. For having ſaid, <hi>This is a great Myſtery,</hi> that we might not think that he ſpake of the Myſtery of Marriage, he addeth, <hi>But I ſpeak concerning Jeſus Chriſt and his Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the Vulgar Tranſlation of this Text calls it, <hi>a Sacrament;</hi> we grant it, but doth this prove Marriage to be a Sacrament? Will the Vindicator own all thoſe things, which in the Vulgar Tranſlation are called Sacraments, to be Sacraments of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Then the great Whore mentioned in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> muſt be one of their Sacraments, for ſo the Vulgar Tranſlation calls her, <hi>Rev.</hi> xvij. 7. And the ſeven Stars, mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> i. 20. muſt be another, for ſo they are there called. And Dreams and Viſions muſt be a third, for ſo they are three times called, <hi>Dan.</hi> ij. 18, 30, 47. And Piety is called a great Sacrament, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> iij. 16. I ſuppoſe he will not own theſe to be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet in their Authentick Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they are called Sacraments, as well as Marriage.</p>
                  <p>But that Marriage is no Sacrament of the New Law, inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt; among many others, we have theſe reaſons to ſatisfy our ſelves: I. Becauſe it was not inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt, for it was in the World before his time. If after his coming, the bleſſed Jeſus did change the nature of it, and make it a Sacrament, then let them ſhew us when and where he did it. II. Becauſe, as it hath no word of Inſtitution, ſo neither hath it any viſible Sign or outward Element; for neither the words, nor the actions are Elements; and unleſs there be an Element, to which the word of Inſtitution is joined, it can be no Sacrament. III. Becauſe there is no promiſe of Grace annexed to any outward Element; for, though the ſtate of Matrimony be a ſign of that Myſtical Union between Chriſt and his Church, having ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogy with it; ye we do not know, that the entrance into this ſtate hath the promiſe of any Grace, to join, or preſerve us in that Union with Chriſt and his Church. And for theſe reaſons, we exclude it from the Sacraments of the New Law, inſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with all the requiſites of a Sacrament properly ſo called. And for our ſo doing, we do not want Authorities among the eminent Doctors of the Roman Church. I ſhall only give you two inſtances. Their own <hi>Durandus</hi> delivers his opinion in plain terms, telling us,<note place="margin">Durand. in ſentent. l. 4. Diſt. 26. q. 3. Cajetan, Annot. in loc.</note> 
                     <hi>That ſtrictly and properly ſpeaking, Marriage is not a Sacrament.</hi> And Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> upon this place of Scripture cited by the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, hath theſe words, <hi>Prudent Reader, thou learneſt not here of St.</hi> Paul, <hi>that Marriage is a Sacrament; for he ſaith not,</hi> This Sacrament, <hi>but</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52954:18"/> this Myſtery <hi>is great;</hi> and in truth the Myſtery of thoſe words is great.</p>
                  <p>Thus it appears, that neither from Antiquity, nor the written Word of God, any of theſe five Additional Sacraments of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> viz. <hi>Confirmation, Penance, Extream <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction, Order,</hi> and <hi>Matrimony;</hi> can with any juſtice plead the ſame title to be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the New Law, inſtituted by Chriſt, and neceſſary for the Salvation of Mankind; as it is confeſſed on all hands, Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper may.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I do alſo receive and admit of all the received and approved Ceremonies of the Catholick Church, uſed in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the above-mentioned Sacraments.</q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. xiv. 40.</note>
                  <hi>THAT all things are to be done decently and in order,</hi> we own to be an Apoſtolical precept, and that in point of duty we ſtand ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to yield Obedience thereunto. We alſo acknowledge that the Superiors in every Society are the proper Judges of that Decency and Order. And that it always hath been, and ſtill is the practice of all well-ordered Societies, to ſubmit to the Determination of their Superiors therein. And that to invert this Order, or for private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to take upon them to dictate to their Governours in this caſe, is the only way to introduce Anarchy and Confuſion. Which is all, or at leaſt the ſubſtance of all, that the Vindicator here offers in behalf of this Article. But after this Conceſſion, there are ſome things ſtill ſtick with us, which will not ſuffer us to ſubſcribe thereunto; <hi>viz.</hi> I. Becauſe we are required to receive it, not only as an Article of Communion but as an Article of Faith; under the penalty of an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema,</hi> though it only concern Ceremonies, which are things muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the pleaſure of the Church. II. Becauſe the Ceremonies here ſpoken of, or ſome of them, neither are, nor ever were received, nor approved by the Catholick Church. III. Becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church (as they call it) is but a particular Church, and hath no more power to impoſe Ceremonies or Uſages upon any other Church, than that other hath to impoſe upon Her. For, <hi>Par in parem non habet imperium.</hi> IV. If any Ceremonies impoſed by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> or any other Church, be ſuch, as that the Members of that Church cannot comply with them without ſin and danger; the general rule of the Apoſtle doth not in that caſe bind to blind Obedience. For then there is an Apoſtolical pattern, which muſt take place, <hi>Whether it be better to obey God, or man, judge ye,</hi> Acts iv. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52954:18"/>
               <q>I embrace and receive all and every thing, which in the Holy Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath been defin'd, concerning <hi>Original Sin,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>IN defence of this Article, and to perſwade us to a compliance therewith, the Vindicator proceeds in this method. I. He un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to give us an account of what the Council hath defin'd in theſe two points. And II. To vindicate thoſe their Definitions. Now whether he hath been faithful in his account, or whether the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Council, or his Vindication of them be ſuch, as may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to comply with him and the Council therein, are the things we are now to enquire into.</p>
               <p n="1">I. As touching <hi>Original Sin,</hi> it muſt be acknowledged that the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator hath faithfully ſet down the Doctrine thereof, as it is defin'd by the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> But notwithſtanding the Authority of this Council, or the ſtrength of the Proofs (which indeed are weak enough) whereby he endeavours to defend its Definition of this point; yet there are ſome things we cannot comply with, and till we are convinc'd by better Arguments than are here offered, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not embrace all and every thing, which in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath been defin'd in this point.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the difference here is not very great, and no new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter offered, but only ſuch as hath been over and over again conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and refuted; and becauſe there are matters of greater moment ſtill behind,<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 5. Decret. de peccat. Origin. Can. 5.</note> I ſhall only deſire the Vindicator once more to read over that very Decree upon which this part of the Article, which he is here defending, is founded, and conſider one paſſage therein, which perhaps he might before overlook. And then I ſhall proceed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the latter part of this Article.</p>
               <p>The Paſſage is this; the Council doth there declare, <hi>That Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence doth ſtill remain even in thoſe that are baptized,</hi> and doth further declare, <hi>that St.</hi> Paul <hi>did ſometimes call this Concupiſcence, Sin.</hi> But though the Apoſtle did ſo, yet the Council tells us, <hi>That the Catholick Church</hi> (no doubt the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick) <hi>did never think it to be ſo. And if any one think otherwiſe, let him be Anathema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the beginning of this Decree the Council pretends to have the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt; whether they had or no, is not eaſie to be granted; but it is confeſſed on all hands, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was inſpired from above; and if ſo, then how comes the Council and he to be at odds in this matter? Either the Apoſtle or the Council were in the wrong, for both parts of a Contradiction cannot be true. Now
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52954:19"/> whether the Authority of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or that of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> be the better, one would think were no very hard Queſtion. St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I am ſure, did not think it was; for if he had, he would not have been ſo poſitive as he was,<note place="margin">Aug ad Hieron. Epiſt. 19.</note> when he ſaid, <hi>The Authority of St.</hi> Paul <hi>is to me inſtead of all the Fathers, and above all the Fathers; to him I flee, and to him I appeal from all other Doctors whatſoever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Concerning Juſtification, he gives us an account of what the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath defin'd in Four particulars:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Men are juſtified by an intrinſecal Juſtice. And this he founds upon Two places of Scripture, <hi>viz. Tit.</hi> iij. 7. where it is ſaid, <hi>That being juſtified by his Grace, we ſhould be made Heirs, according to the hope of Eternal Life. Which Grace,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is in Men.</hi> And for this he quotes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> i. 6. where it is ſaid, <hi>I put thee in mind to ſtir up that Grace which is in thee.</hi> So he renders it; but it is more properly tranſlated, <hi>I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtir up the Gift, of God, which is in thee, by the putting on my Hands.</hi> Which laſt words he leaves out.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer. What St. <hi>Paul</hi> here means, by being <hi>juſtified by his Grace,</hi> he himſelf very well explains in another place, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. iij. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Being juſtified freely by his Grace, through the Redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Where to be <hi>juſtified Freely,</hi> and to be <hi>juſtified by Grace,</hi> are Synonymous Expreſſions, and imply no more, but that God did freely, and without any merit of ours, ſend his Son to die for ſinners; and by his Death to make ſatisfaction to divine Juſtice for our ſins; and by that means to obtain ſuch Grace and Favour with God, that our Sins might be Pardoned, and we Juſtified before him. whence it is very plain, That by the Grace of God, we are not to underſtand any intrinſecal Righteouſneſs of our own, but the free Grace and Favour of God, in accepting the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, inſtead of ours, and imputing the ſame to us, through Faith, for our Juſtification. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> after he had a little more Explain'd himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 28.</note> concludes, ſaying, <hi>Therefore we conclude, that a man is juſtified by Faith, without the Deeds of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for his other Scripture, which he brings in as an Auxiliary Proof, it is quite foreign to the matter in hand; for the Apoſtle there doth not ſpeak of Juſtifying Grace, nor indeed of any Grace, if we take the word ſtrictly; for the word there is not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies not <hi>Grace,</hi> but <hi>a Gift.</hi> And the Gift which he there puts him in mind to ſtir up, was <hi>the Gift of preaching.</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, Be ſure couragiouſly to preach the Goſpel, and exerciſe that Miniſterial Function, which thou haſt received by the Impoſition of my Hands.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:52954:19"/>
               <p>But I find this Gentleman is under a great miſtake, he takes Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Sanctification to be one and the ſame thing; but I cannot much blame him for it, becauſe I know he is led into it by an Authority, which he thinks, to be Infallible, and conſequently Indiſputable, <hi>viz.</hi> the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which teacheth him,<note place="margin">Seſſ. 6. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>That Juſtification conſiſts not only in Remiſſion of Sins, but in Sanctification alſo and the renewing of the inward Man, by a voluntary ſuſception of Grace and Gifts; by which, of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous a Man is made Righteous, and of an Enemy a Friend, that he may be an Heir according to the Hope of Eternal Life.</hi> This is a far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Notion from that which the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Holy Scriptures give us of Juſtification. They teach us, That by Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we are to underſtand only Abſolution, or Remiſſion of Sins; but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> confounds Juſtification with Sanctification, and the Remiſſion of Sins with the Renovation of our Minds. And indeed in this Channel runs the main difference between us and them through the whole Controverſie. The Church of <hi>England</hi> delivers her Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments touching Juſtification thus:<note place="margin">Art. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>We are accounted Righteous before God only for the merit of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, by Faith, and not for our own works or deſervings. Wherefore that we are juſtifyed by Faith only, is a moſt wholeſome Doctrine, and very full of comfort.</hi> And for a farther Explication thereof, ſhe refers to the Homily of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; where ſhe declares, <hi>That by Juſtification,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Hom. <hi>of Juſtificat.</hi> part 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhe means the Forgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Sins and Treſpaſſes. That this being received of God's Mercy and Chriſt's Merits, embraced by Faith, is taken and allowed of God for our perfect and full Juſtification. That nothing on the behalf of Man, doth contribute to this Juſtification, but only a true and lively Faith, which Faith is alſo the Gift of God: Yet doth not this Faith exclude Good-works, nor the neceſſity of them in Juſtified Perſons, but only ſhuts them out from the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Juſtifying.</hi> This is the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and for this ſhe hath good Authority both in Scripture and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but I muſt not now enter upon this Controverſie, leſt I loſe the Vindicator therein. I ſhall therefore proceed to his next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He tells us, That the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath defin'd, <hi>That all Works of the Juſt are not Sins.</hi> This, ſaith he, is evident in Scripture, as <hi>Luke</hi> i. 6. where 'tis ſaid of <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, They were both Righteous before God; walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord, blameleſs.</hi> And 1 <hi>John</hi> v. 18. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not.</hi> Which likewiſe proves, <hi>That the Commandments are not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be kept,</hi> as the ſame Council declares.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, If the Premiſſes be good, the Inference there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, I confeſs, is natural; For if Juſtified perſons be ſo Righteous,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52954:20"/> as to be void of all Sin, they may, no doubt, keep all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But if the Foundation which he builds upon happen to fail him, all his Superſtructure will fall to the Ground. Let us therefore Examine that, whether it be firm and good.</p>
               <p>In order whereunto let me premiſe, That there is a Legal and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Righteouſneſs: The former of which conſiſts in a perfect and unſinning Obedience to the whole Law: And the latter in a ſincere deſire and endeavour to keep all God's Commandments. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe, it is not in the power of fallen Man, to attain unto: And to juſtifie this Aſſertion, we have good warrant from the Holy Scriptures; The wiſe <hi>Soloman,</hi> in his Prayer at the Dedication of the Temple, humbly confeſſeth, <hi>There is no Man that ſinneth not,</hi> 1 Kings viij. 46. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>The Scripture hath concluded all under Sin,</hi> Gal. iij. 22. And St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>In many things we offend al,</hi> Jam. iij. 2. <hi>And if we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the Truth is not in us,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>John</hi> 1 <hi>Ep. c.</hi> i. <hi>v.</hi> 8. I might add many more places of Scripture to this purpoſe, but theſe may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſhow us, how far it is out of the power of fallen Man, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form a perfect and unſinning Obedience to the Law of God. But the latter, <hi>viz.</hi> an Evangelical Righteouſneſs, we acknowledge to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in this Life. It is poſſible for a good Man ſincerely to deſire, and honeſtly to endeavour to keep all the Commandments of his God; and though he fail in the attempt, by reaſon of the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and depravation of his Nature; yet God, for Chriſt's ſake, will pardon thoſe Failings, and accept of thoſe his honeſt Endeavours <hi>For if there be firſt a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a Man hath, and not according to that he hath not,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> viij. 12 And according to this Notion of Righteouſneſs it is,<note place="margin">Hierom. ad Ctefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. Aug. ad Bonifaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, l. 3. c. 7.</note> that holy and good Men are ſaid to be Juſt and Righteous. So St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Men are called juſt, not becauſe they are void of all Sin; but becauſe in the main they are Vertuous.</hi> And S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Vertue that is now in a juſt Man, ſo far forth is called perfect, that it pertaineth to the perfection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, both in Truth to know, and in Humility to confeſs, that it is imperfect.</hi> And the ſame St. <hi>Aug.</hi> in another place ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 19 c. 26.</hi> Ipſa noſtra ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia, quamvis vera ſit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter veri boni finem ad quem refertur, tamen tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt in hac vita, ut potius peccatorum remiſſione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet, quam perfectione vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum.</note> 
                  <hi>Our very Righteouſneſs it ſelf is ſuch in this life, that it ſtands rather in the Remiſſion of Sins, than in the perfection of Righteouſneſs.</hi> Thus <hi>Job,</hi> by the Mouth of God himſelf, is ſtiled, <hi>A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and upright Man, one that feared God, and eſchewed evil,</hi> Job i. 8. and yet he curſed <hi>the day of his Birth,</hi> c. iij. And thus <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are ſaid to be both <hi>Righteous before God, and to walk in all the Commandments and Ordinances blameleſs,</hi> i. e. Their Lives and Converſations were ſo good
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52954:20"/> and vertuous, that no Man had any juſt cauſe to blame them. But that they were without ſin, doth not appear; but the contrary is very manifeſt, for not long after we find <hi>Zacharias</hi> puniſhed for his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief,</hi> Luk. i. 20.</p>
               <p>His other Scripture Proof (which is 1 <hi>John</hi> v. 18. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, ſinneth not,</hi>) will do him no better ſervice than his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. For the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>c.</hi> i. <hi>v.</hi> 8. ſaith, <hi>If we ſay, that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us.</hi> If therefore the Text by him alledged, be ſo to be underſtood, as if the Regenerate were free from all manner of ſin; then muſt he ſay that St. <hi>John,</hi> and thoſe he ſpeaks of in the other Text, were not born of God, or elſe that he contradicts himſelf in theſe two places; neither of which, I preſume, they will dare to ſay. We muſt therefore find out another ſence of theſe words, which methinks is very obvious. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God, ſinneth not,</hi> i. e. He doth not make a trade of ſin, or he doth not deliberately, and on ſet purpoſe ſin againſt God. This their own <hi>Lyra,</hi> if he had conſulted him, would have told him; for he ſaith,<note place="margin">Lyra in loc.</note> 
                  <hi>That the intention of the Apoſtle in this place, is not to ſecure the Regenerate from all ſin, but from that ſin unto death,</hi> of which he ſpeaks, <hi>v.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Thus have I examined his proofs, and find them to fall far ſhort of proving what he pretends to prove by them. But if I ſhould grant his Propoſition, which he calls a Definition of the Council, to be true; yet I do not ſee how the poſſibility of keeping the Commandments can thence be inferred. <hi>All works of the juſt,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>are not ſins.</hi> What then; doth it neceſſarily follow, That it is poſſible for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate to keep all the Commandments? No ſurely; for though all be not, yet if any of them be, it will be a ſufficient bar to this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference; So St. <hi>James</hi> thought, or elſe he would not have ſaid, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet faileth in one point, he is guilty of all,</hi> Jam. ij. 10. Unleſs therefore they will underſtand, a poſſibility of keeping the Commandments,<note place="margin">Aug. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. l. 1. c. 19.</note> in the ſame ſence that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth (who tells us, <hi>All the Commandments of God are accounted to be done, when that thing that is not done, is forgiven</hi>) I do not ſee how it can be aſſerted, much leſs defended. And if thus they underſtand it, we ſhall not quarrel with them about it.</p>
               <p n="3">III. He tells us, That the Council hath defin'd, <hi>That a man juſtified, truly deſerves life everlaſting by his good works.</hi> And this he undertakes to prove both by Scripture, and the Teſtimony of St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I come particularly to examine his Proofs, the force of all which ſtands in a miſunderſtanding of the Words, <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> It will be convenient, for a more clear deciſion of the difference
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52954:21"/> between us, to ſtate the true notion of thoſe words; for Ambiguity of Words often hath been, and ſtill is, not only the occaſion of hot and fierce Diſputes among men, but of their continuance alſo.</p>
               <p>That the word, <hi>Merit,</hi> is frequently uſed by the Fathers we own; but that they uſed it in that ſence, in which the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, we deny; and thence ariſeth the difference between us. The Holy Fathers underſtood no more by it, than <hi>Obtaining</hi> or <hi>Impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but the Romaniſts would now have it to be underſtood of <hi>Earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Deſerving</hi> in the way of <hi>Condign Wages;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellarm de Juſtificat. l. 5. c. 17.</note> as if there were an equality of due proportion between our Works and Heaven, without any reſpect had to Pact, Promiſe or Favour.</p>
               <p>To make a work truly meritorious, it muſt have theſe five Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The work that is done, muſt not be a work that is due to be done. For it is no merit for a man to pay his debts. Now our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tells us, <hi>When we have done all thoſe things which are commanded us, we are ſtill but unprofitable Servants, having done only that which was our duty to do,</hi> Luke xvij. 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The thing we offer muſt be our own. For to preſent any thing to another that belongs unto him, is no merit in us. Now St. <hi>Paul.</hi> tells us, <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves, to think any thing as of our ſelves, but all our ſufficiency is of God,</hi> 2 Cor. iij. 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The work that a man doth to merit of another, muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to that other, of whom he deſigns to merit. For no man will pretend to merit by an unprofitable ſervice. Now holy <hi>David</hi> freely confeſſeth, That <hi>his Goodneſs did not extend to God,</hi> i. e. was no way profitable or advantageous to him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> xvi. 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The work we do to merit withal, muſt not be defective. For if there be any thing in it that wants a pardon, it can never truly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Now St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us,</hi> 1 John i. 8.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There muſt be ſome proportion between the Work and the Reward. Otherwiſe we cannot be ſaid to deſerve it. In St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s account, <hi>The afflictions of this preſent time</hi> (and certainly Suffering is more than Doing) <hi>are not worthy of the Glory which ſhall be revealed in us,</hi> Rom. viij. 18.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the requiſites of Merit, which if well attended to, may be very uſeful in deciding this Difficulty, and determining this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in difference between us. Let us now conſider the other word, <hi>viz. Reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Word, <hi>Reward,</hi> is frequently uſed both in Scripture, and by the Fathers, we own; and that the ſtrict and proper notion of it,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52954:21"/> is a <hi>Debt due to man for the work he hath done,</hi> we deny not. But that it was ever uſed in this ſence with reſpect to God, or that ever any man, according to this notion of the Word, can be ſaid to deſerve a reward at God's hands, we can by no means grant. And hence ariſeth the difference between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and us; in order to the deciding of which, let us conſider that there is a twofold Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the one due, the other not due; the one given as a juſt retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution for the work done, and the other freely, or, at moſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Pact and Promiſe. This diſtinction is fairly founded in Scripture, where St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>To him that worketh, the reward is not accounted to be of grace, but of debt,</hi> Rom. iv. 4. Which plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, that a free gift beſtowed out of meer bounty and liberality may be called a Reward, as well as that, which by the ſtrict rules of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is due to Merit. And thus we find it in Scripture ſometimes given to the one, and ſometimes to the other: For, that which in <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 46. is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Reward, in <hi>Luke</hi> vi. 32. is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Grace, or Free Gift. And the peny given to the labourer who came in at the laſt hour is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Reward, though much above his deſert, <hi>Matth.</hi> xx. 8.<note place="margin">Ambr. l. 1. Ep. 1.</note> Upon which St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> very well obſerves, <hi>There is a kind of Reward, which is given of liberality and of Grace, and another which is the wages of Vertue, and the recompence of a man's labour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus ſtated the true notion of theſe two words, <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Reward,</hi> upon which depends the whole Controverſie between us; I ſhall now take a more particular view of his Proofs.</p>
               <p>His firſt Scripture proof is, <hi>Rev.</hi> iij. 4. From which he thus argues, <hi>Thou haſt a few names in Sardis, which have not defiled their garments</hi> (there is Purity and Juſtice) <hi>and they ſhall walk with me in white,</hi> (there is the Reward, and the reaſon follows) <hi>for they are worthy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole ſtreſs of this Argument lies in the word <hi>worthy,</hi> a right underſtanding whereof, will facilitate our anſwer thereunto.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly ſaith, <hi>I reckon that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthy</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Condig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae ad fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam Gloriam. Vulg. Lat.</note> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>of the glory, which ſhall be ſhewed unto us,</hi> Rom. viij. 18. The <hi>Glory</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> here ſpeaks of, and the <hi>White Aray,</hi> which St. <hi>John</hi> mentions, do certainly import one and the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> Eternal Life. Of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, all our Sufferings, (and certainly they are more valuable than our Doings) are not worthy. And yet thoſe who had not defiled their garments, are ſaid <hi>to be worthy</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>to walk in white, i. e.</hi> to be made partakers of Life and Glory.</p>
               <p>This looks like a perfect contradiction, which we cannot ſuppoſe theſe two holy and inſpired Men could be guilty of: for, as they were
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52954:22"/> both taught by the ſame Spirit, ſo, no doubt, they both ſpake the ſame thing. To reconcile them therefore, we muſt find out another ſence of the Word, <hi>Worthy,</hi> than this Gentleman puts upon it; and, I think, it is no difficult matter ſo to do. For a Man may be ſaid to be worthy of a Reward either upon his own account, or upon the account of another; either for the ſake of his own deſervings, or for the ſake of another's merits. To be worthy in the former ſence, a Man muſt have all thoſe Requiſites and Qualifications, which are required to make up a Merit ſtrictly ſo called; but to be worthy in the other ſence, requires no more but only to be fitted and diſpoſed to receive thoſe favours, which are merited for him by another. That according to the latter of theſe notions we are to underſtand the worthyneſs here ſpoken of, will appear plainly; if we conſider, That the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is here rendred Worthy, may be, and often is rendred <hi>fit</hi> or <hi>meet;</hi> as for inſtance, St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt warns the Phariſees and Sadduces which came to his Baptiſm, <hi>To bring forth fruits</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>worthy of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. iij. 8. Luk. iij. 8.</note> or <hi>meet for, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> that ſo they might eſcape the wrath to come. <hi>i. e.</hi> Let your Reformation declare your Repentance to be ſuch, as may fit you to come to this Baptiſm, and conſequently to eſcape wrath; let your Repentance be according to the meaſure of your ſin, if your Sins have been great,<note place="margin">Lyra in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed. apud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. Ord. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oc.</note> ſo muſt your Repentance be too. So their own <hi>Lyra</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it. And the venerable <hi>Bede</hi> gives this reaſon for it, <hi>Becauſe the ſame meaſure of Repentance is not required of him who is guilty of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no Sin, as of him who hath more grievouſly offended.</hi> By fruits wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Repentance, we are therefore to underſtand ſuch fruits as are meet to teſtifie the truth of our Repentance, and fit us to receive Grace and Favour offered. And if we conſider the following words, they will farther confirm us herein; for it is added, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall be cloathed in white aray,</hi> &amp;c. Whence it is evident, that to walk in white, or to be worthy to do ſo, was not a privilege peculiar to thoſe <hi>few names in Sardis which had not defiled their garments,</hi> but to all others, who by Faith are armed with the power of Chriſt, and by that means obtain a Victory over the World and the Devil; for they alſo ſhall be cloathed with <hi>white aray.</hi> This well repreſents that Righteouſneſs wherewith all the bleſſed ones ſhall ſtand cloathed and covered before God; which is not their own, but a Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs given unto them by another, and put upon them. And is the ſame ſpoken of by holy <hi>David,</hi> and quoted by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had occaſion to treat of this argument.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. xxxij. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. iv. 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered. Bleſſed is the man, to whom the Lord imputeth not ſin.</hi> To be worthy therefore imports not, that Men do
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52954:22"/> merit eternal life by their works, but it imports a fitneſs and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in them to receive it, being juſtified by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, as their holy and godly life did declare.</p>
               <p>His next Scripture proof is, <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 12. <hi>Rejoice and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven:</hi> Whence he inferrs, that Heaven is given as a reward for their ſuffering, and good Works.</p>
               <p>That Heaven is a Reward, we grant, but it is a Reward of Grace, not of Debt; That it is given to thoſe that ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake and do well, we deny not; but it is not given them for their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or well-doing. And we acknowledge, that it is a great Reward, ſo great, that it far exceeds the merit of all that we can do or ſuffer; <hi>For our light afflictions which are but for a moment, work for us a far more exceeding</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>and eternal weight of glory,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. iv. 17.</p>
               <p>His laſt Scripture is, <hi>Matth.</hi> xxv. 34. where our Saviour is giving an account in what manner he will proceed in the laſt Judgment. What inference the Vindicator would draw from hence, he leave us to divine; for he only quotes it, and ſo leaves it; and ſo ſhall I too, till he thinks fit to form his argument, and bleſs the World with the ſight of it. But he cloſeth up his Scripture Arguments with this Salvo, <hi>All this as ſuppoſing and built upon the promiſe of Chriſt, and his aſſiſting grace.</hi> Which, if I miſtake not, is a full confutation of all that he hath been endeavouring to prove: For if our good works be done by his aſſiſting grace, (as undoubtedly they are) then are they not ſo our own, as to merit by them; and if our deſerving life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting muſt ſuppoſe, and be built upon the promiſe of Chriſt, then is it not a Reward of Debt, but of Grace, or by Pact and Promiſe; which is the thing we contend for.</p>
               <p>And now I come to examine his Authorities, which he brings out of two Epiſtles of St. <hi>Auſtin, viz.</hi> the 105. and the 118. <hi>ad Sixt.</hi> I have carefully read over theſe two Epiſtles, which, I queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Vindicator has done; for if he had, he would not have been guilty of ſo great a miſtake; for, the 118 Epiſtle is not directed to <hi>Sixtus</hi> (as he ſaith it is) but to <hi>Januarius;</hi> nor is there one word in it of all that he here quotes out of it, nor any one Syllable relating to that matter; it being wholly ſpent in directing him how to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf to the Cuſtoms of any particular Church where he came, provided they were not contrary to Faith and good manners, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the buſineſs <hi>of Faſting,</hi> and <hi>the Euchariſt.</hi> The 105. Epiſtle is indeed directed to <hi>Sixtus,</hi> (though he doth not tell us it is) and in that I meet with what he here ſets down; which makes me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture that he hath taken it from ſome other upon truſt; for if he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52954:23"/> did conſult the Author himſelf, he betrays a great want either of honeſty or ingenuity or both. For it is not honeſt in any man to cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail his Author's Sence, nor is it very ingenuous by that means to endeavour to impoſe upon unwary Readers. All therefore that I have here to do, is, to bring St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to ſpeak for himſelf, and ſo leave the unbyaſſed Reader to judge between us. The deſign of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in this Epiſtle is to inſtruct <hi>Sixtus</hi> how to anſwer the Arguments of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> who were then the great Advocates for <hi>Free Will</hi> and <hi>Merits,</hi> by advancing the Free Grace and Mercy of God againſt them. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in this Epiſtle hath theſe words which the Vindicator ſets down, <hi>viz. As death is rendred to the Merit of ſin, as the pay; ſo everlaſting life is rendred as the pay, to the merit of Juſtice.</hi> But he doth not tell you what goes before, nor what follows after thoſe words in that place; If he had you would more clearly have underſtood St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than perhaps he deſired you ſhould. To undeceive you therefore I ſtall give you the paſſage intire as it is in the Author. <hi>When St.</hi> Paul (ſaith he) <hi>in</hi> Rom. vi. 23. <hi>had ſaid, The wages of ſin is death, who would not have expected that he ſhould have added; and the wages of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is eternal life? And truly it is ſo, for as death is rendred to the merit of ſin, as the wages; ſo eternal life, as the wages, is rendred to the merit of Righteouſneſs. But the bleſſed Apoſtle to repreſs the pride of Men, ſaith,</hi> The Wages of Sin is Death. <hi>Truly Wages, becauſe due, becauſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily deſerved, becauſe rendred to Merit. But then to prevent the exalting of our ſelves upon the account of our own Merit or Righteouſneſs, he doth not ſay,</hi> The Wages of Righteouſneſs is eternal Life; <hi>but</hi> the gift of God is eternal Life. <hi>And that we may not ſeek it in any other way, he adds,</hi> In Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. <hi>As if he ſhould have ſaid, O Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, not Righteouſneſs, but Pride in the name of Righteouſneſs, why doſt thou begin to exalt thy ſelf, and to require eternal Life, as Wages due to thee? It is true Righteouſneſs, to which eternal life is due; But if it be true Righteouſneſs, it is not of thy ſelf, but is from above, coming down from the Father of lights. Wherefore, O Man, if thou art about to receive eternal Life, it is indeed the Wages of Righteouſneſs, but to thee it is a Grace, to whom Righteouſneſs it ſelf is a Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Epiſtle, I alſo meet with theſe words, <hi>Are there no Merits of the Righteous? ſurely there are, becauſe they are Righteous. But they had no Merits by which they became Righteous. For they are made Righteous, when they are juſtified, but as the Apoſtle ſaith,</hi> They are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied freely by his Grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> iij. And to explain himſelf, a little after he adds, <hi>That Grace would not be Grace, if it were not given freely, but rendred as a due Debt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Epiſtle, I find alſo theſe words, <hi>It is not therefore in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52954:23"/> vain that we ſing unto God, His mercy ſhall prevent me; and His mercy ſhall follow me. Whence life eternal it ſelf, which in the end ſhall be enjoyed without end, and therefore is rendred to precedent merits, yet becauſe thoſe merits to which it is given, are not prepared by any ability of ours, but are wrought in us by Grace, even Life eternal it ſelf is called Grace, for no other reaſon but becauſe it is given freely, not therefore becauſe it is not given to Merits, but becauſe thoſe very Merits to which it is given, are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words are an Inference from what went before, where St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> argues againſt Merit, either before, to obtain Grace; or after, to deſerve a Reward. Theſe are his words, <hi>What is the Merit of Man before Grace, by which he may deſervedly obtain Grace, when as all our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is from Grace, and when he crowns our Merits, he crowns nothing elſe but his own Gifts?</hi> And from hence he inferrs in the words before cited, Whence I obſerve, 1. That all that is good in us here, is owing to Divine Mercy preventing us. 2. That all the good we can expect hereafter, muſt be from the ſame Divine Mercy following us. 3. That Life eternal, which is the great Reward of Vertue and Goodneſs, is called Grace. 4. That though it be ſaid to be given to Merits, it is not ſaid to be given for the ſake of thoſe Merits. 5. That thoſe Merits to which it is given are themſelves the gift of God, and therefore not Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in the ſtrict ſence of the word. <hi>It is not Righteouſneſs, but Pride in the name of Righteouſneſs, that expects eternal Life as a Reward due to its deſerving:</hi> Theſe are St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s own words in the next page, which directly contradict this Definition of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> viz. <hi>That a man juſtified truly deſerves Life everlaſting by his good works.</hi> And now if the Vindicator can make any advantage of theſe words of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> either to himſelf, or to his cauſe, I ſhall not envy him.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. He tells us, that the Council hath defin'd, <hi>That by works a Man is juſtified, and not by Faith only.</hi> And to prove this he alledgeth, <hi>Jam.</hi> ij. 24. where it is ſaid, <hi>ye ſee then, how that a man is juſtified by works, and not by faith only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This place of Scripture hath been ſo often urged, and all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments raiſed therefrom ſo often, and ſo miſerably baffled; that I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with what confidence this Gentleman could bring it upon the ſtage again. They have been often told, that St. <hi>James</hi> here doth not ſpeak of Juſtification before God, but before Men. That as Faith only (though that Faith be not alone) juſtifies us before God, ſo good Works do juſtifie the truth of that Faith, and evidence the reality of our Juſtification thereby unto Men. Which Interpretation is well war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>If Abraham was juſtified by Works, then hath he whereof to glory, but not before God,</hi> Rom. iv. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:52954:24"/>
               <q>I likewiſe profeſs, That in the <hi>Maſs</hi> is offered a true, proper, and propitiatory Sacrifice, for the Living and the Dead.</q>
               <p>TO perſuade us to a compliance herewith, the Vindicator advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth both Scripture and Antiquity; Two great Arguments if well managed. Which whether they be or no, I ſhall now Examine.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He begins with Scripture, and by way of Preface thereunto tells us, <hi>That our bleſſed Saviour being a Prieſt according to the Order of</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck, <hi>did at his laſt Supper offer his Body and Blood after an unbloody manner, for the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is unhappily to ſtumble at the Threſhold. For, 1. How his Conſequent comes to be tack'd to his Antecedent is paſt my capacity to underſtand. Our bleſſed Saviour was <hi>made a Prieſt for ever after the Order of</hi> Melchiſedeck: Therefore <hi>at his laſt Supper he did offer his Body and Blood after an unbloody manner, for the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> What Logick there is in this, I am yet to learn. 2. If he did offer himſelf at his laſt Supper, to whom did he do it? For we do not find that he did addreſs himſelf, or offer any thing to any, but only to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and ſurely he will not ſay that he offered himſelf as a Sacrifice unto them. 3. If he did offer his Body and Blood, then was it not an unbloody Sacrifice, as they ſay it was. 4. If it was an unbloody Sacrifice, then could it not be propitiatory; <hi>For without ſhedding of Blood, there is no Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> Heb. ix. 22.</p>
               <p>But the Vindicator hath good Scripture for all this, <hi>viz. Luke</hi> xxij. 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 24. <hi>Matth.</hi> xxvi. 28. In all which places the Words of Inſtitution are recited, with ſome variation; St. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> verſ. 26. St. <hi>Luke</hi> adds, <hi>Which is given for you.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Which is broken for you.</hi> His whole Argument there depends upon the Words of Inſtitution: Before therefore I meddle with his reaſoning therefrom, it will be convenient to conſider and explain them. And, 1. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>This is,</hi> not, <hi>This is Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate,</hi> or, <hi>wonderfully converted into another ſubſtance,</hi> viz, the ſubſtance of my Body. 2. If when he ſaid, <hi>This is,</hi> he meant <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> then his Body muſt be Tranſubſtantiate before he ſpake; and if ſo, then the Converſion doth not depend upon the Words, as they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm; For, <hi>This is,</hi> implies a thing already done. 3. When he ſaid, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> it is evident, that his true, natural, humane Body was there with them, took the Bread, brake it, gave it, eat it; now if that which he took, brake, gave and eat, was then the Body of Chriſt; either he muſt have two Bodies there at that time, or elſe the ſame Body was by the ſame Body taken, broken, given and eaten;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52954:24"/> and yet all the while neither taken, broken, given nor eaten. 4. When he ſaith, <hi>This is my Body which is given for you,</hi> as St. <hi>Luke,</hi> or, <hi>Which is broken for you,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul;</hi> if it be underſtood literally, then muſt it be either his natural or his glorified Body; if they ſay the former, then we urge them again with the preceding Obſervation; the latter they will not dare to ſay, becauſe his Body was not then Glorified. 5. If theſe words be to be literally and ſtrictly to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, then the ſubſtance of Bread muſt be Chriſt's Body at that time; for what can any Man living underſtand by, <hi>This,</hi> but only <hi>this Bread?</hi> For, what he took he bleſſed; what he bleſſed, he brake; what he brake, he gave to his Diſciples; what he gave to them, he bad them take and eat; and what he bad them take and eat, of that he ſaith, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and all this he himſelf tells us was Bread. And that it did not receive any ſuch wonderful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion or Change as they believe it did, by the pronouncing of thoſe words, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who may be preſumed to underſtand the mind of his Maſter, as well as any of them, is a very good Evidence; who after the Words of Conſecration, by which they pretend the Change is made, doth over and over again call it Bread; as you may read, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 26, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 6. When he ſaith, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me,</hi> it implies an Abſence; for we can no more be ſaid to remember that which is preſent, than to ſee that which is abſent. 7. When it is ſaid, <hi>This Cup is the New-Teſtament in my Blood, which is ſhed for you, and for many, for the remiſſion of Sins;</hi> Are theſe words to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood literally too? Muſt we believe, that by the pronouncing of theſe words, there is a ſubſtantial Change made? If ſo, then it muſt not be of the Wine, but of the Cup; and that not into the Blood of Chriſt, but into the New Teſtament, or New Covenant in his Blood, which none of them as yet have been ſo bold as to affirm. 8. If we conſider that our Saviour celebrated this Sacrament before his Paſſion, and ſaid, <hi>This is my Body which is broken,</hi> and, <hi>This is my Blood which is ſhed,</hi> it cannot be literally true of his natural, humane Body, for that was then whole and unbroken, and his Blood was not then ſhed. And indeed it was impoſſible that the Diſciples ſhould underſtand theſe words literally, becauſe they not only plainly ſaw that what he gave them was Bread and Wine, but they ſaw likewiſe as plainly that it was not his Body which was given, but his Body which gave that which was given; not his Body broken and Blood ſhed, becauſe they ſaw him alive at that very time, and beheld his Body whole and unpierced.</p>
               <p>Having thus conſidered the words of Inſtitution, and made ſome Remarks upon them, let us now ſee how the Vindicator argues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:52954:25"/>
               <p>His firſt Remark is, That the words of Inſtitution are ſpoken in the preſent Tenſe, whence he thus argues, <hi>That it is certain, that then, before the Paſſion on the Croſs, the Body was given, and broken Myſtically, and the Chalice ſhed for the Remiſſion of Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, 1. That if the Vindicator had conſulted the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Bible,</hi> or the <hi>Maſs,</hi> he might there have found <hi>Tradetur</hi> inſtead of <hi>Traditur, ſhall be given,</hi> inſtead of <hi>is given;</hi> and <hi>Effundetur</hi> inſtead of <hi>Effunditur, ſhall be ſhed,</hi> inſtead of <hi>is ſhed.</hi> Which words were likewiſe long ago uſed by <hi>Origen</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Origen in Matth. Tract. 35.</p>
                     <p>Chryſoſt. in 1 Cor. 11.</p>
                     <p>Sa in verb. Matth.</p>
                     <p>Cajetan in Luc. 22.</p>
                  </note> and the Jeſuit <hi>Sa</hi> would have told him, in <hi>Greek</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Which is ſhed,</hi> the time preſent for the time to come. And Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> would have informed him, even as the Evangeliſts by the time preſent have expreſſed the future Effuſion of Blood, ſaying, <hi>is ſhed;</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe ſaying, <hi>is broken,</hi> ſignifieth by the preſent time, the breaking of his Body, which was after to be done upon the Croſs.<note place="margin">Barrad. Harmon. Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilſt. Tom. 4. l. 3. c 4.</note> And <hi>Barradius</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit ſaith, <hi>The Lord uſeth the time preſent inſtead of the future time, which then approached;</hi> for the words ought to be underſtood of his future paſſion, which then drew near; in this ſence, <hi>This is my Body which ſhall ſhortly be given for you, to ſuffer and to die.</hi> So that though the words were really ſpoken in the preſent Tenſe, yet did not that hinder either the Primitive Fathers, their own Tranſlators of the Bible, the Compilers of their Maſs, or their own Eminent Doctors, from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding them of the time to come. Nor is it to be wondered at, for they well knew that it was our Saviour's way and manner of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: As for inſtance, before any of the <hi>Jews</hi> were come to lay hands on him, he ſaid, <hi>Behold the Son of Man,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>is betrayed,</hi> or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>into the hands of Sinners,</hi> Matth. xxvi. 45. <hi>Therefore doth my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther love me, becauſe,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I lay down my Life, that I may take it again, John</hi> x. 17. And in another place, <hi>I am no more in the World, John</hi> xvij. 11. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> in conformity to his Maſter's way and manner of ſpeaking, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I am already offered up,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. 6. All which conſidered, it will not appear to be ſo very certain, as this Gentleman thinks it is, <hi>That the Body of Chriſt was given and broken before his Paſſion on the Croſs.</hi> But 2dly. He ſeems to qualifie the rigour of his Aſſertion, by telling us, <hi>That all this was done Myſtically.</hi> To which I anſwer, That if by Myſtically he mean Sacramentally, <hi>i. e.</hi> That our bleſſed Saviour, by what he did at his laſt Supper, intended to ſignify to his Diſciples what he was about to do and ſuffer for them, and the reſt of Mankind, the day following, we ſhall not differ with him about it. But if by Myſtically he mean Really, though Inviſibly, (as undoubtedly he doth) we cannot
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52954:25"/> agree with him; for in a true, proper, and propitiatory Sacrifice, (as the Article which he here undertakes to defend calls it) the thing offered ought to be viſible, and there ought to be a Deſtruction of it in the Sacrifice; none of all which appears to be in this Action of our Bleſſed Saviour.</p>
               <p>But he proceeds, <hi>Which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>being done in an unbloody manner, and offered to God, we call it an unbloody Sacrifice; and it being for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, 'tis likewiſe propitiatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, 1. The Vindicator here takes that for granted, which we can by no means allow him, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Body of Chriſt was given and broken Myſtically, and the Chalice ſhed for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, before his Paſſion on the Croſs. And why we cannot admit of this, I have given you an Account already. 2. He contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts himſelf, for he tells us, <hi>This was done in an unbloody manner;</hi> and yet he had before told us, <hi>That the Chalice was ſhed,</hi> by which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he means (if he have any meaning in it) the Blood in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: Now if Chriſt's Blood was ſhed, how could it be done in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloody manner? Or how could it be called an unbloody Sacrifice? 3. He tells us, <hi>It was offer'd to God,</hi> but how doth that appear? That our Saviour in his laſt Supper did indeed offer Bread and Wine to his Diſciples, is very plain and evident; but that he offered either them or any thing elſe to God, the Words of Inſtitution give us no account. 4. <hi>That it being for Remiſſion of Sins, it was likewiſe propitiatory.</hi> And here he is under a great miſtake, for every thing, that is for Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins, is not a propitiatory Sacrifice. The Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> and his Preaching, was for the Remiſſion of Sins, <hi>Mark</hi> i. 4. And ſo likewiſe is Baptiſm and Repentance, <hi>Acts</hi> ij. 38. And yet, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the Vindicator will not ſay, That either Baptiſm, or Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Repentance are propitiatory Sacrifices. But perhaps he will ſay, That all ſhedding of Blood made for Remiſſion of Sins, is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice. I cannot conſent to him in this neither, for there is a ſhedding of Blood ſacramental and not real, which is made to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the ſhedding of Chriſt's Blood upon the Croſs, and that is no propitiatory Sacrifice. But what if it be real? Though it be, yet will not the propoſition be univerſally true; for the Blood of our Lord was really ſhed, and for Remiſſions of Sins too, at his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; and yet Circumciſion was no Sacrifice. In a true propitiatory Sacrifice three Things are required. 1. There muſt be a real Effuſion of Blood. 2. That real Effuſion of Blood muſt be for the Remiſſion of Sins. 3. That Effuſion of Blood muſt be by the Death of the thing offered. None of which are to be found in this Action of our Bleſſed Saviour at his laſt Supper, and therefore it could not be a true, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and propitiatory Sacrifice.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52954:26"/>
               <p>But if we ſhould grant (which we cannot do) that this were a Sacrifice, and a propitiatory Sacrifice too, will it by a neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence follow, that every Maſs-Prieſt at this day doth in the Maſs offer a true, proper, and propitiatory Sacrifice, for the Living and the Dead? Yes, ſaith the Vindicator, For, though Chriſt was offered but once upon the Croſs, (of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Hebr.</hi> vij. 27.) yet in this manner, as Chriſt offered himſelf at his laſt Supper, we believe that the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors were commanded to repeat it, in a perpetual memory, and repreſentation of his Death and Paſſion, by Chriſt's own Inſtitution, when he ſaid to them, <hi>Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me;</hi> in which words he gave them power of doing the ſame that he had done. To this I anſwer, That in the ſame manner as Chriſt offered himſelf at his laſt Supper, he is offered ſtill; <hi>i. e.</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally; and that by the command of Chriſt we are obliged often to celebrate or repeat this Sacrament in memory of his Death and Paſſion upon the Croſs: And that by virtue of thoſe Words, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me,</hi> Power was give to the Apoſtles and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors to do the ſame thing he did, <hi>i. e.</hi> to celebrate this Sacrament in memory of his Death and Paſſion on the Croſs. All this we readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grant, but what is all this to the Prieſt's Offering in the Maſs, a true, proper, and propitiatory Sacrifice for the Living and the Dead?</p>
               <p>Thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion do indeed lay great ſtreſs upon theſe words, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me,</hi> pretending to find therein a power given to every Maſs-Prieſt to offer up the Son of God as a true, proper, and propitiatory Sacrifice, for the Living and the Dead. But if they would but conſult St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he would better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them what the importance of theſe words is: For after he had recited the words of Inſtitution, and in the cloſe thereof theſe very words, <hi>Do this in Remembrance of me;</hi> in the very next words he tells them what it was they were to do in remembrance of him, ſaying, <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lord's Death till he come,</hi> 1 Cor. xi. 26.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Having gone as far as he can with his Scripture proofs, he calls in the aſſiſtance of Antiquity, telling us with ſufficient confidence, <hi>That this (i. e.</hi> the matter contained in this Article) <hi>is the Sence of the Primitive Fathers.</hi> Whether it be or no, is the thing we are now to conſider; and for that purpoſe I ſhall examine his Quotations out of them.</p>
               <p>His firſt Witneſs is St. <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 7. (I ſuppoſe he means 17.) <hi>in Ep. ad Hebr.</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>We ſtill offer the ſame Sacrifice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, What St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> meant by thoſe words, I know no body can better inform us, than St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> himſelf, who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52954:26"/> immediately ſubjoins, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Or to ſpeak more properly, we make a commemoration of the ſame Sacrifice.</hi> And in the ſame Homily, had the Vindicator carefully peruſed it, of been ſo honeſt as to have noted it, he might have found ſuch Expreſſions as theſe, <hi>We offer indeed, but it is in remembrance of his Death. This Sacrifice is an Example of that Sacrifice. This which we now do, is in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of that which hath been done.</hi> But that which the Vindicator ſeems to lay the great ſtreſs upon, is, That St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in this Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and likewiſe, <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>de Sacerd.</hi> calls the Euchariſt a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> We grant it, but if he will let him explain himſelf, he will tell him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what account he ſo calleth it in this Homily, <hi>Becauſe it repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Sacrifice of our Lord's Death, and therein we commemorate the ſame till his coming again.</hi> And in the other place, <hi>Becauſe we pray unto God, that he would receive the Sacrifice of his Death as a ſatisfaction for our Sins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His next Evidence is St. <hi>Ambroſe, ſup. Pſ.</hi> 38. Where he ſpeaks of the Prieſt's offering Sacrifice for the People, and of Chriſt's being offered up upon Earth, when his Body is offered. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the ſame place explains himſelf, ſaying, <hi>The Shadow went before, the Image followed, the Truth ſhall be. The Shadow in the Law, the Image in the Goſpel, the Truth in the Heavens. O Man, go up into Heaven, and thou ſhalt ſee thoſe things whereof here was an Image and a Shadow.</hi> Where he plainly tells us, that what is done here upon Earth, is only an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or Repreſentation. And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">In Luc. l. 5. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>We have ſeen him and look'd upon him with our Eyes, and we have thruſt our Fingers into the print of his Nails. For we ſeem to ſee him, that we read of, and to have beheld him hanging upon the Croſs, and with the feeling Spirit of the Church to have ſearched his Wounds.</hi> Now as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> here ſaith, <hi>We ſee him hanging on the Croſs, &amp;c.</hi> In like manner doth he ſay, <hi>He is offered up upon Earth, when his Body is offered.</hi> For as their own Gloſs upon the Sentences of <hi>Proſper</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is Sacrificed, i. e.</hi> his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is repreſented, and a commemoration is made of his Paſſion.</p>
               <p>His next Authority is <hi>Cyril. Alex. Anath.</hi> 11. <hi>We celebrate in our Churches an Holy, Life-giving, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbloody Sacrifice.</hi> What St. <hi>Cyril.</hi> meant by this Unbloody Sacrifice, he himſelf will beſt inform us, if we conſult him about it; for in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">Cyril. contr. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian. l. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>We having left the groſs Miniſtery of the Jews, have a commandment, to make a fine, thin, and ſpiritual Sacrifice. And therefore we offer unto God for a ſweet ſmelling ſavour all manner of Vertues, Faith, Hope, Charity.</hi> And in the ſame ſence that he calls theſe Sacrifices, doth he call the Euchariſt <hi>an unbloody Sacrifice i. e.</hi> A Sacrifice of praiſe and thankſgiving.</p>
               <p>His laſt Reſerve is St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> who <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>Confeſs. c.</hi> 13. ſpeaks of his Mother <hi>Monica</hi> deſiring to be remembred at the Altar after her death;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52954:27"/> becauſe ſhe knew that thence was diſpens'd the Holy Victim, by which was cancelled the Hand-writing, which was contrary unto us. And <hi>Serm.</hi> 32. <hi>de Verb. Apoſt.</hi> where he ſpeaks of a propitiatory Sacrifice, and Alms offered for Souls departed; and of commemorating the Dead at the Sacrifice; and of a Sacrifice being offered for them.</p>
               <p>That Chriſtians did uſually meet to celebrate the memorial of Holy Martyrs, and others departed in the Faith of Chriſt; and that ſome kind of prayers were in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s time uſed for the dead, we deny not. But theſe are not the things in queſtion, but whether in the Maſs there be offer'd a true, proper and propitiatory Sacrifice for the living and the dead. To prove this he produceth theſe paſſages of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> wherein he ſeems to call the Euchariſt, <hi>the holy Victim,</hi> and <hi>the Sacrifice.</hi> Now what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> meant by theſe words he himſelf ſhall tell you.</p>
               <p>In his Book of Faith he calls it, <hi>A Sacrifice of Bread and Wine offered in Faith and Charity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Petr. Diac. c. 19.</note> and <hi>A Commemoration of the Fleſh of Chriſt which he offered for us, and of the Blood which he ſhed for us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. de Civ. Dei l. 17. c. 17.</note> And in another place, <hi>To eat the Bread in the New Teſtament, is the Sacrifice of Chriſtians.</hi> And again, <hi>This Fleſh and Blood of Chriſt was promiſed before his coming,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. contr. Fauſtum, l. 20. c. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>by the reſemblance of Sacrifices; in the Paſſion of Chriſt it was truly exhibited; After the Aſcention of Chriſt, it is celebrated by the Sacrament of Commemoration.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. Epiſt. ad Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac. 23.</note> And again, <hi>Was not Chriſt once ſacrificed in his Body? and yet he is ſacrificed to the people in a ſacred ſign every day.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. de Civ. Dei l. 10. c. 5.</note> And again, <hi>That which we call a Sacrifice, is a ſign or repreſentation of the true Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> Thus doth St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> explain himſelf, and if thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, the Vindicator can any way avail either himſelf or his cauſe, by his teſtimony, he hath free liberty ſo to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I believe and profeſs, That in the Holy Sacrament of the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt is truly, really, and ſubſtantially, the Body and Blood together with the Soul and Divinity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and that there is a change or converſion of the whole Subſtance of the Bread into the Body, and of the whole Subſtance of the Wine into the Blood; which Converſion or Change the Holy Church calls <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>THIS Doctrine, he ſaith, is founded in the expreſs words of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood.</hi> To this I anſwer,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52954:27"/> Theſe and the other words of Inſtitution having been conſidered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and no new matter here offered, I ſhall not need to trouble my ſelf, nor the Reader, with the Repetition of what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid. And this being the only Scripture proof he here alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I ſhall only referr you to what I have ſaid of it in the foregoing Article, and ſo wait upon the Vindicator to his Authorities.</p>
               <p>The Authorities which he here produceth (if they be any thing to his purpoſe) muſt be acknowledged to be ancient, and the Authors of good Credit. Whether therefore they will ſerve the end which he aims at, we ſhall now enquire.</p>
               <p>His firſt Evidence is, St. <hi>Ignatius Martyr</hi> in <hi>Ep. ad Smyrn.</hi> where ſpeaking of ſome Hereticks of his time, he ſaith, <hi>They do not allow of Euchariſts and Oblations, becauſe they do not believe the Euchariſt to be the Fleſh of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which ſuffered for our Sins, and which the Father in his mercy raiſed again from the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words are indeed thus cited by <hi>Theodoret Dial.</hi> 111. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>They do not receive the Euchariſts and Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> But in the Copy of this Epiſtle, which is to be ſeen in the <hi>Florentine</hi> Library, and is generally thought to be the moſt genuine, we find this paſſage thus worded, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>They recede or abſtain from Euchariſts and Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this only by the bye; the ſtreſs of his Argument lies not in this, but in the reaſon of their receſſion and refuſal, which was, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not confeſs that the Euchariſt was the Fleſh of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, which ſuffered for our Sins, and was raiſed again.</p>
               <p>Theſe words at firſt ſight to an unthinking Man, may ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the point; but if we conſider who they were that refuſed the Euchariſt for this reaſon, it will much abate the force of them. That they were Hereticks the Vindicator owns, and what their Hereſie was, <hi>Ignatius</hi> will tell us; They denied Chriſt to be a perfect Man, they held that he had not a true humane, but only a fantaſtical Body; That he did not really, but in appearance only, ſuffer upon the Croſs, and riſe again from the Dead. Againſt theſe the holy Martyr, in the beginning of this Epiſtle, bends his whole diſcourſe; his whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being to make it appear, That Chriſt was truly born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> truly baptized of <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> truly ſuffered under <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate,</hi> and was truly raiſed again from the Dead.</p>
               <p>Now what wonder is it, that thoſe who did believe that he never had any real Body, ſhould refuſe and reject with ſcorn his Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Body, when offered to them? For, what Sacrament, what Sign, what Remembrance, what Repreſentation can there poſſibly be of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52954:28"/> that, which in truth never had any Being? The whole importance therefore of theſe words is only this, Theſe Hereticks would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Euchariſt to be the Sacramental Body of Chriſt, becauſe they did not believe that ever he had any real Body. St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome ſuch in his time, who would not believe that Chriſt really ſuffered;<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Matth. Hom. 83.</note> tells us in what manner they uſed to convince them; <hi>When they ſay, How may we know that Chriſt was offered? bringing forth theſe Myſteries, we ſtop their mouths. For if Chriſt died not, whoſe Sign and Token is this Sacrifice?</hi> Where he calls the Euchariſt a Myſtery, a Sign, and a Token, <hi>i. e.</hi> A Repreſentation of the Death of Chriſt; and in this ſence are we to underſtand the Holy Martyr <hi>Ignatius</hi> in this place.</p>
               <p>His next witneſs is St. <hi>Hilary l.</hi> 8. <hi>de Trinit.</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>My Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed. There's no place left for doubting of the Reality of his Fleſh and Blood; for now, both by the Profeſſion of Chriſt himſelf, and by our Faith, 'tis truly Fleſh, and truly Blood. Is not this Truth? It may indeed not be true to them, who deny Chriſt to be God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That the words which St. <hi>Hilary</hi> here quoteth are in <hi>John</hi> vi. 55. In which whole Chapter our Saviour ſpeaketh not one word of the Euchariſt, that not being inſtituted till two years after, or thereabouts. Nor doth he there ſpeak of a Corporal eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is done by the Mouth of the Body; but of a Spiritual eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is done by Faith. For He is there ſpeaking to the <hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naitan</hi> Jews, who followed him for the Loaves, and takes occaſion from their gluttonous Appetite, to inſtruct them better; to acquaint them with another kind of Food, a Celeſtial Bread, of which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever eateth, liveth eternally; and that Bread is Himſelf. And of this it is that he ſaith, <hi>My Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</hi> And leſt they ſhould underſtand him carnally, he cloſeth up his Diſcourſe with theſe words, <hi>The words which I ſpeak unto you are Spirit and Life,</hi> v. 63. And that in this ſence St. <hi>Hilary</hi> is here to be underſtood, I do not doubt; for in theſe very words he ſaith, <hi>It is ſo by our Faith, i. e.</hi> to them that believe; and the truth of it will not be denied by any, but thoſe who deny the Divinity of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> who deny him to be <hi>the Bread which came down from Heaven,</hi> v. 50. For it was not his Fleſh and Blood, but his Divinity that came down from Heaven.</p>
               <p>But if we ſhould grant that St. <hi>Hilary</hi> in this diſcourſe had an eye to the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, as I do believe he had, yet doth he very well explain himſelf, and give us to underſtand, that he doth not ſpeak of Bodily but Spiritual Meat, not of Corporal but Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual eating, not of receiving Chriſt by the Mouth of the Body, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52954:28"/> by the Mouth of the Soul, which is Faith. For in the very ſame Book that is here quoted, he ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is in us</hi> (not bodily,<note place="margin">Hilar. in Matth. Can. 30. Chryſoſt. in Matth. Hom. 83.</note> but) <hi>by the Myſtery of the Sacraments.</hi> And again, <hi>We receive Chriſt truly</hi> (not ſubſtantially, but) <hi>under a Myſtery.</hi> And in another place he ſpeaks <hi>of drinking of the Fruit of the Vine.</hi> Which, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Doth certainly produce Wine, not Water:</hi> And I may add, nor Blood.</p>
               <p>His next Quotation is out of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, l.</hi> 3. <hi>de Sacerd.</hi> where that Holy Father in an Ecſtacy crys out, <hi>O Miracle! He that ſits above with his Father, at the very ſame inſtant of time is here in the Hands of all; he gives himſelf to thoſe that are willing to receive him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That it was uſual with the Ancient Fathers, by vehement Expreſſions, and Rhetorical Amplifications, to raviſh the Minds, and inflame the Devotions of their Hearers, we very well know; and that it was as frequent with St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> as any other, cannot be unknown to any who have been converſant in his Writings. I ſhall only trouble you with one Inſtance, which the Vindicator may find in the ſame Book which he here quotes, <hi>Chriſt is Crucified before our Eyes, his Blood guſheth out of his ſide, and ſtreameth, and floweth over the Holy Table, and the People are therewith made red and bloody.</hi> Did St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> intend to be underſtood plainly and literally here? Surely the Vindicator will not ſay ſo, nor, if he well conſider, will he think it fit to underſtand him ſo in the place by him alledged; for if ſo, then muſt he grant, That the People do verily and indeed ſee Chriſt's very Body, and handle and touch it with their Fingers; which ſome of his own Doctors will be ready to tell him is not only falſe, but a worſe Hereſie than ever was defended by <hi>Berengarius.</hi> The Miracle therefore which St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> here ſpeaks of, is not the fleſhly or bodily preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, but the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Effects that God worketh in the Faithful, in that dreadful time of the Holy Communion, wherein the whole Myſtery of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Blood of Chriſt, is expreſſed.</p>
               <p>But if this place of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> doth not ſo fully expreſs the bodily preſence of Chriſt in the Euchariſt, the Vindicator hath another, which he thinks will ſufficiently do it; and that is in his 83. <hi>Hom. in Matth.</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>He that wrought thoſe things at the laſt Supper, is the Author of what is done here. — We hold but the place of Miniſters, but he that ſanctifies and changes them, is Chriſt himſelf.</hi> Of what change St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> here ſpeaks, he himſelf doth plainly intimate; for in the ſame Homily, he immediately adds, <hi>So is it alſo in Baptiſm,</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, As in the Sacrament of Baptiſm, the Water is changed from common to ſacramental Water; ſo in the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, the Bread and Wine are changed from common to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52954:29"/> Bread and Wine. And that he meant only this, and not any ſubſtantial Change, is plain; for, in the ſame Homily, he ſaith, <hi>When he would repreſent the Myſteries, he gave Wine.</hi> And in another place he ſaith,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Ep. ad Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</note> 
                  <hi>As the Bread before it is Sanctified, is called Bread; when by the Interceſſion of the Prieſt, divine Grace hath ſanctified it, it loſeth the Name of Bread, and becomes worthy to be called the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, although the Nature of Bread abides in it.</hi> And in another place he ſaith, <hi>If it be dangerous to employ the Holy Veſſels about common uſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Matth. Opere Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perf. Hom. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>wherein the true Body of Jeſus Chriſt is not contained, but the Myſteries of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; how much rather the Veſſels of our Bodies, which God hath prepared to dwell in.</hi> By all which we may plainly underſtand what St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi>'s Thoughts were of a ſubſtantial Change, or of Chriſt's bodily preſence in the Euchariſt, when they were cool and calm, and free from any Ecſtatical Rapture.</p>
               <p>His next is St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, in Catech.</hi> whence he quotes theſe Words, <hi>Since therefore Chriſt himſelf thus affirms and ſays of the Bread,</hi> This is my Body, <hi>and,</hi> This is my Blood; <hi>who can doubt of it, and ſay it is not his Blood?</hi> (No body certainly; for in the ſame ſence that Chriſt ſaid it was ſo, there is no doubt to be made but that it is ſo, <hi>i. e.</hi> Sacramentally and in a Myſtery; but here is to be noted, that if St. <hi>Cyril</hi> be to be underſtood literally, he will be no good Evidence for the Vindicator; for he doth not ſay of the Bread, <hi>it is changed into his Body,</hi> but, <hi>it is his Body,</hi> &amp;c. So that according to him, the Bread muſt be Chriſt's Body, and the Cup his Blood, which as yet they have not had the confidence to affirm, nor indeed will it conſiſt with their notion of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> And if it be to be underſtood Figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it will leſs ſerve his purpoſe; for then it will import no more than what <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Tertul. contra Marcion. l. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt took Bread, and made it his Body, by ſaying, This is my Body;</hi> i. e. <hi>The Figure of my Body.</hi>) But he further enforceth his Argument, ſaying, <hi>In</hi> Cana <hi>of</hi> Galilee <hi>he once by his ſole Will turned Water into Wine, which reſembles Blood; and doth he not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be credited, that he changed Wine into his Blood?</hi> (Yes, no doubt, when he tells us that he did ſo; or when we have as clear Evidence of his changing Wine into Blood, as we have of his changing Water into Wine at the Marriage Feaſt in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee.</hi> In this he appeals to Sence, bidding the Servants draw out now, and carry it to the Governor of the Feaſt, that he might taſte it. But in the other we are required to believe againſt all Evidence of Sence.) But to clear the point more fully, St. <hi>Cyril</hi> himſelf will tell us what kind of change he here ſpeaks of;<note place="margin">Cyril. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eroſol. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech. Myſt. 3.</note> for, ſaith he, <hi>As Bread in the Euchariſt, after the Invocation of the Holy Spirit, is no more common Bread, but is the Body of Chriſt; ſo this Holy Ointment is no more that Ointment,</hi> i. e.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52954:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52954:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:52954:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:52954:31"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:52954:31"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52954:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:52954:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:52954:33"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:52954:33"/> 
                  <hi>As the Ointment is changed, ſo is the Bread in the Euchariſt, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. As the Ointment, when once conſecrated to an holy uſe, is no more common Ointment,</hi> i. e. <hi>Though it be Ointment ſtill, and the ſame in ſubſtance that it was, yet it is no more the ſame Ointment; for, before it was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, now it is Conſecrate. So the Bread in the Euchariſt, after the Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Holy Spirit, is no more common Bread;</hi> i. e. <hi>Though it be Bread ſtill, yet is it not common Bread; but it is the Body of Chriſt,</hi> i. e. <hi>The Sacrament of his Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His next Authority is <hi>Greg. Nyſſen. Orat. Catech.</hi> c. 37. whence he cites theſe words, <hi>I do therefore now rightly believe, That the Bread ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the Word of God, is changed into the Body of the Word. — Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it</hi> (the Bread) <hi>is ſuddenly changed by this Word,</hi> This is my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. — <hi>And this is effected by the virtue of Benediction, by which the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe things that appear is Tranſelemented into it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That the Bread ſanctified by the word of God, is changed or Tranſelemented into the body of the Word. If it be underſtood in the ſame ſence that the Ancient Fathers uſed it, we can readily ſubſcribe unto it; and in what ſence they uſed it, has been in part declared already. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Tertull. contra Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. l. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt took Bread, and made it his Body, by ſaying,</hi> This is my Body, i. e. <hi>A Figure of my Body.</hi> And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. ad Bonifac. Ep. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>After a certain manner the Sacrament of Chriſt's Body is the Body of Chriſt.</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>It really is,</hi> but <hi>after a certain manner.</hi> And in what manner it was ſaid to be ſo, he himſelf in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place informs us, ſaying, <hi>He made no doubt to ſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Aug. contr. Adimant. c. 12.</p>
                     <p>Theophilact. in 6. cap. Johan.</p>
                  </note> This is my Body, <hi>when he gave the ſign of his Body.</hi> And <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact</hi> ſaith, <hi>We our ſelves are Tranſelemented into the Body of Chriſt.</hi> Which, I ſuppoſe, this Gentleman will not underſtand, as if Believers were really and ſubſtantially changed into the Body of Chriſt. But to clear this point, let but <hi>Greg. Nyſſen,</hi> who certainly beſt underſtood his own meaning, be his own Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, and it will plainly appear, that by theſe Expreſſions he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no more, than what is expreſſed by theſe and many other Holy Fathers. For in another place thus he writeth, <hi>This Altar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gregor. Nyſſen, de Sancto Baptiſm.</note> 
                  <hi>whereat we ſtand, is by nature a common Stone, nothing differing from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Stones, whereof our Walls are built, and our Pavements laid; but after that it is once dedicated to the honour of God, and hath received bleſſing, it is a Holy Table, and an undefiled Altar, afterward not to be touched of all Men, but only of the Prieſts, and that with Reverence. Likewiſe the Bread, that firſt was common, after that the Myſtery hath hallowed it, is both called, and is Chriſt's Body; likewiſe alſo the Wine, Chriſt's Blood. And whereas before they were things of ſmall value, after the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52954:34"/> Bleſſing, that cometh from the Holy Ghoſt, either of them both worketh mightily. The like power alſo maketh the Prieſt to be Reverend and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, being by means of a new Benediction divided from the common ſort of the People.</hi> Whence it is evident, That as the Altar of ſtone was changed from its former ſtate, and yet remained ſtone ſtill; and as the Prieſt is changed from what he was before, and yet remaineth the ſame Man ſtill; ſo, and no otherwiſe, did the Holy Father think that the Bread and Wine are changed in the Sacrament; <hi>i. e.</hi> They are changed into Chriſt's Body and Blood, and yet remain Bread and Wine ſtill.</p>
               <p>In the next place he brings in St. <hi>Ambroſe, l. de his qui Myſt. initiant.</hi> where ſpeaking of the Euchariſt, he ſays, <hi>Shall not the words of Chriſt be powerful enough to change the nature of things?</hi> (Yes, no doubt, when he pleaſeth ſo to do) <hi>you have read of the Creation of the World, that God ſpake, and the things were made; he commanded, and they received a Being. If therefore Chriſt by his Word was able to make ſomething of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſhall he not be thought able to change one thing into another?</hi> Yes, certainly, when he thinks fit to do it. But the Queſtion here is not. What Chriſt, as God, can do, but, what he will, or hath done? Now let us ſee what kind of Argument this Gentleman can find in this Topick; if he has any, it muſt run thus, Whatſoever Chriſt, as God, by his Omnipotent Power, can do, that he doth. But Chriſt, as God, by his Omnipotent Power, can make the Bread in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be his Body, therefore he doth it. Would it not be every whit as good an Argument? Chriſt, as God, by his Omnipotent Power, can make the Vindicator a Pope or a Cardinal, therefore he hath done it. Would not any Freſh Man ſmile at ſuch an Argument, and put him in mind of an old Maxim, <hi>A poſſe ad eſſe non valet conſequentia?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to clear St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> from that foul Aſperſion, which the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator here would inſinuate and impoſe upon him, we need but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> himſelf; for there is none of the ancient Fathers, who has delivered his Opinion in this matter more plainly and expreſly than he has done. For in the ſame Book which is here cited, he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ambr. de his qui initiant. Myſt. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>It is one thing that is done viſibly, and another thing that is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted inviſibly. — Believe not only what thou ſeeſt with thy bodily Eyes, for that is better ſeen which thou doſt not ſee; the thing that thou ſeeſt is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, the thing which thou doſt not ſee is for ever.</hi> Where he plainly diſtinguiſheth between the Sacrament, and the thing ſignified thereby. And again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> c. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>As the Fleſh of Chriſt, which was Crucified and Buried, was true Fleſh, ſo this is truly a Sacrament of that Fleſh. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſaith,</hi> This is my Body. <hi>Before the Bleſſing of the heavenly words it is named one kind, after Conſecration the Body of Chriſt is ſignified.</hi> And
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52954:34"/> in his Book of <hi>Sacraments,</hi> he hath theſe expreſſions, <hi>In eating and drinking we ſignifie that Fleſh and Blood which were offered for us.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. de Sacram. l. 4. c. 4 &amp; 5. And l. 6. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou receiveſt the Sacrament in a ſimilitude. It is the Figure of the Body and Blood of our Lord. Thou drinkeſt the likeneſs of his precious Blood.</hi> And again, <hi>Bread and Wine remain ſtill the ſame thing they were before, and yet are changed into another thing,</hi> i. e. <hi>They are the ſame things really and in ſubſtance, but another thing Sacramentally and in ſignification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to his laſt Authority, taken from St. <hi>Cyril Alex. Ep. ad Coloſſ.</hi> Though there be ſome Rhetorical aggravations, the like whereunto may be found in other of the Fathers; ſome of which I have given you an account of; yet do I not ſee, that any thing more is deſign'd by St. <hi>Cyril</hi> in this place, than only to aſſure us of Chriſt's real, but Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual preſence in this Sacrament. For that he never dreamt of any real and ſubſtantial change of the Elements therein, is plain from his own words in another place, where he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Cyril in Johan. l. 4. c. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt gave to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Diſciples pieces of Bread,</hi> not pieces of his Body. And again,<note n="†" place="margin">Id. Ad Object. Theodor.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Sacrament doth not aſſert the eating of a Man,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Fleſh and Blood) that were to draw the minds of the Believers, in an irreligious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to groſs cogitations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I confeſs alſo, That under one kind alone is received Chriſt whole and entire, that being a true Sacrament.</q>
               <p>THIS, he tells us, is a conſequence of what is declared above; and if ſo, then muſt they ſtand and fall together. If the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation be defective, the Superſtructure is in danger; If the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent be falſe, the Conſequence can ſcarce be true. Having therefore throughly ſifted and examined the preceeding Article, and found no Foundation upon which to build our Faith, that there is any ſuch real and ſubſtantial change wrought in the Elements of the ſacred Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt after Conſecration, as is there pretended; nor any reaſon to receive their monſtrous and new invented Article of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into the Articles of our Creed, we may juſtly reject this which he calls a conſequence thereof.</p>
               <p>But to ſhew that we have other reaſons, beſides the inconſequence thereof, to reject this Article as a Sacrilegious robbing of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of one half of the ſacred Euchariſt; let us conſider the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and the conſtant practice of the Church thereupon. If we conſider the Inſtitution, we ſhall there find that our bleſſed Saviour, in words as plain as poſſible, did inſtitute his Holy Supper under both
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52954:35"/> kinds; we may alſo find, that as he did inſtitute it, ſo likewiſe he did adminiſter it under both kinds; we may alſo obſerve, that He who ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Take, eat,</hi> did alſo ſay unto them, <hi>Drink ye all of this;</hi> and in the cloſe of all, he leaves this word of command with them, <hi>This do in remembrance of me,</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, what you have ſeen me do, the ſame do ye. And it is evident by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles practice hereupon, that they underſtood this to be the meaning of their Maſter. And that this was not to remain a duty only during their time, but in all after Ages of the Church St. <hi>Paul</hi> is very plain, ſaying, <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread and drink this Cup,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. xi. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>ye ſhew forth the Lords death till he come.</hi> And as for the practice of the Church thereupon, it is very evident, that for above a thouſand years after Chriſt, the Euchariſt was always adminiſtred in both kinds. So that if we have any regard either to the Inſtitution, or Example, or Command of Chriſt, or to the Practice of the Apoſtles, or of the Church of Chriſt for ſo many Ages; we have great reaſon to reject this Article as a great Novelty. And indeed ſo it is, for the firſt Foundation of it, as a thing neceſſary to be believed and practiſed, is laid in a Decree of the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1416.</p>
               <p>But the Vindicator will tell us, that we are miſtaken here, for he pretends to find ſome footſteps of it in the Scriptures; and for this alledgeth certain paſſages out of the ſixth Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> where our Saviour ſpeaks ſometimes both of <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of <hi>Eating</hi> only.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That our Bleſſed Saviour in that place doth not ſpeak any thing of the Sacrament of his Body and Blood; but only of a Spiritual feeding upon him by Faith. For, when he held that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with the <hi>Capernaitan</hi> Jews, this Sacrament was not then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, nor of two years after; and therefore no concluſive Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be built thereupon.</p>
               <p>But he urgeth us with the Authority of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Caeſar. Patr.</hi> where he ſaith, he finds theſe words, <hi>It hath the ſame efficacy, whether a perſon receives from the Prieſt one part or more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether theſe be the words of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> or how truly they are tranſcrib'd, I have not the opportunity now to examine; but admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the preſent that they are, what is all this to the denying of the Cup to the Laity, and forbidding the Adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in both kinds, under ſo ſevere a penalty.</p>
               <p>But I find St. <hi>Baſil</hi> cited by <hi>Johannes Gerhardus</hi> for a quite different purpoſe;<note place="margin">Johan. Gerhard. de Sacra Coena, c 9. §. 43. Baſil. l. 1. de Bapt. c. 3.</note> for he brings him in ſpeaking on this wiſe; <hi>If he who by eating offends his Brother, be void of Charity; what ſhall be ſaid of him, who dares idly and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52954:35"/> unprofitably both eat the Body and drink the Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> And again, <hi>What is the duty of a Chriſtian?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralib. ſub finem.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him cleanſe himſelf from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit; and ſo let him eat the Body, and drink the Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But at laſt he urgeth us with the opinion of <hi>Luther, Melancthon</hi> and <hi>Spalatenſis, That in this point Chriſt hath left no neceſſary precept, but that it may profitably, and lawfully be received under one or both kinds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, 1. That our Faith, is not founded upon <hi>Luther</hi>'s or any other Man's aſſertion, but upon the Inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt. 2. That <hi>Luther</hi> wrote his Epiſtle to the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> before he was fully grounded in the truth; and that afterwards he did retract (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) many things that he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. To this end you may find him begging and beſeeching his Reader to read his former writings with pity and commiſeration.<note place="margin">In praefat. Tom. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Before all things, I pray and beſeech the godly Reader, and I beſeech him for our Lord Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, that he would read theſe my writings with judgment, yea and with great pity; remembring that I was ſometimes a Monk, a mad Papiſt, ſo drunk, ſo drown'd in Popery, that I was ready to kill every one, or aſſiſt and conſent to their death, if in any things they differed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I hold, That there is a Purgatory, and that the Souls there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd are help'd by the Prayers of the Faithful.</q>
               <p>THE Vindicator here tells us, that he doth verily believe, and is fully ſatisfied, that there is a Purgatory; but <hi>where it is,</hi> or <hi>whether there be a true and proper Fire there,</hi> or <hi>how long that puniſhment laſts,</hi> theſe are no Articles of his Faith. He might have added, Or <hi>what it is;</hi> For the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> upon which he builds his Faith, doth not tell him that. So that to ſubſcribe to this Article, is in effect to ſubſcribe to he knows not What, nor Where, nor Whether, nor How long, nor indeed Why.</p>
               <p>It may not be amiſs therefore to acquaint you what the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is concerning Purgatory, which I ſhall do out of their moſt Authentick Record, <hi>viz.</hi> The Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seſſ. 25. Decret. de Purgator.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is declared, <hi>That there is a Purgatory, and that the Souls detain'd there do receive aſſiſtance from the ſuffrages of the Faithful, but eſpecially from the acceptable Sacrifice of the Altar.</hi> And all who do not believe the ſame, are by that Council anathematized, which makes it a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Article of Faith. For thus the Council determineth, <hi>If any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52954:36"/> one ſhall ſay, that after a Man hath received the Grace of Juſtification, the guilt of his Sin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seſſ. 6. Can. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>and the eternal puniſhment due thereto, is ſo remitted, that there remains no temporary pain to be ſatisfied for by him, either in this World, or in Purgatory, before he can enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; let him be Anathema.</hi> And in another place the ſame Council tells us,<note place="margin">Seſſ. 22. cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Sacrifice of the Maſs is a truly propitiatory Sacrifice for the Living, and for the Dead, who are not yet throughly purged.</hi> And to confirm this, there is a Canon of that Council, in the ſame Seſſion in theſe words,<note place="margin">Can. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>If any one ſhall ſay, that the Sacrifice of the Maſs is only a Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thanksgiving, or a bare Commemoration of the Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, and not a propitiatory Sacrifice; Or that it is profitable only to him that receives it, and ought not to be offered up for the ſins, pains, ſatisfactions, and other neceſſities both of the quick and the dead; let him be Anathema.</hi> And the <hi>Catechiſm ad Parochos,</hi> which always ſpeaks the ſence of that Council, teacheth the ſame Doctrine, telling us,<note place="margin">Part. 1. Art. 2. n. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>That there is a Purgatory Fire, wherein the Souls of the Godly, being tormented for a certain time, are expiated; that ſo the Gates of the eternal Country may be opened unto them, into which nothing defiled can enter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Doctrine of the Romiſh Church touching Purgatory, which we are required to ſubſcribe unto in this Article; wherein we are taught, and it is expected that we ſhould ſteadfaſtly believe, 1. That there is a middle ſtate for the reception of Souls departed, which is neither Heaven nor Hell. 2. That this ſtate is a ſtate of pain and puniſhment. 3. That in this ſtate they are to ſatisfie for ſome temporary puniſhments, which were not accompliſhed nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for in this life. 4. That thoſe tormented Souls may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and relieved by the Prayers and Alms-deeds of their Friends here, but eſpecially by the acceptable Sacrifice of the Altar.</p>
               <p>Now this Doctrine we cannot ſubſcribe to, having (as we think) great reaſon to reject it. For, 1. We do not find in holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture any mention made of any other place for the reception of Souls departed, beſides Heaven and Hell; and therefore we look upon it as a fond thing, vainly invented. 2. Nor do we find any the leaſt footſteps of a Popiſh Purgatory, among the Primitive Fathers, nor for many hundred years after Chriſt.<note place="margin">In lib. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> There own Martyr <hi>Roffenſis</hi> deals plainly with us, telling us, <hi>That ſo long as there was no care of Purgatory</hi> (which fairly implies, that there was a time when Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory was either not known, or not much cared for) <hi>no Man ſought after Indulgences; for upon that depends all the opinion of Pardons:</hi> If you take away Purgatory, wherefore ſhould we need Pardons? Since therefore Purgatory was ſo lately known and received of the whole
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52954:36"/> Church, (<hi>viz.</hi> not till the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. about the Year 1300.) who can wonder that there was no uſe of Indulgences in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Church? But though there was not then, there is great uſe made of them now; and would you know for what reaſon? <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi> in a witty Expreſſion of his, will give you a true account, <hi>They do wonderfully affect the Fire of Purgatory, becauſe it is ſo profitable for their Kitchins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Vindicator will tell us, <hi>That both</hi> Roffenſis <hi>and we are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily out in our Calculation;</hi> for he hath found very plain Footſteps of this Purgatory, both in Scripture and Antiquity. Which whether he hath or no, is the thing now to be examined.</p>
               <p>He produceth only one Scripture, <hi>viz. Matth.</hi> xij. 32. where it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall ſpeak against the Holy Ghoſt, it ſhall not be forgiven him, neither in this World, nor in the World to come.</hi> Whence he thinks it follows by a neceſſary conſequence, <hi>That there are ſome Sins which ſhall be forgiven in the next World, though not in this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, 1. That if we ſhould allow him this Expoſition, yet will it not thence follow that there muſt of neceſſity be a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Fire, in which the Souls departed muſt be purged, and have their ſins pardoned. For, 1ſt. Whether there be any true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Fire there, this Gentleman knows not; it is no Article of his Faith. 2. The Purgatory they ſpeak of, is not a place of pardon, but of pain and puniſhment. For, according to their Doctrine, Sin is already pardoned, before the Souls enter into Purgatory; only they are to remain there for ſome time, to make up ſome ſatisfaction which was not completed in this Life. But, 2dly. We cannot allow him this Expoſition, for it is ſo far from being a neceſſary conſequence from theſe words, that a contrary one ſeems to be plainly deſigned therein. It ſhall not be forgiven, neither in this World, nor in the World to come; <hi>i. e.</hi> It ſhall never be forgiven, but ſhall certainly be puniſhed both in this Life, and in that to come. So that whether we allow or diſallow of this his Expoſition, this Scripture will not ſerve his purpoſe.</p>
               <p>His Argument from Antiquity makes indeed a greater ſhew, which is built upon theſe Foundations, 1. That the ancient Fathers did fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſpeak of an Intermediate State between Death and Judgment. 2. That they did often make mention of a Purgatory, and a Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Fire, which was to be endured before an actual entrance into Heaven. 3. That they did uſe Prayers for the Dead, and did think thoſe Prayers might be advantageous to Souls departed. All which we can readily grant him, and yet reject this Article of a Popiſh Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:52954:37"/>
               <p>For the two firſt of theſe he quotes St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> St. <hi>Greg. Nyſſen,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and he might have cited a great many more, who ſpeak of an Intermediate State, and a Purgatory Fire. But if he had attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to what they ſay, he might have found that the middle State they ſpeak of, is not a State of pain and torment, but of reſt and eaſe; and the Fire they mention is only that at the day of Judgment, when their Purgatory Fire muſt be extinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>As for St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> it muſt be acknowledged, that he ſpeaks of a purgatory Fire, and that he ſometimes ſeems to ſpeak of a Purgation between Death and Judgment. But he might have obſerved alſo with what doubting and uncertainty he ſpeaks of it. For thus he writeth,<note place="margin">Aug. in 8. Qu. ad Dulcitium. Qu. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>That there may be ſome ſuch thing</hi> (as the Fire of Purgatory) <hi>after this Life is not incredible.</hi> And whether it be ſo or no, it may be a Queſtion. And again,<note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 21. c. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Spirits of the Dead may find a Fire of Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Tribulation, I deny not; for perhaps it is true.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,<note place="margin">Aug. de Fide &amp; Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, cap. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether Men ſuffer ſuch things only in this Life, or elſe ſome ſuch Judgments follow even after this Life; as much as I think, the underſtanding of this Sentence diſagreeth not from the order of the Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 21. c. 27.</note> And again, <hi>What Mean that is, and what Sins thoſe are, which ſo hinder a Man from coming unto the Kingdom of God, that they may notwithſtanding obtain Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by the Merits of Holy Friends, it is very hard to find, and very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to determine. Certainly, I my ſelf, notwithſtanding all my ſearch and Study, could never attain to the knowledge of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> here doubteth, ſo in other places, and at other times he might have found him fully reſolved,<note place="margin">Aug. Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pognoſt. l. 5. Aug. de verb. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt. Serm. 18. Aug. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Ebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etat. Serm. 232.</note> and poſitively declaring himſelf againſt it. For thus he delivers himſelf: <hi>Any other third Place after this Life, beſides Heaven and Hell, we know none, neither can we find in the Holy Scriptures that there is any ſuch.</hi> And again, <hi>There are two Habitations, the one in the eternal Kingdom of Heaven, the other in the eternal Fire of Hell.</hi> And again, <hi>Let no man deceive himſelf, my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for there are two places, and no third Place. He that ſhall not merit to reign with Chriſt in Heaven, without doubt ſhall periſh with the Devil in Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Greg. Nyſſen,</hi> if his Works were not corrupted by the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniſts,</hi> as ſome ſuſpect, we confeſs that he ſpeaks of a Purgatory Fire; but the Fire that he ſpeaks of is the Fire of the laſt Judgment; for that there is no place of pain and torment for the purgation of Souls, between Death and Judgment, ſeems to be his ſettled Opinion; for, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Greg. Nyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. lib. de dormient.</note> 
                  <hi>The war that is in us being ended by Death, our Souls reſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left the Field wherein the Battle was fought,</hi> i. e. The Body.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:52954:37"/>
               <p>As for that of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> in his <hi>Scholia</hi>'s upon 1 <hi>Cor. cap.</hi> 3. it is a gloſs directly contrary to the words of the Text. For, 1. The Apoſtle there ſpeaketh of a Fire which trieth the work, and not of a Fire which puniſheth the perſon. 2. He ſpeaks of every Man's work, not excepting the Apoſtles and Martyrs, and yet the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empts them from Purgatory. By the Fire therefore here ſpoken of, ſome underſtand the Fire of Tribulation, or the fiery Trial, which is to be undergone in this Life; others underſtand it of the fiery Trial at the laſt Judgment, which muſt paſs upon all; neither of which will favour a Popiſh Purgatory; and therefore if <hi>Theodoret</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it of that, he was beſides his Text.</p>
               <p>For his other Foundation upon which he pretends to build his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, <hi>viz.</hi> The practice of praying for the Dead, he quotes <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, Epiphanius, Chryſoſtom,</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but without any direction where to find his Quotations. But that is not much material, for we willingly grant that this was an ancient practice in the Church; but that they intended thereby to deliver Souls out of Purgatory we deny; for it is certain their Prayers were made for the beſt Men, for the Holy Apoſtles, the Martyrs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Church, and for the bleſſed Virgin her ſelf; all which they thought were then in complete happineſs, and who, the Papiſts themſelves ſay, never touch'd at Purgatory by the way. And though it was frequently practiſed, yet was there no determination of the Church in that point, but it was wholly left to the Piety and Opinion of particular Men.</p>
               <p>But if the Vindicator have a mind to be better informed in this matter, I would commend unto him a little, but learned Treatiſe printed at <hi>London</hi> this laſt Year, intituled, <hi>A ſhort Summary of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Controverſies between the Church of</hi> England <hi>and the Church of</hi> Rome. In which he will find theſe two Points fully cleared. 1.<note place="margin">P. 45.</note> That a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle State between Death and Judgment, which is neither Heaven nor Hell, does not prove a Popiſh Purgatory. And, 2.<note place="margin">P. 61.</note> That the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent practice of praying for Souls departed, does not prove that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is a Popiſh Purgatory, or that thoſe ancient Chriſtians did believe that there was. Which are the two Foundations upon which he here builds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:52954:38"/>
               <q>
                  <p>I hold that the Saints reigning with Chriſt are to be Honour'd and Invocated, that they offer Prayers to God for us, and that their Relicks are to be had in Veneration.</p>
                  <p>I moſt firmly hold, That the Images or Pictures of Chriſt, of the Bleſſed Mother of God always a Virgin, and of other Saints, ought to be kept and reſerved, and that due Honour and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ought to be given them.</p>
               </q>
               <p>IN the former of theſe Articles we are required firmly to believe and ſtedfaſtly to hold, 1. That the Saints reigning with Chriſt are to be honour'd. 2. That they are not only to be honour'd, but invocated and prayed unto. 3. That thoſe Saints do offer Prayers to God for us. And, 4. That their Relicks are to be had in Veneration.</p>
               <p>In the other it is required, that we firmly hold, 1. That the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages or Pictures of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ought to be kept and reſerved. And, 2. That due honour and veneration ought to be given them.</p>
               <p>That the Saints reigning with Chriſt are to be honoured, we will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly grant; we hold their Memories to be very precious, and we think we ought to follow thoſe pious Patterns, and imitate thoſe holy Examples which they have left us; which is the greateſt honour that we can do them. But that they are to be invocated, call'd upon, or pray'd unto, we cannot conſent; becauſe we have no warrant for it either in the Word of God, or any good Antiquity. Whether they do offer Prayers to God for us, as it is not very certain, ſo is it not any part of the queſtion between us; nor, if it be granted, will it warrant our praying to them. As for their Relicks, thoſe that are truly ſuch, <hi>viz.</hi> their Sepulchres, their Memories, their Writings and their good Examples, we have a great Veneration for them, and do think that they ought not only not to be expoſed to any contempt or diſgrace, but that a very great reſpect and regard ought to be paid them. But that all thoſe things which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> tells us are the Relicks of Saints, are really ſuch, we cannot agree; nor can we go along with them in paying them that Veneration which they do; we cannot repoſe any confidence in them, nor expect any help or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from them, nor hope to have our Prayers heard in this place rather than in another, upon the account of ſome Relicks being there. As for their Images, and the honour and veneration due to them; it had been well, if either Pope <hi>Pius</hi> or his Vindicator had thought fit to explain themſelves, and told us what kind of honour and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they mean. The Vindicator indeed ſaith, <hi>That they being things
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:52954:38"/> relating to God, it muſt be another kind of Regard, Honour, and Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than is uſually given to prophane things.</hi> But whether this is, or ought to be called a Religious Honour, is matter of diſpute, but no matter of his Faith. And that as for the manner, or external profeſſion of it, it ought to be meaſured from the intention of the Church, ſo that we are ſtill as far to ſeek for the meaning of it, as before. Now, where can we hope to find what the intention of the Church is, unleſs it be in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> and its Catechiſm, out of which Pope <hi>Pius</hi> extracted theſe New Articles? It may not be amiſs therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we proceed any further, to ſee what that Council hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in theſe two points, <hi>viz. The Invocation of Saints,</hi> and <hi>the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images,</hi> which are the two things promoted in theſe two Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and which this Gentleman hath here undertaken to vindicate from Novelty.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Touching the Invocation of Saints, The Council hath defin'd, <hi>That the Saints reigning with Chriſt do offer their Prayers unto God for us.</hi> But is this all? No, it farther declares,<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. Seſſ. 25. Decret. de Invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That it is a good and profitable thing for us in an humble manner to pray unto them.</hi> But is this all yet? No, <hi>We muſt have recourſe to their Prayers, Aid and Aſſiſtance.</hi> Nor is this all, for <hi>the Bodies of Holy Martyrs, and others now living with Chriſt, which have been the living Members of Chriſt, and Temples of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> veneranda ſunt, <hi>are to be worſhipped or had in veneration.</hi> And it expreſly damns all thoſe who teach, <hi>That Veneration and Honour are not due to the Relicks of the Saints;</hi> or, <hi>that it is not profitable to honour theſe Relicks, and other ſacred Monuments of the Saints;</hi> or, <hi>that it is in vain to frequent the Memories of the Saints,</hi> and that, eorum opis impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trandae cauſâ, <hi>to obtain their help and aſſiſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far the Council, which is ſeconded by the Catechiſm, which ſaith, <hi>We pray to God, either to give us good things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Catech. ad Parochos, Part 4. Tit. Quis ſit Orandus?</note> 
                  <hi>or to deliver us from evil; but becauſe the Saints are more acceptable to him than we are, we beg of them to undertake our cauſe, and to obtain for us thoſe things we ſtand in need of. From whence it comes to paſs, that we uſe two very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Forms of Prayer; for to God the proper manner of ſpeaking is,</hi> Have pity on us, Hear our Prayer, <hi>whereas we only deſire the Saints</hi> to pray for us. But then it follows, <hi>Though it be lawful on another account to pray to the Saints, that they would have pity on us, for they are mighty merciful.</hi> And in another place it ſaith, <hi>Invocandi ſunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They are to be prayed unto, becauſe they are continually in God's preſence, and moſt willingly take upon them</hi> patrocinium ſalutis noſtrae, <hi>the patronage of our Health and Safety, which is committed to their care.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Concerning the Worſhip of Images, that Council hath alſo defin'd, <hi>That the Images of Chriſt, of the Virgin-Mother of God, and of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52954:39"/> other Saints,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seſſ. 25. Decret. de Invocatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>are to be had and retained in Churches.</hi> But is this all? No, <hi>All due honour and veneration is to be given to them.</hi> And how is this to be given? By kiſſing thoſe Images, uncovering the Head, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating our ſelves before them. And is all this for no other end, but only to excite in us the remembrance of thoſe they repreſent? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Council intended ſomething more, for it builds this Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition upon the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Nicaen. 2. Action. 3, 4, &amp; 6. Catech. ad Parochos, part 3. de cultu &amp; Invocat. Sanct.</note> in which it was ordained, <hi>That the Images of Chriſt, of the bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and of the Saints, ſhould not only be received into places of Adoration, but alſo ſhould be adored and worſhipped.</hi> And ſo the Catechiſm explains it, for we are there told, <hi>That to make and honour the Images of Chriſt the Lord, of his moſt holy and immaculate Mother, and of other Saints, is an holy and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain argument of a grateful mind.</hi> But is this all? No. <hi>It is not only lawful to have Images in Churches, and to give Honour and Worſhip to them; provided that Honour which is given to them be referred to their</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totypes, <hi>but alſo it is for the greateſt good and benefit of the Faithful ſo to do.</hi> But is this all yet? No. <hi>The Images of Saints are placed in Temples,</hi> ut colantur, <hi>that they may be worſhipped.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in theſe two Articles, as it is delivered by the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Catechiſm <hi>ad Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochos,</hi> out of which theſe and the other new Articles were collected by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. Which Doctrine we can by no means comply with, nor ſubſcribe to. For,</p>
               <p n="1">I. As for the Invocation of Saints, 1. We look upon it as a fond thing, vainly invented, grounded upon no warranty of Scripture, but rather repugnant to the word of God. 2. We think it to be highly derogatory to the Mediatorial Office of Jeſus Chriſt. 3. We look upon Prayer as an eminent Act of Religious Worſhip, which we think to be due to God alone, and ought not to be given to any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And,</p>
               <p n="2">II. As for the Worſhip of Images. We think that it is an abſolute breach of the ſecond Commandment, which forbids the worſhip of Images, and that in words ſo large and comprehenſive, that there is no room left for Evaſion. For, 1. It forbids all external acts of Adoration, as bowing down to them, or before them. 2. It doth not only forbid the Worſhip of Images as Gods, but as Images and Repreſentative Objects. 3. It doth not only forbid the Worſhip of the Images of Heathen Gods, but of the Lord <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all this notwithſtanding, the Vindicator thinks he hath found out both Scripture and Antiquity, wherewith to defend both theſe Articles.</p>
               <p>For the Invocation of Saints, he alledgeth <hi>Gen.</hi> xlviij. <hi>v.</hi> 16. where
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52954:39"/> 
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſing <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s two Sons, ſaith, <hi>The Angel that delivered me from all evil, bleſs the Lads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That by <hi>Angel</hi> here is generally underſtood the Angel of the Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt the Son of God. But if we ſhould grant him, that it is to be underſtood of an Ordinary Angel, yet can he not thereupon avail himſelf any thing in this caſe; for, God being pleaſed often to make uſe of the Miniſtry of Angels in ſending ſuccor and relief to good Men, <hi>Jacob</hi> prayed not unto the Angel, but to God, (as may be ſeen in the 15 Verſe) that he would appoint the ſame Bleſſed Angel that adminiſtred unto him in all his ſtreights, to be the Inſtrument of his good providence to thoſe two Sons of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> whom he had now made his own, and cauſed them to be called after his name.</p>
               <p>He alledgeth alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> i. 4. <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 8. and <hi>Rev.</hi> viij. 9. The firſt of theſe Texts is nothing to his purpoſe, for the moſt that can be made of it is only this, <hi>John</hi> prays that God would ſend his Grace to the ſeven Churches, by the Miniſtry of the ſeven Spirits there mentioned, and what is all this to the matter in hand? or how will this warrant our praying to Saints departed?</p>
               <p>Nor will his next Scripture do him any more ſervice, for it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally underſtood to be, either a Repreſentation of the Church below, offering up prayers by her Paſtors, who are the mouths of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to God; or elſe a Repreſentation of the whole Church of Chriſt both in Heaven and Earth, joining together in their Doxologies and Praiſes to God for the Victories of the Lamb, and the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World by his Blood. And this latter ſeems to be warranted by the very next words, where it is ſaid, <hi>And they ſung a new ſong ſaying, Thou art worthy to take the Book, and to open the ſeals thereof; for thou waſt ſlain, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy blood, out of every kindred, and tongue, and people, and nation,</hi> v. 9.</p>
               <p>Nor will his other Text any more avail him, the 9th verſe which he quotes is nothing to the purpoſe, but I ſuppoſe he meant <hi>v.</hi> 4. where it is ſaid, That <hi>the ſmoak of the incenſe which came with the prayers of the Saints, aſcended up before God, out of the Angels hand.</hi> That by <hi>Angel,</hi> here, we are to underſtand <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Angel of the Covenant, they themſelves dare not deny. For the Angel that offered up the Prayers of the Saints, in <hi>v.</hi> 3. is called <hi>another Angel,</hi> different both in Nature and Office from thoſe other ſeven Angels, mentioned <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Scripture</hi> will not do his buſineſs, <hi>Antiquity</hi> he thinks will; for that, he ſays, is very expreſs in all the Doctrine of this Article. And as witneſſes of what he ſays, he names St. <hi>Cyril Alex.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> but without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52954:40"/> where to find their evidence recorded. Only in the Margin he tells us, That theſe Quotations may be ſeen cited at large in <hi>Nubes Teſtium.</hi> To all which I ſhall only return him this Anſwer, That all theſe Quotations may be ſeen anſwered at large in <hi>The Antiquity of the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> &amp;c. Firſt and Second Parts, and in another Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe intituled <hi>Veteres Vindicati,</hi> and in <hi>the Anſwer to the Compiler of</hi> Nubes Teſtium.</p>
               <p>For the Worſhip of Images: All that he offers to prove is no more than this, 1. <hi>That the making and having of Images in Churches or private Houſes, is not unlawful.</hi> 2. <hi>That ſome reſpect and veneration is due to them,</hi> both which we readily grant. But whether the Veneration and Honour that is due to them, ought to be called a Religious Honour? This, he tells us, is a Diſpute among Divines, but no matter of his Faith. But if this be no matter of his Faith, yet it is the only mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Debate between us and them in this point; and that it is the intention of his Church, from which he tells us, we are to take our meaſures as to the manner and external profeſſion of this Honour, hath been plainly made appear from the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Catechiſm <hi>ad Parochos,</hi> out of which this Article is gathered. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he doth not prove this, as indeed he doth not pretend to do, he is ſo far from vindicating the Doctrine of this Article, that he proves nothing at all. Not finding therefore any thing in his proofs that tends this way, I ſee no reaſon either to give my ſelf or the Reader a needleſs trouble, by a tedious examination of them. But if there be any thing wherein this Gentleman deſires a further ſatisfaction, I would recommend to his peruſal (if he be permitted to read them) two or three ſmall Treatiſes, which have lately been publiſhed upon this Subject, <hi>viz. A Diſcourſe concerning the Object of Religious Worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>An Anſwer to a Diſcourſe intituled, Papiſts proteſting againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Popery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>A Diſcourſe of the Worſhip of the bleſſed Virgin and the Saints,</hi> &amp;c. In which if he doth not find full ſatisfaction in this matter, I muſt diſpair of giving him any.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I believe that the power of Indulgences has been given and left by Chriſt to his Church, and that the uſe of them is very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to the Faithful.</q>
               <p>THE Council of <hi>Trent</hi> hath indeed aſſerted the Doctrine of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences,<note place="margin">Contin. Seſſ. 25. Decret. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ulg.</note> but not explain'd it. It damns all thoſe with an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema,</hi> who either affirm them to be unprofitable, or deny that the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52954:40"/> Church hath power to grant them. And all this without once letting us know what it means by Indulgences.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> in his Expoſition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would perſwade us, that all that is intended by Indulgences, is only a Relaxation of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Penance; and in complyance with him, the Vindicator here ſeems to be of the ſame opinion; for that is all that he advanceth for the Vindication of this Article.</p>
               <p>That ſuch a power as this was given and left by Chriſt to his Church, and that the due adminiſtration of it is very beneficial to the Faithful; we willingly grant. And that this godly Diſcipline was anciently uſed by the Church of Chriſt, we deny not. For, it is moſt certain, that it was the practiſe of the Church to enjoin penance to her offending Members, and if they did humbly and patiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thereunto, and prove penitent under them, ſhe did frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax ſome part of their penance. And if this be all that is intended by Indulgences, we ſhall not much quarrel with him about them; but, I am apt to think, that this Gentleman will find but few of his own Communion, who will be ſo ready to comply with him herein, as we are. There are two eminent perſons of his own Church, (if he has any acquaintance with them) <hi>viz. Greg. de Valentia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. de Valentia, de Indulg. c. 2. Bellarm. de Indulg. l. 1. c. 7.</note> and Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who, if he pleaſe to conſult them in this matter, will tell him another tale; The former will aſſure him, <hi>That this opinion dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not from that of the Hereticks,</hi> and makes Indulgences to be <hi>uſeleſs and dangerous things.</hi> And the latter will inform him, <hi>That if this opinion be true, then there will be no need of the Treaſure of the Church,</hi> and <hi>that Indulgences will be rather hurtful than profitable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is plain, That theſe Doctors had a far different notion of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, from that which the Vindicator here would perſwade us to. But it may be he will appeal from them as private Doctors; which if he do, whither will he ſend us to learn the Intention of the Church in this matter? The Council is ſilent, and gives us no Definition of the thing eſtabliſhed by it, and their chief Paſtor, who by the Bull of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. is made the ſole Interpreter of that Council, hath not by any publick Act, that we ever yet heard of, declared the ſence of the Council in this Decree. So that we are ſtill left either to ſpell out the intention of the Church in the Writings of their approved Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, or elſe to gueſs at it by the practices of their ſupreme Paſtors. As to the former, I have already given you a taſte, in two eminent Inſtances, and might, without any great trouble, furniſh you with many more. And for the latter, we need go no farther than the Tax of the Apoſtolick Chamber, and the <hi>Bullarium;</hi> in the former of which you may find Rates ſet, which being paid, an Indulgence may
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52954:41"/> be had for almoſt any kind of Sin. And in the latter you have an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſeveral Bulls of Indulgence by ſeveral Popes,<note place="margin">Vide Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Tom. I. p. 204. Tom. III. p. 74 Tom. IV. p. 86.</note> wherein a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and moſt plenary Remiſſion of Sins, and of all Sins is granted. Which certainly muſt amount to more than a bare Relaxation of ſome part of Canonical Penance, or elſe the poor People who pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed them, were horribly cheated both of their Money, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations. And if this be their notion of Indulgences, we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that any ſuch power was ever given or left by Chriſt to his Church, or that the uſe of it is at all beneficial to the Faithful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I acknowledge the Holy Catholick and Apostolick <hi>Roman</hi> Church, the Mother and Mistreſs of all other Churches; and I promiſe and ſwear true Obedience to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Prince of the Apostles, and Vicar of Jeſus Christ.</q>
               <p>THE Vindicator foreſeeing what Objection might be made to the Catholiciſm of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, begins his defence of this Article with an explanation of that Title, telling us, <hi>That as the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick or univerſal Church, ſignifies a Church conſiſting of all particular Churches united in the Communion of the ſame Faith and Sacraments, and ſubmiſſion to the ſame Eccleſiaſtical Government, the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is not the univerſal or Catholick Church, but a part of it; but as it imports a Church, which is univerſal in its influence, and by a ſingular privilege hath Authority over all other particular Churches, and is the Center of their Communion, the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>in this ſence is the Catholick or univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church, and is rightly ſtiled the Mother and Miſtreſs of all other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Notion of the Catholick Church is liable to as many, if not more, Objections than the other. For, 1. Where or by whom was ever the Catholick or Univerſal Church underſtood to import a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church endowed with univerſal Influence? 2. By what ſingular privilege hath any particular Church this univerſal Influence or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over all other particular Churches, ſeeing <hi>par in parem non habet imperium?</hi> 3. Whence had the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> this ſingular Privilege? Was it from God or of Men? If from God, let her produce her Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; if of Men, then thoſe who gave it were ſuperior to her to whom it was given; and certainly they did not give away their own Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority; and if not, then the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> inſtead of being a Mother and Miſtreſs, muſt own her ſelf to be a Daughter and Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to another. 4. When, where, or by whom was the Church
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52954:41"/> of <hi>Rome</hi> ever made or owned to be the Center of Catholick Union or Communion? Theſe Queſtions, I doubt, will not be quickly anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and till we are ſatisfied in theſe and ſome others, we ſhall hardly be perſwaded to ſubſcribe this Article. But why not? The Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor aſſures us, This was the Doctrine of the firſt Ages of the Church, and if ſo, then ought we rather to ſuſpect our own Judgments, than diſtruſt theirs.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That if this was the Doctrine of the firſt Ages, then Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great (who certainly was as Infallible as any other Pope) was mightily miſtaken. For, when <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> did arrogantly aſſume to himſelf the Title of <hi>Oecumenic,</hi> or, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop; Gregory</hi> ſharply reproves him for it; and tells him,<note place="margin">Gregor. l. 4. Epiſt. 38, 39. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>It is a New Name, a wicked, profane, inſolent Name, the general plague of the Church, a corruption of the Faith, againſt Canons, againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> Peter, <hi>and againſt God himſelf.</hi> And he farther adds, <hi>That never any Godly Man, never any of his Predeceſſors uſed thoſe Titles, and whoſoever doth or ſhall uſe them, is the very Fore-runner of Antichriſt.</hi> From whence it is plain, that before his time (which was about Six hundred Years after Chriſt) there never was any pretence made to it. But the Vindicator ſays there was, and that it was the Doctrine of the firſt Ages. Now whether <hi>Gregory</hi> or this Gentleman be in the right, is the thing in queſtion.</p>
               <p>The Vindicator, to make good his ground, urgeth us with the Authority of <hi>Irenaeus, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>adv. Haer.</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>That the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is the greateſt, and moſt ancient of all others, founded and eſtabliſhed there by the Two moſt Glorious Apoſtles,</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul.—<hi>'Tis neceſſary that every Church ſhould recurr to this, by reaſon of its more powerful principality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in that Book writeth againſt <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, Cerdon,</hi> and <hi>Marcion,</hi> who, contrary to the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, had deviſed certain ſtrange Hereſies; for trial whereof he appeals to thoſe Churches which the Apoſtles had planted, ſaying, <hi>The Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>firſt inſtructed by St.</hi> Paul, <hi>and afterward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by St.</hi> John, <hi>is a ſufficient witneſs of the Apoſtles learning.</hi> Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus <hi>being converted, and taught by the Apoſtles, inſtructed the Church of</hi> Smyrna, <hi>and all the Churches of</hi> Aſia <hi>follow it. Yet none of all theſe Churches ever allowed or received your ſtrange Doctrine. Yea the very wild Barbarous Nations, that have received the Faith of Chriſt at the Apoſtles hands, only by hearing, without any Book or Letter, if they ſhould hear of theſe Hereſies, they would ſtop their Ears.</hi> Here he appeals to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and all the Churches of <hi>Aſia:</hi> But then he adds, <hi>It would be too tedious to reckon up the Suceſſion of all Churches;</hi> and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52954:42"/> for that reaſon, being himſelf a Weſtern Biſhop, he appeals to that Church which was of Apoſtolical plantation in the <hi>Weſt, viz.</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Which he calls, <hi>the greateſt, moſt ancient,</hi> and <hi>known to all Men.</hi> Not <hi>the moſt Ancient of all other Churches,</hi> as the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator renders it, for it is well known, that <hi>Jeruſalem, Antioch,</hi> and ſeveral others were more ancient; but it was then the moſt famous Church in the <hi>Weſt.</hi> To this Church therefore he appeals, and thinks it neceſſary that in ſuch caſes all other Churches, <hi>i. e.</hi> all other Churches in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> ſhould do the ſame; and that for two Reaſons, 1. Becauſe of the more powerful principality. 2. Becauſe in this Church the Tradition of the Apoſtles hath ever been kept. The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of theſe, which is the principal, the Vindicator leaves out, and he had reaſon for it, for with that he could not ſerve the end he aim'd at. At that time the Tradition, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, was look'd upon to be the beſt Trial and Rule of Faith. Which Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in thoſe early days was exactly obſerved in <hi>Rome</hi> without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and for that reaſon was that Church had in Reverence and Eſtimation above others. And if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day did as faithfully keep the Traditions and Doctrine of the Apoſtles, as ſhe did then; we would never ſcruple to yield her that ſame Honour, that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> gives to the ancient Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he makes ſure not to forget the other reaſon, <hi>viz. The more powerful principality.</hi> And yet he will be as little able to avail himſelf of this as of the other; for the <hi>Principality</hi> which <hi>Irenaeus</hi> here means, is <hi>the Civil Dominion,</hi> and <hi>Temporal State</hi> of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was then the Imperial City. For if we conſider that this was in the Reign of <hi>Commodus</hi> the Emperor, who was an Heathen and a Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, we cannot imagine that the Church was then poſſeſſed of any <hi>powerful Principality.</hi> But as in every Province there was a <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> or chief City; ſo it was uſual with the Fathers to call the Church planted there, the chief or principal Church. And it is well known,<note place="margin">Concil. Conſtant. 6.</note> that upon that very account the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was, by a general Council, declared to have equal Privileges and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with the Patriarch of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that this was all the principality that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> dream'd of, will appear plainly; if we conſider, that when <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was angry with the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> for not celebrating the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> at the ſame time,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l. 5. c. 23.</note> and in the ſame manner as they did at <hi>Rome,</hi> and would have Excommunicated them for it; <hi>Irenaeus</hi> oppoſed his deſign, and ſharply reproved him as a diſturber of the Church's peace. Which certainly he would not have done, had he thought that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had been the Mother and Miſtreſs of all
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52954:42"/> Churches, and that Obedience to her Biſhop was neceſſary for every Chriſtian, in order to his Salvation.</p>
               <p>His next witneſs is <hi>Optatus Milevitanus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>adv. Parm.</hi> Where he ſpeaks of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair being erected at <hi>Rome,</hi> to the end that Unity might be preſerved, and that they are Schimaticks, and Sinners, and Sacrilegious, who ſet up themſelves in defiance againſt the Chair of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That <hi>Optatus</hi> there writes againſt <hi>Parmenianus</hi> the <hi>Donatiſt.</hi> Now the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were a certain Sect of Chriſtians, broken off from the Unity of the Catholick Church, confining it to a corner of <hi>Africa,</hi> where they themſelves dwelt; as our Neighbours of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion do now to <hi>Rome.</hi> To convince theſe People of their folly and madneſs, and to reduce them, if poſſible, into the boſom of the Church, <hi>Optatus</hi> doth (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> before him had done) appeal to thoſe Churches which were planted by the Apoſtles, and particularly to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> blaming them for departing from that Faith and Doctrine which was there kept and taught; and telling them that they could not belong to the Church of Chriſt, ſo long as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in a ſtate of ſeparation from that Church. He doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore require their Union and Communion with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as with the Mother and Miſtreſs of all other Churches, but as with the keeper of the Apoſtolick Faith. Nor doth he require them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> as the univerſal Head and Monarch of all Churches, for there is not one word to be found in all <hi>Optatus</hi> tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that way.</p>
               <p>His next Evidence is St. <hi>Cyprian, Epiſt.</hi> 40. <hi>There is one God, and one Chriſt, and one Church, and one Chair, founded upon</hi> Peter, <hi>by the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The deſign of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in this Epiſtle, is to give an account to thoſe to whom he wrote, of the Schiſmatical Sedition raiſed by <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciſſimus</hi> and Five other Presbyters, in the Church of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and againſt him their Biſhop; and by warning them againſt it to preſerve them in Peace and Unity. To that end he lays down theſe words, <hi>There is one God, &amp;c.</hi> And immediately adds, <hi>Another Altar cannot be ſet up, nor a new Prieſthood made, beſides that one Altar, and one Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. Whoſoever gathereth elſewhere, ſcattereth. It is Adulterous, it is Wicked, it is Sacrilegious, to make way for humane Inventions, by the viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a divine Conſtitution.</hi> Whence it is plain, That by <hi>the one Church</hi> here, he meant the One, Holy, Catholick, and Apoſtolick Church; and by <hi>the One Chair,</hi> the Epiſcopal Chair; Obedience whereunto preſerves Unity, and Diſobedience begets Schiſm and Sedition in the Church.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:52954:43"/>
               <p>But the force of his Argument lies here, That this <hi>One</hi> is founded upon <hi>Peter,</hi> and that not by any humane, but by divine Authority, <hi>Voce Domini,</hi> by the Word of the Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi> as the Margin of St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> directs us, thoſe Words of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> xvi. 18. where our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Thou art Peter, and upon this Rock will I build my Church, and the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, 1. That there are ſome who read theſe words of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> not <hi>ſuper Petrum,</hi> but <hi>ſuper petram,</hi> not upon <hi>Peter,</hi> but upon <hi>the Rock;</hi> not upon <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon, but upon his profeſſion; or as others, upon Chriſt, who is the ſpiritual <hi>Rock,</hi> upon which St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was builded. But, 2. Suppoſe we ſhould grant that St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaks of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſon, what is this to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome?</hi> for it is granted by all, that after this time, he was firſt ſettled in the See of <hi>Antioch,</hi> but it is queſtioned by many, whether ever he was fixed in the See of <hi>Rome?</hi> Or if he was, why ſhould his Succeſſors in the latter place have a better Title to it, than thoſe in the firſt? But, 3. If we will ſuffer St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> to be his own Interpreter, he will ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clear the matter; where having occaſion to explain thoſe words of our Saviour to <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">St. Cypr. de Unitat. Eccleſ. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Oxon. p. 107.</note> he concludes, <hi>The reſt of the Apoſtles were the ſame that St.</hi> Peter <hi>was, being joined with him in the ſame fellowſhip of Honour and Power.</hi> Where it is plain, he gives no Supremacy to St. <hi>Peter</hi> over the reſt of the Apoſtles, much leſs did he intend any to his Succeſſors.</p>
               <p>But St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> muſt not eſcape thus, he is again preſſed to ſpeak in this Cauſe. For in his 73. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> ſaith the Vindicator, he hath theſe words, <hi>Chriſt gave this power to</hi> Peter, <hi>upon whom he built the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That this Epiſtle is an Anſwer to one ſent him by <hi>Jubaianus,</hi> concerning the Rebaptizing of Hereticks. Againſt which it is objected by <hi>Jubaianus, That we are not to enquire by whom a perſon is Baptized, ſince he that is Baptized may receive Remiſſion of Sins, if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> In anſwer to this Objection, St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> after he had for ſome time diſcourſed of the Faith of thoſe who are without the Church, and the Efficacy thereof, at laſt concludes, <hi>But it is manifeſt where and by whom that Remiſſion of Sins, which is given in Baptiſm, can be given. For the Lord firſt gave to</hi> Peter, <hi>upon whom he built his Church, and from whence he ſhows the Original of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, that Power, that whatſoever he ſhould looſe on Earth, ſhould be looſed in Heaven. And after the Reſurrection, he alſo ſpoke to the Apoſtles, ſaying,</hi> As my Father hath ſent me, ſo ſend I you; <hi>and when he had ſaid this he breathed on them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John xx. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſaid,</hi> Whoſoever Sins ye remit, they are remitted; and whoſoever Sins ye retain, they are retained. Where you ſee he joins St. <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the ſame fellowſhip of Honour and Power, with this only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52954:43"/> that it was given to St. <hi>Peter</hi> firſt, and afterwards to them all jointly. And at laſt he concludes, which was all that he aimed at. <hi>By this we underſtand both where and by whom Remiſſion of Sins in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm can be given,</hi> viz. <hi>In the Church, and by the Paſtors of the Church.</hi> And now what is all this to the Supremacy either of the Biſhop or Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he hath not yet done with St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> he muſt come upon the Stage again to juſtifie what he ſaith, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55. where we find theſe words, <hi>They are bold to carry Letters from ſchiſmatical and profane Perſons to the Chair of</hi> Peter, <hi>and the principal Church, from whence the Prieſtly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity hath its riſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In anſwer whereunto, it may not be amiſs to give you a ſhort Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the whole matter: The Story is this; <hi>Feliciſſimus</hi> and Five other Presbyters with him, had made an horrible Schiſm in the Church of <hi>Carthage,</hi> contending for the reception both of Hereticks and Apoſtates, into the Church, without any form of Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline. Theſe were oppoſed by St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> of whoſe Oppoſition they were ſo impatient, that at laſt they proceeded, contrary to all Rule and Order, to chuſe a new Biſhop, and fix'd upon one <hi>Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Hereupon St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls a Council of <hi>African</hi> Biſhops, in which the cauſe was heard, and theſe Schiſmaticks cenſured. This ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed their turbulent and unquiet Minds, that they reſolve to carry the matter to <hi>Rome;</hi> and accordingly <hi>Feliciſſimus</hi> and others of the Party were ſent with Letters from their mock-Biſhop <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> to <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> (And this is <hi>the carrying of Letters to St.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<hi>'s Chair,</hi> &amp;c. that St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> here ſpeaks of.) So ſoon as they were come there, and had made known their buſineſs, <hi>Cornelius,</hi> by Letters, acquaints St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> with it; and he in this Epiſtle returns him an anſwer.</p>
               <p>Whence we may Note, That it was not St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Biſhops of <hi>Africa,</hi> but the ſchiſmatical mock-Biſhop <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and his adherents, that appealed to <hi>Rome.</hi> Nor doth <hi>Cornelius</hi> take upon him to cite St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops to appear, and anſwer the matter before him; but only in a Brotherly and friendly manner, by letters acquaints him with it. And ſo far was St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> from owning any Superiority or power in the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop over him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the Biſhops of <hi>Africa,</hi> that the higheſt titles that he gives him in this whole Epiſtle, are only <hi>Brother,</hi> and <hi>Moſt dear Brother.</hi> He alſo takes upon him ſharply to reprove him, for his puſillanimity and lowneſs of Spirit, at the threats and menaces of thoſe wicked Men; He inſtructs him what he ſhould do, and directs him how to behave himſelf towards them. He acquaints him that the cauſe was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52954:44"/> already judged in <hi>Africa,</hi> and as good as tells him that he ought not to meddle with it: <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it is determined by all of us, and it is both equal and juſt, that every ones Cauſe ſhould be heard where the crime was committed. Every Paſtor hath his portion of the Flock, which he ought to rule and govern, and to give an account thereof</hi> (not at <hi>Rome,</hi> but in Heaven, not to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> but to Chriſt) <hi>to the Lord. Thoſe therefore who are under our Juriſdiction ought not to run about, (i. e.</hi> they ought not to apply themſelves to any foreign Juriſdiction) <hi>but to plead their cauſe there, where they may have both Accuſers and Witneſſes of their Crime.</hi> So far was St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> from owning any Superiority or Power in the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop over himſelf and the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops.</p>
               <p>But he calls the Church of <hi>Rome, The Chair of Peter,</hi> and <hi>the principal Church.</hi> 'Tis true he doth ſo, but that he never intended thereby to aſcribe unto her a Superiority and Juriſdiction over all other Churches, I take to be very plain from the account I have now given you of his ſentiments out of this very Epiſtle. But having already accounted for theſe expreſſions, I am not willing to repeat the ſame thing over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but ſhall rather referr you to what hath been already ſaid.</p>
               <p>His next evidence is <hi>Greg. Naz. Hom. de Cre. Epiſt. Doar. We do not contemn nor revile that great Paſtor, who governs that magnificent City; we know him to be honourable, we acknowledge him the Head — we deſire he will ſhew himſelf an indulgent and tender Father, and diligently take care of the whole Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, That if by <hi>Head,</hi> he mean <hi>the chief Ruler</hi> and <hi>Governour;</hi> we grant that he is ſo in his own province, and that he take care of the whole Church of that Province, committed to his Charge, we think is his duty, and with <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> we heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that he may do it,<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Caeſareen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Chryſoſt. ad pop. Antioche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Hom. 3.</note> and do it diligently. And that this Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meant no more than this, may plainly appear from what he ſaith of the Church of <hi>Caeſarea: It is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in a manner the Mother of all Churches, and the whole Chriſtian Common-wealth ſo embraceth and beholdeth it, as the Circle embraceth and beholdeth the Center.</hi> Thus <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſtiled, <hi>the Mother of all Churches;</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> calls <hi>Antioch, the Head of the World.</hi> Now as theſe Churches are called <hi>Mother Churches,</hi> becauſe the Cities in which they were planted were the <hi>Mother Cities</hi> of thoſe Provinces; ſo for the ſame reaſon, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is oftentimes called <hi>the Chief, the Principal,</hi> and <hi>the Mother Church,</hi> becauſe that City, was the <hi>Metropolis</hi> or <hi>Head-City</hi> of the <hi>Weſt.</hi> And as the Biſhops of thoſe Churches may be, and oftentimes are called the <hi>Chief Rulers</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo likewiſe and no otherwiſe, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſometimes ſtiled the <hi>Head</hi> i. e. <hi>the chief Governour of the Church.</hi> And that by the <hi>whole Church</hi> here, we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52954:44"/> are to underſtand no more, but only the whole Church of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, <hi>Polydor. Virgil,</hi> explaining thoſe words of St. <hi>Cyprian, The Chair of</hi> Peter,<note place="margin">Polydor. Virgil. de Inventor. rerum, l 4.</note> 
                  <hi>the principal Church from which the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood firſt began,</hi> thus writeth, <hi>Leſt any man hereby deceive himſelf, it cannot in any other wiſe be ſaid, that the Order of Prieſthood grew firſt from the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>unleſs we underſtand it only within</hi> Italy. <hi>For it is clear and out of queſtion, that Prieſthood was orderly appointed at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>long before</hi> Peter <hi>ever came to</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>To this I might add, That every Biſhop, may be called <hi>the Biſhop of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church;</hi> becauſe it is his duty to take care not only of his own Flock, but of the whole Church of God. As alſo that this Title, <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> hath been given to ſeveral godly Biſhops, who were never Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor ever dreamt that any Supremacy of power over all <hi>other</hi> Churches, was thereby conferred either upon him, or them. But I am not willing to enter farther into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie than the Vindicator leads me; And to this Evidence of his, I think, enough hath been ſaid, to ſhow that it will not much avail him.</p>
               <p>His next witneſs is St. <hi>Chryſoſtome l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Sacerd. c.</hi> 1. <hi>For what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon did Chriſt ſhed his Blood? Certainly to purchaſe thoſe ſheep, the care of which he committed to</hi> Peter <hi>and his Succeſſors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole force of his Argument, if he can frame any out of theſe words, muſt be, That the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is the true Succeſſor to St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Which, if we ſhould grant him, I do not ſee how it would thence follow, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Supream Paſtor, Head and Governor of the Catholick Church; For if St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was not ſo, he cannot have it by Succeſſion from him.<note place="margin">De Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Eccleſ. Edit. Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. p. 107. Greg. l. 4. Ep. 38.</note> Now St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Apoſtles were the ſame that St.</hi> Peter <hi>was, being joined in the ſame fellowſhip of Honour and Power.</hi> And their own Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, Peter, <hi>the Apoſtle, is</hi> (not the Head, but) <hi>the chief Member of the holy univerſal Church.</hi> Paul, Andrew <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>what are they elſe, but the Heads of ſeveral Nations? Yet notwithſtanding under one Head (viz.</hi> Chriſt) <hi>they are all members of the Church. And to ſpeak in ſhort, The Saints before the Law, the Saints under the Law, the Saints in the time of Grace, all accompliſhing the Lord's Body, are placed among the Members of the Church. And there was never any one yet, that would have him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf called</hi> the Univerſal Biſhop. So that as <hi>Paul, Andrew</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were Heads of the Church, in like manner, and no otherwiſe, was St. <hi>Peter</hi> Head of the Church. If therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> was, then they were all ſo too, for they were all equal; and what a confuſion that would be, let the Vindicator judge.</p>
               <p>To this may be added, That if St. <hi>Peter</hi> was really the Prince of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52954:45"/> the Apoſtles, and Head of the Church conſtituted by Chriſt, St. <hi>Paul</hi> certainly was very much to blame,<note place="margin">Gal. ii. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to withſtand him to the face,</hi> as he did. And it muſt be a very great Arrogance and preſumption in him, to ſay, <hi>That in nothing he was behind the very chiefeſt Apoſtles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. xij. 11. Gal. ij. 7.</note> Or to ſhare Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction with him, ſaying, <hi>That the Goſpel of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion was committed unto him, as the Goſpel of the Circumciſion was unto Peter.</hi> But St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Epiſt. ad Galat. c. ii.</note> whoſe Authority he ſo much depends upon, will tell him, <hi>That</hi> Paul <hi>had no need of</hi> Peter<hi>'s help, nor did he want his voice, but was equal unto him in Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides all this, One may be ſaid to ſucceed another, either becauſe he poſſeſſeth the ſame place that he did; or becauſe he teacheth the ſame Doctrine, and with the ſame diligence that he did. Now the former of theſe will not be enough to make any one the true Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alphonſ. contra Haereſ. l. 1. c. 9.</note> for as their own <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro</hi> ſaith, <hi>Though it be matter of Faith to believe the true Succeſſor of St.</hi> Peter <hi>is the Supream Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the whole Church; yet are we not bound, by the ſame Faith to believe, that</hi> Leo <hi>or</hi> Clement (<hi>though Biſhops of</hi> Rome) <hi>are the true Succeſſors of St.</hi> Peter. And yet this is the Succeſſion they ſo much boaſt of; and if this be it,<note place="margin">Diſt. 40. Multi.</note> the ſame St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> will inform him, <hi>That it is not the Chair that makes the Biſhop, but it is the Biſhop that makes the Chair. Neither is it the place that Halloweth the Man, but it is the Man that Halloweth the place.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſt. 40. Non eſt facile.</note> And St. <hi>Jerome</hi> will tell him, <hi>They are not always the Children of Holy Men, that ſit in the rooms of Holy Men.</hi> Nor did theſe Holy Fathers ſpeak without Book, for <hi>the Scribes and Phariſees ſat in Moſes's Chair,</hi> Matth. xxiij. 2. And <hi>the Abomination of Deſolation ſhall ſtand in the holy Place,</hi> Matth. xxiv. 15. And <hi>the Man of Sin, as God, ſhall ſit in the Temple of God,</hi> 2 Theſ. ij. 3, 4. As the firſt of theſe did Succeed <hi>Moſes</hi> in place, but not in Doctrine; ſo the two other ſhall ſucceed Chriſt and his Apoſtles. And thus Pope <hi>Liberius,</hi> though an <hi>Arian</hi> Heretick; and Pope <hi>Coeleſtinus,</hi> though a <hi>Neſtorian;</hi> and Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> though a <hi>Monothelite;</hi> may be ſaid to ſucceed St. <hi>Peter</hi> in place, though not in Doctrine. But will the Vindicator ſay, or can he imagine, that St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> meant, That Chriſt ſhed his Blood to purchaſe a Church, and when he had done, committed the care of it to ſuch Succeſſors of St. <hi>Peter</hi> as theſe were?</p>
               <p>His next is St. <hi>Jerome, Epiſt.</hi> 57, and 58. <hi>ad Damaſum,</hi> whoſe words are thus rendered by him,<note place="margin">Ego nullum primum, niſi Chriſtum, ſequens, Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudini tuae, <hi>i. e.</hi> Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drae, Petri Communione conſocior.</note> 
                  <hi>I following no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leader but Chriſt, am in Communion with your Holineſs, i. e. with the Chair of</hi> Peter, <hi>&amp;c. And, I cry aloud, Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is in Communion with the Chair of</hi> Peter, <hi>is mine.</hi> Which may better be Tranſlated thus, <hi>I following no firſt Man, but only Chriſt, am joined, as a Fellow in Communion unto thy Bleſſedneſs,</hi> i. e. <hi>to</hi> Peter<hi>'s Chair.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:52954:45"/>
               <p>Whence we may obſerve, 1. That St. <hi>Jerome</hi> doth not acknowledge any firſt, head, or chief in the Church, no not the Pope himſelf, but only Chriſt. 2. That he doth not ſubmit himſelf as a Vaſſal or Subject to the Pope, but doth conſociate himſelf in Communion with him. 3. That it is not only with him, but with St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Chair. And what he meaneth by St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, he afterwards explains, when he comes to give a reaſon of this his Addreſs. Where he tells us, <hi>The Foxes deſtroy the Vineyard of Chriſt, ſo that among theſe broken Ciſterns, that have no Water, it is hard to underſtand, where that ſealed Fountain and incloſed Garden is.</hi> Therefore he thought it good to conſult St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, and that Faith which was commended by the Apoſtles Mouth. So that it was not St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor in place, but in Doctrine, that he applied himſelf unto. Now if we conſider that the Age in which St. <hi>Jerome</hi> lived did mightily abound with Hereticks, we cannot think it ſtrange that he ſhould forſake the company of thoſe wicked Men, and join himſelf in communion with thoſe, who then held that Faith intire, which they impugned. But if you ask me, why ſhould he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addreſs himſelf to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> than any other? The anſwer is ready, he had received his Chriſtianity at <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In vita Hieron.</note> he had been educated there from his youth, he was a Prieſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> and had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time been Secretary to this very <hi>Damaſus.</hi> All which conſidered, it is no wonder, if he had a particular kindneſs for that See. Now what is all this to that univerſal power which the Pope at this day claims to have over the whole Church of God? Should the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor follow St. <hi>Jerome</hi>'s Example, and, and in his Addreſs call the Pope his Fellow, I doubt it would not be very welcome.</p>
               <p>And that St. <hi>Jerome</hi> meant no more than is here explained, will plainly appear, if we conſider what account he made at other times of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, when he found abuſes and errors maintained in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he cries out, <hi>Si Authoritas quaeritur,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Epiſt. ad Evagrium</note> 
                  <hi>If we ſeek for Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that of the World is greater than that of the City (viz.</hi> Rome) <hi>Whereever there is a Biſhop, whether it be at</hi> Rome, <hi>or at</hi> Tanais, <hi>or at</hi> Engubium, <hi>he is of equal Merit, and equal Prieſthood. The power of Riches, and the humility of Poverty, cannot make a Biſhop either higher or lower. All Biſhops are the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His next Evidence is, St. <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 92. <hi>ad Innocentium Papam,</hi> whoſe words are not well tranſlated by him; The words of the Epiſtle are theſe, <hi>In the great dangers of the infirm Members of Chriſt we beſeech you to uſe your Paſtoral diligence. For, there is a new Hereſie, and too perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Tempeſt raiſed by the Enemies of the Grace of Chriſt, who by their wicked Diſputations endeavour to take from us the Lords Prayer.</hi> And then
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52954:46"/> giving him an account, what that Hereſie and Tempeſt was, he at laſt concludes, <hi>But we hope, the Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt aſſiſting, who deigns to govern thee conſulting him, and to hear thee praying to him; thoſe who think ſo perverſely and perniciouſly will yield to the Authority of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, drawn from the Authority of holy Scriptures, that ſo we may rather rejoice in their Correction, than ſorrow for their Deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the better underſtanding hereof, we are to conſider, That this Epiſtle was ſent to Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> not by St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> alone, but by the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Council, in which he preſided, and in which the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Hereſie had been conſidered and cenſured, as it had been before in the Council of <hi>Carthage.</hi> And the deſign of their writing, as appears by the whole tenour of the Epiſtle, was not to beg his confirmation of what they had done, but to acquaint him with what they had done; and to deſire him to take the ſame paſtoral care, and uſe the ſame diligence to diſcountenance that Hereſie in his Province, as they had done in theirs.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 95. ad Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</note> For St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in another Epiſtle tells him, <hi>We have heard that there are ſome even in</hi> Rome <hi>it ſelf,</hi> (where <hi>Pelagius</hi> long lived) <hi>who for divers cauſes are favourable to him; ſome there are who report that you perſwade them ſo to be, but more who believe that he is cleared from that Hereſie by the Eaſtern Biſhops.</hi> And therefore they expected that he ſhould not only clear himſelf of that ſuſpicion, but alſo unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his people as to the Tranſactions in this matter in the Eaſt.</p>
               <p>This was the deſign of this Epiſtle, as indeed it was of all thoſe Communicatory Letters, which in thoſe days were ſo frequent, when any matter of great importance happened in the Church; which were things of great uſe, and no ſmall advantage then, for thereby Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Communion was preſerved, warning was given of any approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing danger, and the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church awakened to provide againſt it. Nor were theſe Epiſtles ſent to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> only, but to other Biſhops alſo. To this purpoſe we meet with another Epiſtle to <hi>Hilarius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Poitiers</hi> in <hi>France,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 94.</note> written in the ſame ſtile, and to whom he makes his Addreſs in words to the ſame effect, as he did to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> for thus he directs it, To <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius</hi> our moſt bleſſed Lord, and reverend Brother and Fellow-Biſhop in the truth of Chriſt. In this Epiſtle he tells him, That a new Hereſie, an Enemy to the Grace of Chriſt, was endeavoured to be ſet up; and having given him an account what it was he deſires him to uſe his paſtoral care and diligence to ſuppreſs it.</p>
               <p>But that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and the Fathers in the <hi>Numidian</hi> Council never dreamt of any power or authority either in him or the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other Biſhop, over them and all other Churches, we need no other Evidence, than the Acts of this very Council. In which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:52954:46"/> we find this Decree made,<note place="margin">Concil. Milevitan. Can. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>If they have a mind to appeal from their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, let them not appeal but only to the Councils of</hi> Africa, <hi>or to the Primates of their own Provinces. But if they ſhall make their Appeals beyond the Seas</hi> (i. e. to <hi>Rome) let no Man in</hi> Africa <hi>receive them into Communion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Carthag. 6. Can. 92.</note> The ſame was alſo decreed in the <hi>African</hi> Council; and the reaſons of it are expreſſed at large in the Epiſtle of that Council to Pope <hi>Coeleſtinus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I conſidered the Proofs brought for Vindication of this important Article, and having laid them in the Balance, have found them all too light. But he hath yet one Authority more, not from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, but from a Modern Author, and one of our own, <hi>viz.</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and learned Doctor <hi>Sherlock.</hi> This, I confeſs,<note place="margin">Diſc. of the Knowl. of Jeſ. Chriſt, <hi>p. 163.</hi>
                  </note> I did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect; for who would ever have thought that that worthy Gentleman ſhould ever have been brought upon the Stage as an Advocate for the Popes Supremacy. But this Gentleman thinks, that whatſoever is ſaid by any Body touching Order and Diſcipline in the Church, and the neceſſity of ſubjection and obedience to the Governors thereof, muſt needs terminate in the Pope, who, they ſay, is the Center of Unity; though in ſo ſaying, they do but beg the Queſtion. For we can with great cheerfulneſs and willingneſs ſubſcribe to all that Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> hath there ſaid, and yet think our ſelves never a jot the more obliged <hi>to ſwear Obedience to the Biſhop of</hi> Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article_of_faith">
               <q>I undoubtedly receive and profeſs all other things delivered, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, and declared by the Sacred Canons and General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and particularly by the Holy Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and I condemn, reject and anathematize all things contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and all Hereſies whatſoever the Church hath condemned, rejected and Anathematized.</q>
               <p>THIS, he tells us, is the conſequence of that Doctrine of our Creed, wherein we profeſs to believe <hi>The Holy Catholick Church.</hi> But how comes this to be the conſequence of that Doctrine? Very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally; for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>this Catholick Church.</hi> 'Tis boldly ſaid, but how doth this appear? Very plainly, for there are the greateſt reaſons in the world to believe it. So that now we muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhow our ſelves to be unreaſonable Men, or elſe of neceſſity we muſt ſubſcribe this Article. But are we obliged to take all this upon the bare word of the Vindicator? May we not look into, and conſider theſe reaſons, whether they be ſo great and good as he talks of? Surely we may, or elſe he would not have expoſed them to publick view. Well then let us ſee what they are.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:52954:47"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>R.</hi> 1.</note>His firſt Reaſon is, <hi>Becauſe the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>has continued in a viſible Succeſſion of Paſtors from Chriſt's time till now.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note>The point of Succeſſion hath been already conſidered, and, I think, enough ſaid to ſhow the unreaſonableneſs of that Plea. But becauſe he ſo much inſiſts upon the viſible Succeſſion of Perſons in the ſame place, let me ask him two or three queſtions. 1. Who was the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> next by Succeſſion to <hi>Peter?</hi> who the ſecond? who the third? who the fourth? For in this they are not yet well agreed. Some ſay <hi>Linus</hi> was the ſecond, others ſay <hi>Clemens.</hi> Some ſay <hi>Anacletus</hi> was the third, others ſay <hi>Clemens.</hi> Some ſay <hi>Anacletus</hi> was the fourth, others ſay <hi>Anacletus.</hi> 2. Whether an Heretick, or a Necromancer, or a Blaſphemer being in the Chair, be the true Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter?</hi> and if not, whether that do not break the Line of Succeſſion? 3. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when there was no Pope for ſome Years, the viſible ſucceſſion of Paſtors in that Church was not diſcontinued? 4. When there were three or four Popes at one and the ſame time, and not known who was the true one, there was not an apparent interruption of their viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſucceſſion?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>R.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>never went out of, or ſeparated from any precedent Church, but all other ſeparate Congregations have gone out from her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note>If by going out of, or ſeparating from any precedent Church, he mean departing from the Doctrine, and renouncing the Diſcipline of that Church; which he muſt do, if he mean any thing; then we ſay, That in both theſe the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath gone out of, and ſeparated from the Primitive Church, as hath been plainly made appear in this Diſcourſe. And that thoſe who ſeparate from her, do not ſeparate from the Church, but from the corruptions of that particular Church; which they are well warranted to do by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who having told the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> That there can be no fellowſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Righteouſneſs and Unrighteouſneſs; no Communion between Light and Darkneſs; no Concord between Chriſt and Belial; nor any Agreement between <hi>the Temple of God</hi> and <hi>Idols;</hi> at laſt thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs, <hi>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you,</hi> 2 Cor. vi. 14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath ſent Apoſtles abroad, and converted all Heathen Nations to Chriſtianity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>R.</hi> 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note>This is ſo notoriouſly falſe, and ſo well known to be ſo, to every one that hath but looked into Church Hiſtory, in which we have an account of moſt Nations, when and by whom they were converted; that I cannot but wonder at the Confidence of this Gentleman in aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52954:47"/> it. But if we ſhould grant him this, would it thence follow, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Catholick Church? Might I not as well reaſon thus, The Scribes and Phariſees compaſs Sea and Land to gain Proſelytes, therefore thoſe two Sects were the whole Jewiſh Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Becauſe the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>in publick Synods has oppoſed and condemn'd in all Ages ariſing Hereſies.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>R.</hi> 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This is as notoriouſly falſe as the former,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> as is plain from thoſe two Inſtances of the <hi>Milevitan,</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Councils, which I mentioned in the precedent Article; and might eaſily be made more plainly appear by Inſtances of other Councils, which have not only not deſired, but rejected the Authority of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when it would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. But the thing is ſo well known that I ſhall not need to do it.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all the Reaſons he alledgeth, and theſe, he tells us, are the greateſt in the World. If they be ſo, the World is in an ill condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and men, like the great <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> may be ſent now to graze amongſt the Beaſts of the Field, having loſt their Reaſon.</p>
               <p>I am of Doctor <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s mind, <hi>That Men cannot own the Authority and Government of Chriſt, till they ſubmit to the publick Inſtructions, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Diſcipline of the Church.</hi> But what is all this to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s being the Catholick Church? 'Tis plain he doth not ſay it, and I am well aſſured he never meant it.</p>
               <p>I ſubſcribe to St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Judgment, <hi>That particular Councils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Bapt. cont. Don. l. 2. c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt yield to General, becauſe the whole is deſervedly preferred before a part.</hi> But did ever any Council, either particular or General, decree a part to be the whole, or a particular Church to be the Catholick Church? If not, I do not ſee how the Vindicator can avail himſelf of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, nor for what end he did produce it.</p>
               <p>Thus it appears, that the New Articles in Pope <hi>Pius</hi> his Creed, are neither agreeable to Scripture, nor the Sence of the Primitive Fathers. And for that reaſon we cannot ſubſcribe to this laſt Article.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="closer">
               <head>THE CLOSE.</head>
               <p>TO cloſe up his Vindication, he undertakes to anſwer ſome Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ours againſt theſe New Articles, which, how well he hath done, I ſhall now examine.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles knew beſt what was to be believed;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> ſince therefore none of theſe Articles are in their Creed, they ought not to be impoſed on us as Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith.</p>
               <p>To this he anſwers,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Apoſtles Creed is a Summary of the principal Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, but doth not contain all that is of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I reply, That a thing may be ſaid to be of Faith two ways,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reply.</note> either
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52954:48"/> abſolutely or occaſionally. 1. Abſolutely, <hi>i. e.</hi> in, and for its ſelf, when by its own nature, and God's primary intention, it is an eſſential part of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; ſuch an one as Teachers in the Church cannot, without mortal Sin, omit to teach the Learners; ſuch an one as is intrinſecal to the Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man; and not only plainly revealed by God, and ſo a certain Truth, but alſo commanded to be preached to all Men, and to be diſtinctly believed by all, and ſo a neceſſary Truth. Of this kind there are two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> Such as are neceſſary to be believed, or ſuch as are neceſſary to be done, and of the former of theſe it is that we ſpeak, when we ſay, That the Apoſtles Creed contains all neceſſary Matters of Faith. 2. A thing may be ſaid to be of Faith only occaſionally, <hi>i. e.</hi> when it is not ſo in, and for its ſelf, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is joined with others which are neceſſary to be believed, and for the ſake of that Authority by which it is delivered. Of this ſort there are multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Verities contained in the Holy Scriptures, as for Inſtance, That <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> was a Prieſt of the Courſe of <hi>Abia,</hi> that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Aaron,</hi> that <hi>Cyrenius</hi> was Governor of <hi>Syria,</hi> that <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> was the <hi>Roman</hi> Deputy, that <hi>Paul</hi> left his Cloak at <hi>Troas.</hi> Theſe are all Truths and Objects of Faith, becauſe they are found in the divine Revelation; but they are not ſuch Truths as the Paſtors of the Church are bound to teach their Flock, or their Flock bound to know and remember. For it would be no crime to be ignorant of theſe, or to believe the contrary, if I did not know that they were delivered in Holy Scripture. When therefore we ſpeak of Matters of Faith contained in the Creed, we mean all neceſſary points of meer Belief, and of ſuch we ſay it is a perfect Summary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No,</hi> ſaith the Vindicator, <hi>for it doth not contain all that is in the Scripture, and yet all that is there is of Divine Inſpiration and of Faith.</hi> We grant it, but all things that are there are not equally of Faith; many of them are not abſolute and neceſſary, but only occaſional and accidental Objects of Faith; as I have already ſhown.</p>
               <p>As for Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, we acknowledge them to be great Myſteries of our Religion, but they are not points of meer Faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not within the queſtion. That the Scripture is the word of God, and that ſuch and ſuch Books are Canonical, depends upon another Evidence; by which we muſt be convinc'd that they are ſo, before we can give a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal aſſent to the Articles of the Creed; becauſe they are all taken out of theſe Books and our belief of them built upon that Authority. The Belief there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of this being neceſſarily antecedent to the belief of the other, it would have been a very abſurd and prepoſterous thing to have made that an Article of our Creed. As for the 39 Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded only as Articles of Communion, not as Articles of Faith; and therefore the Objection doth not reach them. And as for the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſian</hi> Creed, they are only explications of the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſame, and no other Faith, but what is contained in that. This I think, may ſuffice to ſhow, That he hath not yet anſwered that Objection. But if the Vindicator deſire yet further ſatisfaction in this point; I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to him (if he be allowed to read ſuch Books) the fourth Chapter of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Book, intituled, <hi>The Religion of Proteſtants a ſafe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:52954:48"/> way to Salvation,</hi> and another little Treatiſe printed at <hi>London</hi> the laſt year, intituled, <hi>The Pillar and Ground of Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the particulars in this profeſſion were not undoubtedly believed by all,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> before the Decrees were made at <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he anſwers, <hi>Suppoſe they were not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither was the Canon of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which the Church of</hi> England <hi>receives, undoubtedly believed by all in the primitive times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This may be allow'd to be a good anſwer to that Objection,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reply.</note> but that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is his own, it is none of ours; Our Objection is this, <hi>That not one of all theſe twelve new Articles in Pope</hi> Pius<hi>'s Creed was ever received as an Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith by the Primitive Church. And to this he anſwers nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theres no Authority upon Earth can make a new Article of Faith.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object. Anſw.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To this he anſwers, <hi>That there is an Authority, which can declare a thing to be of Faith, which was not before expreſly ſo believed by all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This we willingly grant, but this doth not anſwer the Objection;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reply.</note> for we do not queſtion the Church's power to declare a thing to be of Faith, which before was dubious, or not expreſly believed by all. But we ſay, That there is no ſuch Authority in the Church, as to make that to be of Faith, which really was not ſo before, <hi>i. e.</hi> to make a new Article of Faith. And to this he returns not one word of Anſwer.</p>
               <p>This Authority can declare only ſuch points,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> as may be warranted by Holy Scripture, and ſuch as theſe are the ſubject of the XXXIX Articles; but as for Pope <hi>Pius</hi>'s Creed, it is but the Invention of Men.</p>
               <p>For Anſwer hereunto, he referrs us to what he hath ſaid in his Book,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he ſaith, he hath ſhewed, <hi>That all the Articles of this Creed are founded upon Scripture, and the Authority of the moſt eminent Men in the Primitive Church.</hi> And farther faith, <hi>That the</hi> XXXIX. <hi>Articles are not ſo expreſs in Scripture, as theſe of Pope</hi> Pius.</p>
               <p>Whether there be any Truth in the firſt part of his Anſwer,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reply.</note> as he referrs us to his Book, ſo I ſhall referr you to the Anſwer given to it in theſe Papers. And to the latter part of his Anſwer, it may be a ſufficient Reply, to remind him of what he hath been often told, That the XXXIX Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not propounded as Articles of Faith, but as Articles of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, nor is the Belief of them required of all upon pain of Damnation, as theſe of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> are; and therefore there is not ſo much danger in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance or non-complyance with the one, as with the other. Whether theſe Articles of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> be founded upon Scripture, hath been one part of the queſtion between us, and therefore for ſatisfaction in this point, I ſhall refers you to what hath been ſaid upon that Subject on both ſides.</p>
               <p>Thus have I conſidered the Vindicator's Anſwers to ſome Objections, which he thought fit to encounter with; and how well he hath acquitted himſelf therein, I ſhall now leave it to the ingenuous Reader to judge between us.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
